Agricultural Sciences & Natural Resources

ADMISSION

Requirements for admission into the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources (CASNR) are consistent with general University admission requirements (one unit equals one high school year): 4 units of English, 4 units of mathematics, 3 units of natural sciences, 3 units of social studies, and 2 units of foreign language. Students must also meet performance requirements (ACT composite of 20 or higher OR combined SAT score of 950 or higher OR rank in the top one-half of graduating class; transfer students must have a 2.0 (on a 4.0 scale) cumulative grade point average and 2.0 on most recent term of attendance.

Admission Deficiencies/Removal of Deficiencies

Students who are admitted to CASNR with core course deficiencies must remove these deficiencies within the first 30 credit hours at UNL, or within the first calendar year at UNL, whichever takes longer, excluding foreign languages. Students have up to 60 credit hours to remove foreign language deficiencies. College-level course work taken to remove deficiencies may be used to meet degree requirements in CASNR.

Deficiencies in the required entrance subjects can be removed by completion of specified courses in the University or by correspondence.

The Office of Admissions, Alexander Building (east entrance), City Campus, provides information to new students on how deficiencies can be removed.

ADVISING

Academic Advising

Undergraduate Advising: Dann E. Husmann

Advising activities are coordinated by the Associate Dean for Student Affairs in the CASNR Dean’s Office. Each student in the College is assigned a faculty or professional adviser to assist in career planning, implementing, and completing academic programs. Assignments are made so that students will be working with an adviser who shares their academic interest. Students are encouraged to visit with their faculty or professional adviser about their career interests and development opportunities. Students may change their college, degree, and/or adviser. Such changes must be initiated in 103 Agricultural Hall.

Student Responsibility

Students are ultimately responsible for fulfilling all the requirements of the curriculum in which they are enrolled. Students are also responsible for initiating advising contacts and preparing for advising sessions. The mentoring relationship between academic advisers and students is confidential and is strengthened by advisers’ listening with empathy.

Students are expected to take responsibility for successful university experiences and effective advising sessions by:

1. Participating in New Student Enrollment and priority registration programs;

2. Scheduling appointments with advisers well in advance of priority registration and at other times as needed;

3. Identifying class choices from requirements of the selected program;

4. Identifying questions to address in advising sessions;

5. Informing advisers of any special needs, deficiencies or barriers that might affect academic success;

6. Following academic policies and procedures and meeting academic calendar deadlines (e.g. registration, fee payment, degree audit, filing for degree, etc.);

7. Knowing and completing degree or program requirements;

8. Monitoring their progress toward meeting degree requirements by maintaining a copy of their academic records and seeking assistance to resolve any errors or questions;

9. Acting on recommendations to seek assistance from the various student support services provided by the University; and

10. Achieving requirements for BS candidacy prior to senior year.

ACADEMIC PROGRAMS & POLICIES

Academic Load

CASNR students may register for up to 18 credit hours per semester. Written permission must be obtained from the CASNR Dean to exceed the credit hour maximum and must be filed with an Override Authorization form at the time of registration. Students must be enrolled for 12 UNL credit hours to be considered full-time students. For recognition on the Dean’s List, these 12 UNL credit hours must be for a letter grade.

Course Exclusions & Restrictions

Not more than 12 hours of independent study.
Not more than 24 hours of Pass/No Pass grade option.
Not more than 60 hours from two-year colleges.
Not more than 90 hours from other four-year institutions.
Not more than 6 hours of non-UNL courses can be counted among the last 36 hours earned.
No credit toward the BS degree is allowed for MATH 100A.
No more than 10 semester hours of below C grades are transferable from colleges outside the NU system. Grades below C can only be applied to free electives.

Credit by Examination

Through study or experience that parallels a University of Nebraska–Lincoln course, a regularly enrolled University student may feel prepared to pass an examination on the course content of a specific course for credit in that course. To apply for credit, a student should:

1. Consult with the department head or designee.

2. Obtain a Credit by Examination Form at the Records Office, 107 Canfield Administration Building, 402-472-3649. Current enrollment in the University must also be verified.

3. Secure the approval signature from the department head, instructor, and the dean of the college. The Dean’s signature can be obtained in the 103 Agricultural Hall.

4. Secure the bursar’s receipt for payment of the appropriate fee per course for credit by examination. Currently, the fee is one-half the resident tuition rate.

5. Present the completed form to the instructor designated by the department head. The instructor will give the examination and report the results on the Credit by Examination Form to the Admissions Office, Alexander Building, 402-472-0130.

Examination for credit through UNL departments may be taken only by currently enrolled students. A student is not permitted to receive credit by examination in a course which is a prerequisite for a course already taken unless the course and its prerequisites cover essentially different subject matter.

The College also gives credit for the subject and general examinations of the College Level Examination Program (CLEP) and the Advanced Placement (AP) Program administered by the College Entrance Examination Board. See the CASNR Associate Dean, 103 Agricultural Hall, for current policy regarding CLEP and AP examinations.

Dual Degrees

Dual Degrees from the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources

Students in CASNR may earn a bachelor of science degree in more than one program. They must complete all requirements for both programs.

Dual Degrees from CASNR and Other UNL Colleges

Students in other colleges may earn a bachelor of science from CASNR and a degree from another UNL college. Students will need to consult with both colleges to ensure all requirements are satisfied.

Grading Appeals

A student who feels that he/she has been unfairly graded must ordinarily take the following sequential steps in a timely manner, usually by initiating the appeal in the semester following the awarding of the grade:

1. Talk with the instructor concerned. Most problems are resolved at this point.

2. Talk to the instructor’s department head.

3. Take the case to the Grading Appeal Committee of the department concerned. The Committee should be contacted through the department head.

4. Take the case to the CASNR Curriculum Committee by contacting the Dean’s Office, 103 Agricultural Hall. Notification to the Curriculum Committee must be in writing and will include in the notice a statement of the grounds of appeal. Both the student and the instructor will be given an opportunity to present materials to the committee in the presence of each other.

Graduation Application

Students should access their Degree Audit via MyRed at least once each term to review degree requirements and progress toward graduation. It is the student’s responsibility to make sure their Degree Audit accurately reflects their current College and program of study.

Students are expected to develop a clear understanding of degree requirements and to plan their course of study with a College adviser. Students requiring clarification of outstanding degree requirements should visit with a College adviser promptly. Students who believe their Degree Audit has errors or omissions should visit with a College adviser promptly. It is important that you resolve these matters as soon as practicable to avoid a delay in graduation.

Each student must submit an Application for Graduation plus $25.00 check or cash fee for each degree to be received to the Office of the University Registrar by:

The last Friday in January for May graduation
The last Friday in June for August graduation
The last Friday in September for December graduation

An electronic Application for Graduation and payment is available via MyRed. Those students choosing to apply for graduation in person may visit the Office of the University Registrar, 107 Canfield Administration Building. Applications for Graduation submitted in person or by mail must be accompanied by payment. Failure to submit a timely Application for Graduation may preclude the awarding of a degree in the intended term.

Honors Program

The College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources encourages qualified students to participate in the University Honors Program which is a UNL-wide program. The College’s honors students pursue degree programs offered by the College while completing the required honors courses.

All University Honors Program students are expected to complete a mentored thesis project with a faculty member of their choosing. Students should enroll in AGRI 299H in the spring semester of their sophomore year. As a part of AGRI 299H, students will identify a faculty thesis mentor and write a thesis proposal with their faculty thesis mentor. Because of the breadth of degrees, the program relies on faculty mentors within individual degree programs to determine the criteria for an undergraduate thesis in their area of endeavor. General guidance for mentors is provided as requested by Dr. Madhavan Soundararajan.

The Agricultural Research Division supports a competitive grants program to assist the College’s Honors Program students in the pursuit of their mentored theses. Students may also seek support from UNL’s Undergraduate Creative Activities and Research Experience (UCARE) program.

For more information about the University Honors Program, contact:

Dr. Madhavan Soundararajan

University of Nebraska–Lincoln

N251 Beadle

PO Box 88664

Lincoln, NE 68588-0664

Student Recognition

Dean’s List

Each semester, students having 12 UNL semester-graded hours with a minimum grade point average of 3.75 or above are eligible for the Dean’s List.

Degrees with Distinction

In recognition of outstanding academic excellence, CASNR recommends the bachelors degree With Distinction, With High Distinction, and With Highest Distinction. Recommendations are made by the CASNR Committee on Scholarship. To be eligible for consideration by the Committee, undergraduate students must complete 45 credit hours for a letter grade (excluding Pass/No Pass marks) at UNL prior to the semester in which they graduate and must have completed 60 such credit hours at UNL at the time they graduate. To determine which of the eligible candidates will be recommended for the honor, the Committee currently uses the cumulative grade point average as follows:

With Distinction 3.800-3.849

With High Distinction 3.850-3.919

With Highest Distinction 3.920-4.000

NOTE: For a student to achieve Highest Distinction, the student must successfully complete an undergraduate thesis or a comparable creative effort. It is also recommended that a student who successfully completes an undergraduate thesis (or comparable creative effort) be eligible for distinction consideration if their cumulative grade point is 3.750 or higher.

International Study/Education Abroad

The College offers a variety of opportunities for students to enhance their international awareness. All students are required to demonstrate that they have a minimal international awareness, either through course work or experience. A minor in International Agriculture and Natural Resources can be designed for students who seek a broad understanding of the nature and role of agriculture and natural resources in the integrated world economy and the implications of world events for agriculture and natural resources. International study tours of one to three weeks in duration are also sponsored by CASNR to assist students in discovering different ways of thinking and acting as well as making them more informed global citizens. CASNR also promotes the Education Abroad program offered through the UNL Education Abroad Office which has opportunities of various lengths in numerous countries on all continents.

For financial assistance, the College offers the Robert and Beatrice Kleis Fund. One or more grants are awarded annually to undergraduate students in agriculture-related degree programs at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln. These grants shall be used to subsidize expenses associated with an international study program for credit. For more information on international opportunities, contact John Kerrigan at 316 Nebraska East Union or 116 Henzlik Hall or 402-472-8379.

Student Standing/Classification

Sophomore Standing. For admission to sophomore standing, a student must have completed all of the College entrance requirements except foreign language, earned a minimum of 27 semester hours of credit, and attained a total grade point average of at least 2.0.

Junior Standing. A student has junior standing after meeting the requirements for sophomore standing and completing 53 semester hours of credit.

Senior Standing. A student has senior standing after meeting the requirements for junior standing and completing 89 semester hours of credit.

Substitutions and Waivers

Requests for substitutions and waivers involving courses that fall within the basic four-year curriculum must be filed before the start of the fall semester for December graduates, before the start of the spring semester for May graduates and prior to the last day of classes of the spring semester for August graduates. Forms are available in 103 Agricultural Hall, from the student adviser, or on the website. NOTE: If a course and/or a requirement within the degree program is waived, the credit hours in the degree program are still required.

ACE REQUIREMENTS

All students must fulfill the Achievement Centered Education (ACE) requirements. Information about the ACE program may be viewed at www.ace.unl.

The minimum requirements of CASNR reflect the common core of courses that apply to students pursuing degrees in the college. Students should work with an adviser to satisfy ACE outcomes 1, 2, 3, 4, 6 and 10 with the college requirements.

BULLETIN TO USE

Students must fulfill the requirements stated in the bulletin for the academic year in which they are first admitted to UNL or when they were first admitted to a Joint Academic Transfer Program. In consultation with advisers, a student may choose to follow a subsequent bulletin for any academic year in which they are admitted to and enrolled as a degree-seeking student at UNL in the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources. Students must complete all degree requirements from a single bulletin year. The bulletin which a student follows for degree requirements may not be more than 10 years old at the time of graduation.

COLLEGE DEGREE REQUIREMENTS

Curriculum Requirements

The curriculum requirements of the College consist of three areas: ACE (Achievement-Centered Education); College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources Core; and Degree Program requirements and electives. All three areas of the College Curriculum Requirements are incorporated within the description of the Major/Degree Program sections of the bulletin. The individual major/degree program listings of classes insures that a student will meet the minimum curriculum requirements of the College.

Foreign Languages/Language Requirement

Two units of a foreign language are required. This requirement is usually met with two years of high school language.

Minimum Hours Required for Graduation

The College grants the bachelors degree in programs associated with agricultural sciences, natural resources and related programs. Students working toward a degree must earn at least 120 semester hours of credit. A minimum cumulative grade point average of C (2.0 on a 4.0 scale) must be maintained throughout the course of studies and is required for graduation.

Grade Rules

Removal of C-, D and F Grades

Only the most recent letter grade received in a given course will be used in computing a student’s cumulative grade point average if the student has completed the course more than once and previously received a grade or grades below C in that course.

The previous grade (or grades) will not be used in computation of the cumulative grade point average, but it will remain a part of the academic record and will appear on any transcript.

A student can remove from his/her cumulative average a course grade of C-, D+, D, D- or F if the student repeats the same course at the University of Nebraska and receives a grade other than P (pass), I (incomplete), N (no pass), W (withdrew), or NR (no report). If a course is no longer being offered, it is not eligible for the revised grade point average computation process.

For complete procedures and regulations, see the Office of the University Registrar website at http://www.unl.edu/regrec/course-repeats.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Students in CASNR may take any course offered on a Pass/No Pass basis within the 24-hour limitation established by the Faculty Senate. However, a department may specify that the Pass/No Pass status of its courses be limited to non-majors, or may choose to offer some courses for letter grades only.

GPA Requirements

A minimum cumulative grade point average of C (2.0 on a 4.0 scale) must be maintained throughout the course of studies and is required for graduation.

Transfer Credit Rules

To be considered for admission, a transfer student, Nebraska resident or nonresident, must have an accumulated average of C (2.0 on a 4.0 scale) and a minimum C average in the last semester of attendance at another college. Transfer students who have completed less than 12 credit hours of college study must submit either ACT or SAT scores.

Ordinarily, credits earned at an accredited college are accepted by the University. The College, however, will evaluate all hours submitted on an application for transfer and reserves the right to accept or reject any of them. Sixty is the maximum number of hours UNL will accept on transfer from a two-year college. Ninety is the maximum number of hours UNL will accept from a four-year college. Transfer credit in the degree program must be approved by the degree program adviser on a Request for Substitution Form to meet specific course requirements, group requirements, or course level requirements in the major. At least 9 hours in the major field, including the capstone course, must be completed at UNL regardless of the number of hours transferred.

The College will accept no more than 10 semester hours of C-, D+, D and D- grades from other schools. The C-, D+, D and D- grades can only be applied to free electives. This policy does not apply to the transfer of grades from UNO or UNK to UNL.

Joint Academic Transfer Programs

The College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources has agreements with many institutions to support joint academic programs. The transfer programs include dual degree programs and cooperative degree programs. Dual degree programs offer students the opportunity to receive a degree from a participating institution and also to complete requirements for a bachelor of science degree in CASNR. Cooperative programs result in a single degree from either UNL or the cooperating institution.

Dual Degree Programs

A to B Programs

The A to B Program, a joint academic program offered by the CASNR and participating community colleges, allows students to complete the first two years of a degree program at the participating community college and continue their education and study in a degree program leading toward a bachelor of science degree.

The A to B Program provides a basic knowledge plus specialized course work. Students transfer into CASNR with junior standing.

Depending on the community college, students enrolled in the A to B Program may complete the requirements for an associate of science at the community college, transfer to UNL, and work toward a bachelor of science degree.

Participating community colleges include:

Central Community College
Metropolitan Community College
Mid-Plains Community College
Northeast Community College
Southeast Community College
Western Nebraska Community College

3+2 Programs

Two specialized degree programs in animal science and veterinary science are offered jointly with an accredited college or school of veterinary medicine. These two programs permit CASNR animal science or veterinary science students to receive a bachelor of science degree from UNL with a degree in animal science or veterinary science after successfully completing two years of the professional curriculum in veterinary medicine at an accredited veterinary school. Students who successfully complete the 3+2 Program, must complete the “Application for Degree” form and provide transcripts to the Credentials Clerk, Office of the University Registrar, 107 Canfield Administration Building, UNL. Students should discuss these degree programs with their academic adviser.

Cooperative Degree Programs

Academic credit from UNL and a cooperating institution is applied towards a four-year degree from either UNL (UNL degree-granting program) or the cooperating institution (non UNL degree-granting program). All have approved programs of study.

UNL Degree-Granting Programs

A UNL degree-granting program is designed to provide students the opportunity to complete a two-year program of study at one of the four-year institutions listed below, transfer to CASNR and complete the requirements for a bachelor of science degree.

Chadron State College. Chadron State College offers a 2+2 program leading to a grassland ecology and management degree program.

University of Nebraska at Kearney. Transfer programs are available for students pursuing degree programs leading to a bachelor of science degree.

University of Nebraska at Omaha. The University of Nebraska at Omaha (UNO) cooperates with CASNR in providing four-semester pre-agricultural sciences, pre-natural resources, pre-food science and technology, and pre-horticulture transfer programs.

A student enrolled in these programs may transfer all satisfactorily completed academic credits identified in the suggested program of study, and enter CASNR to study toward a degree program leading to a bachelor of science degree. The total program would require a minimum of four years or eight semesters (16 credit hours/semester or 120 credit hours).

UNL CASNR faculty teach horticulture and food science and technology courses at UNO to assist an urban population in better understanding the food processing, horticulture, and landscape horticulture industries.

For more information, contact Associate Professor Steven Rodie, Pre-Horticulture Program, University of Nebraska at Omaha, 402-554-3752; and/or the CASNR Dean’s Office, 800-472-8800, ext. 2541.

Non UNL Degree-Granting Programs

The CASNR cooperates with other institutions to provide course work that is applied towards a degree at the cooperating institution. Pre-professional programs offered by CASNR allow students to complete the first two or three years of a degree program at UNL prior to transferring and completing a degree at the cooperating institution.

Chadron State College–Range Science. The 3+1 Program in range science allows Chadron State College students to pursue a range science degree through Chadron State College. Students complete three years of course work at Chadron State College and one year of specialized range science course work (32 credit hours) at CASNR.

Dordt College (Iowa) – Agricultural Education: Teaching Option. This program allows students to pursue an Agricultural Education Teaching Option degree leading toward a bachelor of science in agricultural education. Students at Dordt College will complete 90 credit hours in the Agricultural Education: Teaching Option Transfer Program.

Residency

Students must complete at least 30 of the total hours for their degree using UNL credits. Credit earned during education abroad may be used toward the residency requirement if students register through UNL and participate in prior-approved education abroad programs. UNL open enrollment and summer independent study courses count toward residence.

Online and Distance Education

There are many opportunities to earn college credit through the University of Nebraska–Lincoln Office of Online and Distance Education. Some of these credits may be applicable not only as elective credits, but also toward the fulfillment of the College’s education requirements. Credits earned through the UNL Online and Distance Education program may count toward residency. However, certain offerings may not be counted toward scholarship requirements or academic recognition criteria.

For further information, contact:

Office of Online and Distance Education

University of Nebraska–Lincoln

2100 Vine Street

Lincoln, NE 68588-8307

402-472-2175

http://online.unl.edu/

Independent Study Rules

Students wishing to take part in independent studies must obtain permission; complete and sign a contract form; and furnish copies of the contract to the instructor, adviser, departmental office, and the Dean’s Office. The contract should be completed before registration. Forms are available in 103 Agricultural Hall or online at the CASNR website.

Independent study projects include research, literature review or extension of course work under supervision and evaluation of a departmental faculty member.

Students may only count 12 hours of independent study toward their degrees and no more than 6 hours can be counted during their last 36 hours earned, excluding senior thesis, internships, and courses taught under an independent study number.

Other College Degree Requirements

Capstone Course Requirement

A capstone course is required for each CASNR degree program. A capstone course is defined as a course in which students are required to integrate diverse bodies of knowledge to solve a problem or formulate a policy of societal importance.

DEGREES & MAJORS

Degree Programs

Agribusiness (Offered jointly with College of Business Administration)

Agricultural Economics

Agricultural Education

Agricultural and Environmental Sciences Communication

Agronomy

Animal Science

Applied Climate Science

Applied Science

Biochemistry (Offered jointly with the College of Arts and Sciences)

Environmental Restoration Science

Environmental Studies (Offered jointly with the College of Arts and Sciences)

Fisheries and Wildlife

Food Science and Technology

Food Technology for Companion Animals

Forensic Science

Grassland Ecology and Management

Grazing Livestock Systems

Horticulture

Hospitality, Restaurant & Tourism Management (Offered jointly with the College of Education and Human Sciences)

Insect Science

Mechanized Systems Management

Microbiology (Offered jointly with the College of Arts and Sciences)

Natural Resource and Environmental Economics

Plant Biology (Offered jointly with the College of Arts and Sciences)

PGA Golf Management

Turfgrass and Landscape Management

Veterinary Science

Veterinary Technology (Offered jointly with the Nebraska College of Technical Agriculture)

Water Science

Multiple Degrees

Students may complete requirements for more than one degree by declaring, prior to the last 30 hours of study, a dual degree. This is made possible through a common core required for all CASNR students. Students may consider these options with their faculty advisers.

An adviser is assigned for each additional degree declared. Appropriate forms must be processed in 103 Agricultural Hall.

Pre-Professional Programs

Integrated Science

Pre-Forestry

Pre-Law

Pre-Veterinary Medicine

Related Degree Programs

Agricultural Engineering (Offered jointly with the College of Engineering)

Biological Systems Engineering (Offered jointly with the College of Engineering)

Landscape Architecture (Offered jointly with the College of Architecture)

Statistics (Offered jointly with the College of Arts and Sciences)

Professional Programs

Doctor of Plant Health

Veterinary Medicine

Certificate Programs

Contact John Markwell in the CASNR Deans’ Office

MINORS & AREAS OF SPECIALIZATIONS OFFERED

Minors in the College will consist of 18 hours in the minor area of study, including at least six hours at the 300 and/or 400 level. Alternatively, 12 hours of 300- and/or 400-level courses will meet the requirement. At the discretion of the department(s) responsible for the minor, up to three hours of independent study may be counted toward the minor. Departments may specify additional requirements for their minor(s).

Minors offered through CASNR:

Agribusiness

Agricultural Economics

Agronomy

Animal Science

Biochemistry

Community Economics and Social Dynamics (Agricultural Economics)

Computational Biology and Bioinformatics (Offered jointly with the College of Engineering and the College of Arts and Sciences)

Energy Science

Engler Agribusiness Entrepreneurship

Environmental Education

Environmental Restoration Science

Environmental Studies

Food Science and Technology

Fisheries and Wildlife

Grassland Ecology and Management

Grazing Livestock Systems

Horticulture

Insect Science

International Agriculture and Natural Resources

Leadership and Communication (Agricultural Leadership, Education, and Communication)

Leadership and Entrepreneurship (Agricultural Leadership, Education, and Communication)

Mechanized Systems Management

Natural Resource and Environmental Economics

Plant Biology

Statistics

Turfgrass and Landscape Management

Veterinary Science

Water Science

Filing for a Minor

Students wishing to declare a minor, must file a new C-D-M-A (College-Degree-Major-Adviser) form with the Dean’s Office prior to filing for graduation if the minor is exactly the same as that published in the student’s Undergraduate Bulletin. If there are any variations from the published minor, then the student must file the “Revision of Minor” form with the Dean’s Office.

Minors in Other Colleges

A student with a degree leading to a bachelor of science degree who wants to obtain a minor in a department in the College of Arts and Sciences should use the following procedure in making his/her request:

1. In consultation with the adviser, prepare the list of courses required for either Plan A or Plan B in the chosen minor as indicated in the College of Arts and Sciences section of this bulletin. Plan A indicates a single minor; Plan B indicates two minors with fewer hours in each subject than the number required for a single minor.

2. Submit the C-D-M-A form for the minor to the CASNR Dean’s Office prior to the deadline for submitting the application for graduation.

Students who have questions related to the minor after it is declared should consult an adviser in the college through which it is offered. The minor will be recorded on the student’s transcript.

GRADUATE STUDENT INFORMATION

Graduate work leading to the masters degree is offered in the departments of Agricultural Economics; Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication; Agronomy and Horticulture; Animal Science; Biochemistry; Biological Systems Engineering; Entomology; Food Science and Technology; Plant Pathology; Statistics; School of Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical Sciences; School of Natural Resources; the Center for Biological Chemistry; and in the interdepartmental area of nutrition. A master of applied science degree is also available.

Graduate work leading to the doctor of philosophy degree is offered by the departments of Agricultural Economics; Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication (offered jointly with the College of Education and Human Sciences); School of Natural Resources (agricultural meteorology and forestry, fisheries and wildlife); Agronomy and Horticulture; Animal Science; Biological Systems Engineering/Agricultural Engineering; Entomology; Food Science and Technology; Plant Pathology (offered jointly with the School of Biological Sciences); Statistics; Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical Sciences; the Center for Biological Chemistry (offered jointly with the College of Arts and Sciences); and in the interdepartmental area of Nutrition.

Further information appears in the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

Architecture

ADMISSION

Admission to the College of Architecture

Admission to the University of Nebraska–Lincoln does not constitute admission to the College of Architecture. Students seeking enrollment in the College of Architecture should indicate their desire by marking the proper major code on the University application form.

Freshmen and transfer students applying for admission to the pre-architecture, pre-interior design, and pre-landscape architecture program must submit complete admission application materials by May 1 for fall admission and December 1 for spring admission. These admission procedures apply to high school students seeking admission, as well as transfer students, international students, and also those transferring from UNO and UNK to UNL.

High School Standards Pre-Architecture, Pre-Interior Design, and Pre-Landscape Architecture Programs

Prospective students interested in the Professional Program in Architecture are eligible to apply for admission into the pre-architecture major if their high school records meet the following standards:

1. Mathematics–4 units of Algebra I, II, geometry, and one-half unit of trigonometry, and one-half unit that builds on a knowledge of algebra or pre-calculus.

2. English–4 units of intensive reading and writing.

3. Social Studies–3 units. At least one unit of American and/or world history and one additional unit of history, American government, and/or geography.

4. Natural Science–3 units. At least two of the three units selected from biology, chemistry, physics, and earth sciences. One of the units must include a laboratory.

5. Foreign Language–2 units.

Admission Deficiencies/Removal of Deficiencies

Because admission requirements establish the level of knowledge and skills which are needed for a student to succeed at UNL, students who are admitted with core course deficiencies in foreign language and geometry are expected to quickly remove them. Deficiencies must be removed before a student is eligible for graduation.

General Admission Requirements for the College of Architecture

In addition to the high school admission requirements, the College of Architecture has established the following general admission requirements for all undergraduate students.

New freshman students must:

Graduate in the upper quartile of their high school class, or
Have an enhanced ACT composite score of 22, or
Have a combined SAT verbal and math total of at least 1030 enhanced, or
Receive permission from the program director with a waiver from the above requirements.

New international freshman students must:

Meet UNL entrance requirements for new international freshman students, and
Have a MELAB score of at least 80 or a minimum TOEFL score of 550, or computer-based score of 213 or 79-80 Internet-based.

New transfer students must:

Have a minimum 3.0 cumulative GPA for architecture, landscape architecture, and interior design and be in good scholastic standing.

NOTE: New transfer students must comply with new freshman student entrance requirements if they have completed less than 12 credit hours of college study.

New international transfer students must:

Meet UNL entrance requirements for international transfer students
Have a MELAB score of at least 80 or a minimum TOEFL score of 550, or computer-based score of 213, or Internet-based score of 79-80
Have a minimum 3.0 cumulative GPA and be in good scholastic standing

Students who transfer into the College of Architecture from other colleges at UNL must:

Have a minimum 3.0 cumulative GPA for architecture, landscape architecture, and interior design and be in good scholastic standing. Students transferring from UNO and UNK are included in the new transfer student category.

NOTE: New transfer students must comply with new freshman student entrance requirements if they have completed less than 12 credit hours of college study.

Readmission

Students who apply for readmission to the College of Architecture must have a minimum 3.0 cumulative GPA for architecture, landscape architecture and interior design, be in good scholastic standing, and receive permission from the dean of the College.

Former students who withdraw after being admitted to the College, or who have been academically suspended and wish to be readmitted must: a) be readmitted to the College in good scholastic standing, and b) be in good scholastic standing in accordance with the program standards and receive permission from the program director. Applicants for readmission will compete for spaces available with all other admission applicants.

ADVISING

Academic Advising

The College of Architecture is committed to providing effective advising services to students as an essential component of their educational experience.

Students in the pre-architecture, pre-landscape architecture, and pre-interior design programs are assigned to a staff adviser. These advisers are located in the program office to afford students easy access to information and to the program directors should this be necessary or desirable.

After admission into their respective professional program, students are assigned a faculty adviser. This person serves as an important resource for questions about the professions, their future careers, and their academic plans and progress. Students are encouraged to regularly consult with their adviser and are responsible for initiating advising contacts and preparing for advising sessions. Students must consult with their adviser prior to registering for classes. Failure to do so may result in removal from classes. Ultimately, students are themselves responsible for fulfilling all the requirements of the curriculum in which they are enrolled. The intellectual mentoring relationship between academic adviser and student is protected by confidentiality and strengthened by listening with understanding to student concerns.

The program office houses student records and the staff is helpful in checking on degree requirements and University procedures and policies.

The program office provides information for prospective and entering students who are seeking admission to the College of Architecture.

ACADEMIC PROGRAMS & POLICIES

Academic Load

Students in the bachelor of science in design (BSD) degree program must be enrolled in 12 credit hours of course work to be classified as a full time student. Students in the master of architecture degree program must be enrolled in 9 credit hours of course work to be classified as a full time student. Students participating in one of the program’s education abroad programs enrolled in less than the credit hours specified above may also be classified as full time students with permission of the director.

BSD students must obtain permission from the program director to enroll in more than 17 credit hours prior to the start of the semester. Students in the MArch program must obtain similar permission to exceed 15 credit hours.

Employment and Course Load Guidelines

The architecture, interior design, and landscape architecture programs are demanding disciplines requiring significant commitment to succeed. For this reason, the college has adopted a policy recommending students who are employed to not exceed the following registration guidelines:

Work load per week

|

Course load per semester

0 hours

|

up to 18 credit hours

8-16 hours

|

13-16 credit hours

17-20 hours

|

10-12 credit hours

Full time

|

up to 6 cr hours

Professional students holding teaching or research assistantships are required to be enrolled as a student in the professional program and their course load cannot exceed 12 credit hours per semester. Students holding these positions are prohibited from engaging in any other form of remunerative employment without the permission of the program director.

Course Exclusions & Restrictions

Military Science, Naval Science, Aerospace Studies and/or Physical Education

A maximum combination of courses in these areas totaling 6 credit hours can be applied toward the bachelor of science in design degree as elective credit.

Drop/Add

The university’s drop/add policy is outlined in the Schedule of Classes each semester. The professional program subscribes to the same rules and limitations indicated in this publication. In general, classes can only be added during the first week of the semester. You may drop a class from your schedule anytime during the first eleven weeks of the semester. After the eleventh week, withdrawal from the class is possible only for extraordinary circumstances and will be granted only by petition. Grounds for extraordinary withdrawal include: military service, medical illness, death in immediate family, personal trauma, or complete absence from all courses without officially withdrawing.

The specific deadline for dropping a class is listed in the Schedule of Classes. Students can access their MyRED account to drop or add classes. Please be warned, failure to attend classes does not constitute proper notification of dropping a class. If you are unable to attend classes, you need to see or telephone your instructor as soon as possible. Failure to do so may jeopardize your chances for dropping the class. If you wish to drop all your courses, you need to use the Withdrawal from the University form. See the section below for a description of this process.

The Drop/Add form is available in the program office.

Dual Degrees

Joint Degree Programs

Business

Architecture majors accepted to the 5th and 6th years may choose to pursue a three-year course of study that leads to joint degrees of master of architecture and master of business administration. Participation in this joint degree program requires admission into both the MArch and MBA programs. Students should consult with their adviser to develop an appropriate plan.

Community and Regional Planning

Architecture majors accepted to the 5th and 6th years may choose to pursue a course of study that leads to joint degrees of master of architecture and master of community and regional planning. A suggested sequence of courses can be obtained from your adviser, the Architecture Program Office, or the Community and Regional Planning Program Office.

Construction Management

Architecture majors accepted to the 5th and 6th years may pursue a course of study that leads to joint degrees of master of architecture and master of engineering in construction management. This requires acceptance by the construction management program. The required course sequence can be obtained from your adviser.

Enrollment Policy

College of Architecture Enrollment Policy

Enrollment in the pre-architecture, pre-interior design, and pre-landscape architecture majors shall be limited by available teaching resources and space capacities, therefore an enrollment limit is established for each of these programs.

Admission to the pre-architecture, pre-interior design, and pre-landscape architecture programs occurs year-round; however, access to studio courses is not guaranteed for those students admitted beyond the February 15th deadline for transfer students or March 15th deadline for freshmen.

Probation, Appeals and Dismissal

Undergraduate students who are placed on probation will not be allowed to take any new architecture, design, interior design, or landscape architecture courses without the permission of the program director. Students will be allowed to retake architecture, design, interior design, and landscape architecture courses while on probation. Students may not take the same course more than three times.

Students in the undergraduate program placed on academic probation by the College for two consecutive semesters will be transferred out of the College of Architecture into the Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center and must reapply for admission to the College and the architecture, landscape architecture, or interior design programs. Students must have a cumulative GPA of 3.0 to be readmitted from the Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center into architecture, interior design, and landscape architecture.

Students in the MArch program placed on probation will be allowed to continue with their classes for one semester. If their next semester grade point average is below a 3.0 they are dismissed from the degree program. Students desiring to be readmitted will have to apply for admission to the professional program.

Students who register for new architecture, design, interior design, or landscape architecture courses while on probation will be administratively dropped from those courses unless they have received the permission of the program director.

Registration Limits

Students are not allowed to register for 200-800 level architecture, interior design, or landscape architecture courses unless they have been admitted into their respective professional programs. Some specific courses allow registration of non-majors with permission of the faculty member teaching the course but this permission process is not available to majors.

The programs have adopted limits on the number of credit hours a student can register for without the permission of the director. Students in good academic standing are allowed to register for a maximum of 17 credit hours. Students wishing to exceed this number must secure permission from the director prior to registering for the courses. Under no circumstances can a student register for more than 19 hours in a semester.

Students who are on academic probation are restricted to a maximum number of 12 credit hours. Permission to exceed 12 credit hours must be granted by the Program Director.  For more specific limitations for students on academic probation see the text on Academic Standing earlier in this section.

Student Recognition

Dean’s List

Each semester, select undergraduate students enrolled in the College of Architecture are recognized for their scholastic accomplishments by being named to the Dean’s List. Criteria for this honor are:

1. Students must earn a semester (not cumulative) GPA that ranks them in the upper ten percent of the College’s enrollment.

2. Students must earn a minimum of 12 graded credit hours during that semester. (Pass/No Pass credit cannot be applied toward the 12 required credit hours.)

Graduation With Distinction and With High Distinction

Students with outstanding scholastic records may earn the special honor of graduation With Distinction or With High Distinction. One student each graduation may be chosen to graduate With Highest Distinction. Requirements for these honors are listed below.

Graduation With Distinction shall be awarded to students earning at least 60 credit hours in residence at UNL who are in the 90th percentile of those graduating in the prior twelve month period or who have a minimum 3.6 cumulative GPA.

Graduation With High Distinction shall be awarded to students in the top half of those who meet the qualifications for graduation with distinction and have a minimum 3.8 cumulative GPA.

Graduation With Highest Distinction may be awarded by selection of the faculty to a student who meets the qualifications for graduation with high distinction and has also demonstrated outstanding professional excellence through creative work.

International Education Programs

China. The College of Architecture has a formal agreement for an exchange of faculty and students with the Northwest Institute of Architectural Engineering at Xian, People’s Republic of China. This exchange program was initiated in 1989.

Dublin, Ireland. During the fall semester, qualified students in the Department of Architecture can elect to study in Dublin, Ireland. Under an agreement with the Dublin Institute of Technology, students have an opportunity to complete one semester of their requirements toward a degree at UNL.

Hannover, Germany. During the spring semester, qualified students in the fourth or fifth year of the BSD program can elect to study in Hannover, Germany. Under an agreement with Hannover University, students have an opportunity to complete one semester of their requirements toward a degree at UNL.

Clermont-Ferrand, France. During the spring semester, qualified students in the fourth or fifth year of the BSD program can elect to study in Clermont-Ferrand, France. Under an agreement with the university, students have an opportunity to complete one semester of their requirements toward a degree at UNL.

London, England. During each spring semester, qualified students may elect one semester of resident studies in London, England. The program offers students enrolled in the architecture (5th or 6th years), interior design (4th year), or landscape architecture (4th year) programs the opportunity to study urban and architectural design in a cross-cultural and comparative manner. Under the direction of a faculty member in either the architecture, interior design, or landscape architecture programs, the program is annually accommodated by a wealth of historic and modern case materials with cooperative assistance from educators and practicing professionals in the London area. Stephan Rienke (AIA, RIBA) serves as adjunct professor to the College and provides invaluable professional and cultural assistance to visiting UNL faculty and students.

Tianjin, China. During each fall semester, qualified students may elect a semester of resident studies in Tianjin, China. The program offers students enrolled in the architecture (5th or 6th year) or landscape architecture (5th year) the opportunity to study design in an urban environment with cross-cultural influences. Under the direction of a faculty member of either architecture or landscape architecture, the program offers students a rich experience. Working with the urban design and planning office of KX International Design and Planning.

Monteverde, Costa Rica. During the summer 3-week pre-session, the Community and Regional Planning program offers a 3-credit advanced field studies course in Costa Rica, covering basic field techniques in environmental, social and economic aspects of sustainable community planning in developing regions and sensitive environments.

Ecuador. During the 3-week pre-session, the College of Architecture offers a 1-3 credit service-learning course led by Kim Wilson, Community and Regional Planning and Landscape Architecture programs director.

Paris, France. During a 5-week summer session, the College of Architecture offers a 3-credit History & Theory Elective course in Paris.

Senior Check/Degree Audit

Senior and Professional Check and Application for Degree

During the last semester of the third year of study, senior checks are to be initiated by the student and reviewed by the student’s adviser. The senior check forms are maintained by the adviser and filed in the students’ advising folders.

Students in the BSD, BLA, and MArch degree programs must also file a graduation notice with the Credentials Office early in the semester in which they intend to graduate. Failure to meet the published deadline will delay graduation one full term.

Substitutions and Waivers

Students wishing to propose a course substitution in their curriculum of study must petition the Professional Program Committee by completing a substitution form. The substitution form should be filled out in consultation with your academic adviser. All proposals must include a detailed explanation for the substitution. The student’s adviser must review and sign the completed form before it can be submitted to the Professional Program Committee. It is very important that these procedures be followed for an expeditious response to the proposal. Substitutions must be approved before enrolling in a substitute course.

Students are advised the Professional Program Committee meets once a month, and will not consider any substitution proposals without a completed form and explanation signed by their adviser. The process to obtain a course substitution is lengthy and can not be accomplished at the “eleventh hour” to compensate for poor academic planning.

Copies of the substitution form are available in the program office.

Internships

Architecture Internship

An internship program is available to students who have completed the BSD or its equivalent before or during the 5th and 6th year of the Professional Program in Architecture. Academic credits will be given (up to 6 hours) for this internship experience. Students will be required to apply for acceptance into the program and will be monitored by the program’s internship coordinator.

Interior Design Internship

All students enrolled in the interior design program need to complete an approved internship as part of their professional requirements. Students are not eligible for an internship until they are enrolled in, or have completed, IDES 351 Interior Design Studio 4.

Landscape Architecture Internship

Students enrolled in the landscape architecture program are eligible to complete an approved internship as a part of their professional requirements. Academic credit will be given for this internship experience.

ACE REQUIREMENTS

Achievement-Centered Education (ACE)

The University of Nebraska–Lincoln requires all students receive a broad general education as part of their academic experience. This requirement translates into the obligation of all students to fulfill the requirements of the ACE program. Information about the ACE program may be viewed at ace.unl.edu.

English

It is of vital importance that architects, landscape architects, and interior designers be able to express themselves clearly and concisely. As a matter of routine, architects, interior designers, and landscape architects are called upon to prepare reports, papers, or specifications in which clarity and precision are essential. For this reason, a student is required to do more than meet the English composition course requirement. In daily oral and written work the student must demonstrate an acceptable skill in the use of effective English. The dean may require students who fail to meet acceptable standards to do additional work in English composition or speech communication. Each instructor is expected to bring to the dean’s attention the students who need additional work.

Students are expected to take ENGL 150 or ENGL 151. ENGL 186, ENGL 187 and ENGL 192 may not be used to satisfy the freshman English composition requirement.

Mathematics

All students in the College of Architecture are required to receive credit for MATH 104. Courses taken as deficiencies to qualify for MATH 104 will not apply as credit toward their degree.

COLLEGE DEGREE REQUIREMENTS

Minimum Hours Required for Graduation

BSD in Architecture – 120 hours

BSD in Interior Design – 120 hours

Bachelor of Landscape Architecture (BLA) – 120 hours

Grading Appeals

A student wishing to appeal a grade should contact his or her professor for clarification first before an appeal can be filed. If the dispute cannot be resolved with the instructor it is recommended that the student meet with their adviser to get clarification on the appeals process. Appeals are only considered where it can be demonstrated that prejudice or capricious treatment influenced the grade received by the student.

Having exhausted these avenues, a student may then choose to make a formal appeal. The appeal is in the form of a written statement from the student to the program director. The director will then forward the letter to the Faculty Affairs Committee. The deadline for filing a grade appeal (which includes a written statement from the student) is 30 calendar days after the first day of classes of the next regular semester (fall or spring). Appeals filed after the deadline will not be heard.

Incomplete Grades

Incompletes for students in the pre-professional program shall be granted only for reasons outlined in the policy statement adopted by the University Senate. See the UNL Schedule of Classes for the complete text.

Incompletes given to students in the professional program are granted at the discretion of the faculty awarding the grade. The faculty and student together must file an incomplete form in the department office to register the anticipated completion date and the grade that will be registered if the work is not completed by that time.

Architecture students will be allowed a maximum of two weeks to remove incompletes from courses that are prerequisites to classes in which they are currently enrolled or they will be administratively dropped from those courses.

Scholastic Standing

The following scholastic standards have been established to maintain the level of quality for students enrolled in the architecture program:

Pre-Professional Program, Architecture, Landscape Architecture and Interior Design

Students in the first year are required to maintain both a semester and cumulative grade point average at or above 2.0. The College places students who fail to meet these standards on academic probation.

Second, Third and Fourth Year, Architecture

Students in the second year are required to maintain both a semester and cumulative grade point average of 2.6. Students in the third and fourth year of the BSD program are required to meet two parallel academic standards. First the student must maintain a semester grade point average of 2.6 to remain in good academic standing. The program places students who fail to meet this standard on academic probation. Further, students whose GPA for the academic year is between 2.6 and 3.0 are required to submit their studio work for review by the Student Affairs Committee for determination of continuance in the program or repetition of the year’s studio sequence.

Second, Third and Fourth Year, Interior Design and Landscape Architecture

Students in the second year are required to maintain both a semester and cumulative grade point average of 2.6. Students in the third and fourth year of the BSD program are required to maintain a 2.6 cumulative grade point average to remain in good academic standing. The program also requires that students earn a grade of a C or higher in all required courses. The program places students who fail to meet this standard on academic probation.

Fifth and Sixth Year, Architecture

Students in the MArch program are required to maintain a semester grade point average of 3.0 to remain in good academic standing. The program places students who fail to meet this standard on academic probation.

Minimum Grades

Students must earn at least a C (2.0) in all courses with an ARCH, DSGN, IDES, or LARC prefix to earn credit toward their degree. Students will be required to retake all core required courses with a grade of C- or below, but will not be required to repeat courses that were taken as electives.

Removal of Grades C- or Below

A professional student receiving a grade of C- or below for an overall course grade may remove that grade by retaking the same course again and receiving a higher grade. The higher grade will be used to compute the student’s cumulative grade point average, but all grades appear on the student’s transcript. The Pass/No Pass option cannot be used to remove these grades from the grade point average. Please be advised that once a course is no longer taught and no longer offered by the department it is not possible to remove a grade of C- or below through substitution or any other means.

Should you perform poorly in many courses during a semester it is possible to bankrupt the entire semester’s grades. This is a drastic action and should be pursued only after a visit with your adviser.

Pass/No Pass Limits

None of the required classes offered in the professional program are offered Pass/No Pass, but a maximum of 12 Pass/No Pass credit hours of humanities, social sciences, or open electives may be taken from departments outside the College of Architecture.

Courses taken outside the architecture, landscape architecture, or interior design programs to fulfill the upper level outside elective requirement at the 800 level or 900 level, with or without a 400-level counterpart, in a minor, collateral, or supporting area of work, can be taken on a Pass/No Pass basis.

Transfer Credit Rules

All professional credit earned at another university to be applied toward the master of architecture degree must be approved by the Professional Program Committee in cooperation with the program director. At least 50 percent of the required course work for the professional degree must be completed at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln with the exception of those students who are applying to enter the program with a four year degree from an accredited architecture program. No professional transfer credit will be accepted from a non-accredited architecture program.

College Evaluation of Transfer Credit

First time students transferring to the College of Architecture from a similar accredited professional degree program will be evaluated on the basis of the current undergraduate bulletin in effect at the time the student enrolls in the College of Architecture.

Process

The program director will select and identify those courses that are applicable to the professional program in architecture, interior design, and landscape architecture programs. The College of Architecture will not accept courses for transfer which are below a 2.0 on a 4-point scale.

Evaluation of Technical and Nonaccredited Transfer Credits

Students who desire to transfer credits from technical or nonaccredited colleges must have architecture credits evaluated by the director and/or appropriate program representatives. Non-architecture credits will be evaluated by the appropriate university department.

Evaluation of Graphics, Design, and Production Drawing Credit

Transfer credit for graphics, basic and architectural, landscape architecture, and/or interior design work and production drawings will not be granted until the student’s work has been reviewed by the architecture, landscape architecture, or interior design program director. Allowable transfer credit in the design, production drawings, and graphics areas, whether the grades presented are C, B, or A, will be determined from this review and the student placed accordingly.

Confirmation procedure:

1. It is the student’s responsibility to initiate this task,

2. The student procedure is to obtain the confirmation form from the program office and to seek review of appropriate materials, and

3. A “portfolio review” will determine confirmation of credit. This review will be done by the appropriate faculty member or committee.

Evaluation of General Education Credits

Transfer students who have formally applied for admission will have their academic credits evaluated by the Office of the University Registrar and the College of Architecture. The College will evaluate all hours submitted on an admission application but reserves the right to reject any of these credits.

Clarification and Appeal

The student who has questions about or wishes to appeal the initial College evaluation of his or her transfer credit should contact the program office. If the evaluation is not satisfactorily resolved, the student has the right to register an appeal with the Student Affairs Committee of the architecture, landscape architecture, or interior design programs.

Independent Study

Credit hours earned through independent study (ARCH 398, ARCH 498, ARCH 598 and ARCH 898; LARC 398, LARC 498; and IDES 398, IDES 498, IDES 898) need to be formally arranged with the faculty member supervising the work prior to registration for those credit hours. This is accomplished through completion of the Independent Study Contract available in the program office. It must have the signature of the faculty sponsor and be filed with the program office in order to be valid.

Students are limited to a total of 9 credit hours of independent study over the course of their academic career in the professional program.

Other College Degree Requirements

Off-Campus Programs

The College of Architecture recognizes the need for some students to pursue their pre-architecture, pre-landscape architecture, and pre-interior design studies at other institutions. One semester (15 credit hours) of off-campus study should cause minimal delay in students’ educational timetables if courses can be selected from the following list and are approved by the College of Architecture. Students are encouraged to coordinate their off-campus pre-architecture, pre-landscape architecture, and pre-interior design programs with the College of Architecture.

Recommended Courses

Calculus (3 hrs)

English Composition elective (3 hrs)

Humanities and Social Sciences electives (9 hrs) See UNL ACE requirements.

Physics (4 hrs) for pre-architecture or Natural Science (4 hrs) for pre-interior design or Introduction to Horticulture (3 hrs) for pre-landscape architecture

Speech (3 hrs)

DEGREES & MAJORS

Organization and Degrees

The College of Architecture consists of four academic programs: architecture, interior design, landscape architecture, and community and regional planning. Architecture, interior design, and landscape architecture all have a one year pre-professional program followed by professional degree programs. In architecture, it is a five year program in which students get a bachelor of science in design (BSD) degree and the professional master of architecture (MArch) degree. The landscape architecture program is three years in which students receive a professional bachelor of landscape architecture (BLA) degree. The interior design program is three years and culminates in the professional BSD degree. The community and regional planning program is exclusively a graduate degree program.

Both architecture and interior design have post professional MS research degrees.

Community and Regional Planning

The community and regional planning program offers the two-year professional master of community and regional planning degree which is fully accredited by the Planning Accreditation Board (PAB).

MINORS & AREAS OF SPECIALIZATIONS OFFERED

Landscape Architecture

The landscape architecture minor is administered through the College of Architecture’s landscape architecture program.

The minor in landscape architecture is designed to provide a basic understanding of the nature of the profession of landscape architecture. Knowledge of landscape architecture history, theory, and context provides a useful addition to a student in any of the University disciplines.

The minor is open to all UNL students. Entrance to the minor is by application, grade review,and permission of the program director, Kim L. Wilson. Contact Leslie Gonzalez, admissions coordinator (232 Architecture Hall West, 402-472-4065, leslie.gonzalez@unl.edu) for the application.

Hours

Required Courses 18

DSGN 110 Design Thinking 3

CRPL 400 Introduction to Planning 3

LARC 200 Landscape & Environmental Appreciation 3

LARC 241 History & Theory in Contemporary Landscape Architecture 3

LARC 461 Urbanism 3

LARC 497 Professional Elective 3

GRADUATE STUDENT INFORMATION

Graduate and Professional Teaching and Research Assistantships

The College of Architecture has several teaching and research assistantships available each year. Students accepted into the master of architecture program, MS, and PhD/EdD programs or those who are in the process of making application for admission to the master of architecture program are encouraged to apply for these assistantships. A brief letter of interest and qualifications plus completed graduate assistantship recommendation forms (which are available in the Architecture Program Office) should be sent to the architecture program before February 1 of each year for consideration for the fall semester and November 15 for the spring semester.

Course Hold for Professional Credit

Seniors who have obtained in advance the approval of the architecture program director may receive up to 12 hours credit towards their MArch degree prior to the completion of their BSD degree provided the following conditions are met:

they are above the courses required for their BSD degree;
are taken under the 500 number; and
are taken in the calendar year prior to the receipt of the BSD.

BULLETIN RULE

Degree Time Limits

Students will be required to complete course work for their degree within a ten year period from the time they are admitted into the professional program in the second year.

OTHER

Ownership of Class Work

Significant student work will be retained on file by the program each semester as a necessary record for accrediting purposes and periodic display. Other student work must be retrieved by the student no later than seven working days past the end of the semester.

The College of Architecture is not responsible for storing or returning student work. In addition, all padlocks left on lockers will be cut, and the materials in the lockers confiscated after completion of spring semester.

Nonprofessional Master of Science Degree and PhD/EdD Degrees

The scholarly-nonprofessional master of science degree is a scholarly, research-based curriculum. For more information, please see the University of Nebraska–Lincoln Graduate Bulletin.

Arts & Sciences

DESCRIPTION

Steve Goddard, Ph.D., Interim Dean and Olsson Professor of Computer Science and Engineering

Debbie Minter, Ph.D., Associate Dean for Academic Programs and Associate Professor of English

Dan Hoyt, Ph.D., Associate Dean for Faculty and Professor of Sociology

Sunil Narumalani, Ph.D., Associate Dean for Research and Professor of Geography

Alecia Kimbrough, M.B.A., Assistant Dean for Business and Finance and Staff

William Watts, M.A., Assistant Dean for Student Success

For additional information or questions, contact:

Christina Fielder

Interim Director

107 Oldfather Hall

PO Box 880330

Lincoln, NE 68588-0330

402-472-4190

Mission

UNL’s College of Arts and Sciences empowers students with a world-class education befitting the State of Nebraska’s comprehensive, land-grant, research university. Our teaching in the humanities and social and natural sciences gives students the knowledge and skills they need to succeed in an increasingly complex, diverse and interconnected world. We are equally committed to increasing knowledge through research endeavors and creative activities at the leading edge of human experience, and our expertise in service and outreach furthers the interests of Nebraska, the nation, and the world. Our guiding principle is that teaching, research, and service are inextricably intertwined, enhancing our ability to provide an outstanding education.

Careers

The College’s comprehensive liberal arts education empowers graduates to pursue unlimited career possibilities. Arts and Sciences students develop strengths as communicators, critical thinkers, problem solvers and lifelong learners who can see the big picture. They have the skills and adaptability that employers universally value. Graduates are not only prepared to effectively compete in the real world, but they have a solid foundation to excel in an increasingly global, technological and interdisciplinary world.

Often there is no direct link between a student’s academic major and career choice. A student does not have to be a biology major to become a physician. Not all history majors become historians. An English major could become a lawyer.

Arts and Sciences students have access to a powerful network of faculty and advisers dedicated to providing information, support and hands-on experience through engaging course work, co-curricular activities and service opportunities to aid in the career-planning process.

The College works closely with Career Services, 230 Nebraska Union, to help students with their career planning. In addition, the chief advisers provide information and guidance.

ADMISSION

College Admission

The entrance requirements for the College of Arts and Sciences are the same as the UNL General Admission Requirements. Students who are admitted through the Admission by Review process may have certain conditions attached to their enrollment at UNL. These conditions are explained under “Removal of Deficiencies.”

In addition to these requirements, the College of Arts and Sciences strongly recommends a third and fourth year of languages. Four years of high school language will exempt students from the College of Arts and Sciences’ language requirement. It will also allow students to continue language study at a more advanced level, and give more opportunity to study abroad.

Transfer Students

To be considered for admission a transfer student, Nebraska resident or nonresident, must have an accumulated average of C (2.0 on a 4.0 scale) and a minimum C average in the last semester of attendance at another college. Transfer students who graduated from high school January 1997 and after must also meet the UNL General Admissions Requirements. Those transfer students who graduated before January 1997 must have completed in high school 3 years of English, 2 years of the same foreign language, 2 years of algebra, and 1 year of geometry. Transfer students who have completed less than 12 credit hours of college study must submit either the ACT or SAT scores.

Ordinarily, hours earned at an accredited college are accepted by the University. The College, however, will evaluate all hours submitted on an application for transfer and reserves the right to accept or reject any of them. Sixty is the maximum number of hours the University will accept on transfer from a two-year college. Transfer credit in the major must be approved by the major adviser on a Request for Substitution Form to meet specific course requirements, group requirements, or course level requirements in the major. At least half of the hours in the major field must be completed at the University regardless of the number of hours transferred.

The College of Arts and Sciences will accept no more than 15 semester hours of C- and D grades from other schools. The C- and D grades cannot be applied toward requirements for a major or minor. This policy does not apply to the transfer of grades from UNO or UNK to UNL. All D grades may be transferred from UNO or UNK, but they are not applicable to a major or minor.

Readmitted Students

Students readmitted to the College of Arts and Sciences will follow the requirements stated in the bulletin for the academic year of readmission and reenrollment as a degree-seeking student in Arts and Sciences. In consultation with advisers, a student may choose to follow a bulletin for any academic year in which they are admitted to and enrolled as a degree-seeking student at UNL in the College of Arts and Sciences. Students must complete all degree requirements from a single bulletin year. Beginning in 1990-1991, the bulletin which a student follows for degree requirements may not be more than 10 years old at the time of graduation.

Admission Deficiencies/Removal of Deficiencies

You must remove entrance deficiencies in geometry and foreign language before you can graduate from the College of Arts and Sciences.

Removing Foreign Language Deficiencies

A student will need to complete the second semester of the first year language sequence to clear the deficiency and the second semester of the second year language sequence to complete the college graduation requirement in language.

Removing Geometry Deficiencies

A deficiency of one year of geometry can be removed by taking two high school geometry courses by Independent Study or by completing a geometry course from an accredited community college or a four-year institution. Neither of these options count for college credit.

ADVISING

Academic Advising

All students in the College of Arts and Sciences are assigned to an academic adviser or advising center based on their academic interests. Advisers will help students plan their academic careers, understand degree requirements, and identify courses to meet those requirements. Specially trained advisers from the Arts and Sciences Advising Center counsel all incoming freshmen during New Student Enrollment.

Students in the College who have declared a major will be assigned a chief major adviser in their major field of study. Students who have declared a pre-health or pre-law area of interest will work with advisers in the Advising Center, specifically trained to guide students preparing to enter a professional school. All students in the College should also meet with professional advisers in the Arts and Sciences Advising Center to answer questions related to choosing majors and minors, understanding degree requirements and degree audits, completing paperwork, understanding deadlines, adding/dropping courses, and planning for graduation. The professional advisers in the Advising Center are available on an appointment and/or walk-in basis Monday through Friday. Students who have questions should contact the Advising Center.

For complete and current information on chief advisers for majors, minors, and pre-health areas and pre-law, contact the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall, 402-472-4190, http://ascweb.unl.edu/advisingcenter.html.

ACADEMIC PROGRAMS & POLICIES

Course Exclusions & Restrictions

Course Exclusions

No credit for graduation is allowed for non-college level courses or for courses that deal primarily with the development of skills including the following:

Driver training education
Industrial arts (including courses concerned primarily with manual skills, tools, machines, or industrial processes and design) For example at UNL: ALEC 101, ALEC 103, ALEC 104, ALEC 109, ALEC 122, ALEC 201, ALEC 203, ALEC 204, ALEC 205, ALEC 242, ALEC 253, ALEC 301, ALEC 340.
Any introduction computer course training in DOS, word processing, spread-sheets, data base management, or other business software packages (CSCE 137 or BSAD 150 or AGRI 271)
MATH 100A

Course Restrictions

Students majoring in the College of Arts and Sciences may use courses in the following areas toward their degree within the following limits:

Maximum 12 hours religion courses that advocate the doctrine or belief of a particular faith. This 12 hour limit does not apply to religious studies courses whose method and approach conforms to the standards of critical scholarship in the academic study of the humanities and social sciences.
Maximum 15 hours of C- and D grades are transferable from colleges outside UNL. The C- and D grades cannot apply to majors or minors. All C- and D grades from UNO or UNK may be transferred but they are not applicable to a major or minor.
Maximum 60 hours accepted from a community college.
Maximum 30 hours of clinical courses.
Maximum 16 hours of applied music lessons and/or music ensemble.
Maximum 4 hours Activity PE, Athletic Practice, or Basic Military Science with a maximum of 1 credit hour per semester.
Maximum 12 hours total from any combination of the following areas:
First Aid (NUTR 170 at UNL)
Orientation and Study Skills. For example at UNL: AECN 100, ASCI 107, ASCI 181, BIOC 101, BIOS 150, BIOS 160, CHEM 101, CYAF 150, EDPS 150, EDPS 209, FDST 107, FITN 160, FITN 170, NRES 101, NUTR 150, PSYC 100, PSYC 150, TEAC 210, TLMT 127, TMFD 101, VBMS 101
Military Science, Naval Science, or Aerospace Studies. (This restriction does not apply to cross-listed courses between military science, naval science, or aerospace studies and departments of the College of Arts and Sciences.)
Maximum 15 hours athletic coaching
Any restrictions noted specifically by departments. Credit towards the degree may be earned in only one course, including honors sections, from each group of courses listed below:

BIOS 313 or BIOS 314

CHEM 105, CHEM 109, CHEM 111, CHEM 113, CHEM 195

CHEM 116 or CHEM 221

CHEM 251 and more than 1 cr of CHEM 263

CHEM 471 or CHEM 481

CSCE 252A or CSCE 155N

CSCE 252A or ELEC 121

CSCE 340 or CSCE 480

ECON 210 or ECON 211 and ECON 212

ECON 215, CRIM 300, EDPS 459 or STAT 218 (was STAT 180)

FREN 201 and FREN 202, or FREN 210

GEOL 100 or GEOL 101 or GEOL 101H

GEOL 103 or GEOL 105

GERM 201 and GERM 202, or GERM 210

GREK 102 or GREK 151

LATN 102 or LATN 201

MATH 101 and/or MATH 102 or MATH 103

MATH 104 or MATH 106

MATH 300

MATH 301

MATH 340 or MECH 480

PHYS 141 or PHYS 151

PHYS 151 or MSYM 109

SOCI 205 or CRIM 251

SOCI 209 or CRIM 355

SOCI 311 or CRIM 337

SOCI 474 or CRIM 413

SPAN 201 and SPAN 202, or SPAN 210

For transfer students, course exclusions and restrictions will be determined on the Evaluation of Transfer credits.

Credit by Examination

Through study or experience that parallels a University of Nebraska–Lincoln course, a regularly enrolled University student may feel prepared to pass an examination on the course content of a specific course for credit in that course. To apply for credit, a student should:

1. Consult with the department chair.

2. Obtain a Credit by Examination Form at the Records Office, 107 Canfield Administration Building, 402-472-3649. Current enrollment in the University must also be verified.

3. Secure the approval signature from the department chair, instructor, and the dean of the student’s college. The Dean’s signature can be obtained in the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather.

4. Secure the bursar’s receipt for payment of the appropriate fee per course for credit by examination. Currently, the fee is one-half the resident tuition rate.

5. Present the completed form to the instructor designated by the department chair. The instructor will give the examination and report the results on the Credit by Examination Form to the Admissions Office, Alexander Building, 402-472-0130.

Examination for credit through UNL departments may be taken only by currently enrolled students. A student is not permitted to receive credit by examination in a course which is a prerequisite for a course already taken unless the course and its prerequisites cover essentially different subject matter.

The College of Arts and Sciences also gives credit for the subject and general examinations of the College Level Examination Program (CLEP) and the Advanced Placement (AP) Program administered by the College Entrance Examination Board. See the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall, for current policy regarding CLEP and AP examinations.

Dual Degrees

Two Degrees from Arts and Sciences

A graduate who holds the bachelor of arts degree may earn the bachelor of science degree by completing an additional year of work in residence taking at least 30 more semester hours of course work for a minimum of 150 hours. The student must complete all degree requirements for the second degree, including the scientific base. A graduate who holds the bachelor of science degree may earn the bachelor of arts degree by completing another year of work in residence taking at least 30 semester hours of additional course work for a minimum of 150 hours. The student must complete all degree requirements for the second degree.

Two Degrees from UNL

A graduate who holds a bachelors degree from another college at UNL may earn the bachelor of science or bachelor of arts degree from the College of Arts and Sciences by completing an additional year of work in residence taking at least 30 more semester hours of course work beyond the first degree. The student must complete all degree requirements for the arts and sciences degree.

Intercollege Studies

With College of Fine and Performing Arts: A student in the College of Arts and Sciences pursuing a bachelor of arts degree with a major in arts and sciences may also complete a bachelor of arts major in the College of Fine and Performing Arts. In addition, a student in the College of Fine and Performing Arts pursuing a bachelor of arts degree with a major in fine and performing arts may also complete a bachelor of arts major in the College of Arts and Sciences. The student must complete all degree requirements and a major in the home college and a second bachelor of arts major in the visiting college.

With College of Journalism and Mass Communications: A student in the College of Journalism and Mass Communications pursuing a bachelor of journalism degree may also complete a second major in the College of Arts and Sciences. In addition to ACE and College of Journalism and Mass Communications requirements, students will be expected to meet all College of Arts and Sciences distribution requirements and major requirements. Because students choosing this option will not be earning a degree from arts and sciences, they will not be eligible for arts and sciences-based scholarships and aid, but they will be eligible for consideration for Phi Beta Kappa.

Transfer Students with a Non-UNL Degree

A transfer student who has received a bachelors degree from another institution must complete at least 30 hours of credit in residence at UNL in addition to transfer credit. Students must complete at least half of their major course work including 6 hours above 299 in their major, and 15 of the 30 hours required above 299 in residence. The student must complete all degree requirements for the arts and sciences degree.

Honors Program

The College of Arts and Sciences encourages qualified students to participate in the University Honors Program. In addition, several departments of the College of Arts and Sciences offer special honors sections of regular freshman courses to meet the needs of students with superior preparation in those subjects. In some departments such students may then progress more rapidly into advanced courses.

Student Recognition

Dean’s List

The College recognizes students for academic achievement during the fall and spring semesters by placement on the College Dean’s List. To qualify for the Dean’s List in the College of Arts and Sciences, students must complete 12 credit hours of course work (courses must be started and completed in one semester) by the census date of the grade reports and attain a minimum semester grade point average of 3.700. The following do not qualify as part of the 12 credit hours: Pass/No Pass credit, transfer hours, removals of incompletes, and grade changes submitted after the census grade reports.

Degrees with Distinction

In recognition of outstanding academic excellence, the College recommends the bachelors degree With Distinction, With High Distinction, and With Highest Distinction. The recommendations are made by the Committee on Student Academic Distinction, Awards and Appeals. To be recommended for distinction, candidates must fulfill the specific criteria for Highest Distinction, High Distinction, or Distinction, in addition to all of the general criteria and procedures applicable to all distinction classifications.

Information regarding specific criteria and forms are available in 107 and 1223 Oldfather Hall and can also be found on the college website at http://cas.unl.edu/distinction.shtml..

College Scholarships

The College of Arts and Sciences Dean’s Office, in conjunction with the College Committee on Academic Distinction and Awards for Students and the program adviser (when appropriate), chooses recipients for College scholarships. This group also recommends students for certain scholarships awarded by the Office of Scholarships and Financial Aid. To be considered for any college scholarships the Scholarship Application for Current Undergraduate Students must be completed. The application is only available on-line in MyRED from November to February 1st each academic year.

Many of the College scholarships require demonstrated financial need. To provide information regarding financial need, the Free Application for Federal Student Aid (FAFSA), found at www.fafsa.ed.gov, must be completed. A complete list of the scholarships awarded by the College and further information about the college scholarship process can be found on the college website at http://cas.unl.edu/scholarships.shtml.

Departmental Scholarships

There are numerous awards and scholarships earmarked for specific majors, all of which are administered individually by the departments in the College of Arts and Sciences. To find out which scholarships you might be eligible for and the procedures for applying, please contact the appropriate Department for information.

University Scholarships

The Office of Scholarships and Financial Aid administer numerous funds. Consideration for these scholarships is based on submission of the Scholarship Application for Current Undergraduate Students. This is an on-line application that can be found in MyRed from early November until February 1 each year.

Other Scholarships and Fellowships

Edythe Wiebers International Studies Program Scholarship. Application forms can be found on the Education Abroad website at http://educationabroad.unl.edu.

There are many national and international fellowship competitions. Visit the Office of Fellowships website (http://unl.edu/fellowships) for more information.

International Study/Education Abroad

International Opportunities

The College supports the following international interdisciplinary programs offering a major or a minor: African American and African Studies, Asian Studies, European Studies, Global Studies, and Latino and Latin American Studies. Departments and faculty in the College of Arts and Sciences are also actively involved as sponsors, teachers and leaders in many of the numerous education abroad programs administered by the Education Abroad Office.

The College encourages students to study overseas as part of their University experience. The University participates in exchange and several formal education abroad programs world-wide and Nebraska Semester Abroad. The Education Abroad Office can arrange for individuals to earn University credit for study at foreign universities. The Education Abroad Office helps students find opportunities to study, intern, research, and do service learning abroad. Visit http://educationabroad.unl.edu.

Senior Check/Degree Audit

In the term after which a student has completed 85 hours, Graduation Services in the Office of the University Registrar, 109 Canfield Administration Building, will perform a “senior check.” Students will be provided with a copy of the senior check. This check will inform students about the requirements that still need to be fulfilled in their chosen degree program. Questions about remaining requirements should be directed to the chief adviser for the major or the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall.

Each student who expects to receive a diploma must file an application of candidacy for the diploma in Graduation Services, 109 Canfield Administration Building. Announcements about deadline dates are posted on bulletin boards and the online University calendar, and are printed in the Daily Nebraskan.

Students are responsible for informing the Graduation Services of their graduation plans, including their addresses; the manner in which they are completing their requirements such as by correspondence, by clearance of incompletes, by enrollment at another institution, by taking special examinations, etc.; and of any later revision of such plans. Failure to follow this procedure may cause postponement of graduation until a later semester.

Classification of Students

Freshman Program

The first-year program is designed to give students a broad basis for future study. It includes English composition, a foreign language, and courses in science, the humanities, social sciences or mathematics for a total of about 12-15 hours per semester. During this year, the student will progress toward meeting University ACE requirements and will have an opportunity to explore various areas of study while starting or deciding upon a major. With the help of New Student Enrollment and their academic advisers, students choose specific courses according to their needs and interests.

Class Standing

Sophomore Standing. For admission to sophomore standing a student must have completed all of the College entrance requirements, earned a minimum of 27 semester hours of credit, and attained a total grade point average of at least C.

Junior Standing. A student has junior standing after meeting the requirements for sophomore standing and completing 53 semester hours of credit.

Senior Standing. A student has senior standing after meeting the requirements for junior standing and completing 89 semester hours of credit.

Substitutions and Waivers

Special requests concerning degree programs, including inquiries about exceptions to degree requirements, waivers, and substitutions should be made to the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall.

ACE REQUIREMENTS

Consistent with the mission and values of the University, ACE is based on a shared set of four institutional objectives and 10 student learning outcomes. The ACE program was approved by faculty in all eight undergraduate colleges and endorsed by the Faculty Senate, the student government, and the Academic Planning Committee in January 2008 for implementation in the fall 2009. ACE aligns with current national initiatives in general education.

Key characteristics of ACE demonstrate the benefits of the program to students:

Students receive a broad education with exposure to multiple disciplines, critical life skills and important reasoning, inquiry, and civic capacities.
ACE is simple and transparent for students, faculty and advisers. Students complete the equivalent of 3 credit hours for each of the ten student learning outcomes.
Students connect and integrate their ACE experiences with their selected major.
Students can transfer all ACE certified courses across colleges within the institution to meet the ACE requirement and any course from outside the institution that is directly equivalent to a UNL ACE-certified course. Courses from outside institutions without direct equivalents may be considered with appropriate documentation for ACE credit (see academic adviser).

ACE allows faculty to assess and improve their effectiveness and facilitate students’ learning.

ACE Institutional Objectives and Student Learning Outcomes

To meet the ACE Program requirement, a student will complete the equivalent of 3 credit hours for each of the ten ACE Student Learning Outcomes (a total of 30 ACE credit hours). See the ACE website at: http://ace.unl.edu for the most current information and the most recently certified courses.

BULLETIN TO USE

Students must fulfill the requirements stated in the bulletin for the academic year in which they are first admitted to and enrolled as a degree-seeking student at UNL. In consultation with advisers, a student may choose to follow a subsequent bulletin for any academic year in which they are admitted to and enrolled as a degree-seeking student at UNL in the College of Arts and Sciences. Students must complete all degree requirements from a single bulletin year. Beginning in 1990-1991 the bulletin which a student follows for degree requirements may not be more than 10 years old at the time of graduation.

COLLEGE DEGREE REQUIREMENTS

College General Education Requirements

The College of Arts and Sciences distribution requirements are designed to further the purposes of liberal education by encouraging study in several different areas. Courses satisfying these requirements may impart specialized knowledge or broadly connect the subject matter to other areas of knowledge.

All requirements are in addition to University ACE requirements. A student may not use a single course to satisfy more than one of the following five distribution requirements. A student cannot use a single course to satisfy both an ACE outcome and a College distribution requirement. A student cannot use a course from their major to satisfy the Breadth Requirement (F), but may apply an ancillary requirement of the primary major or a course from their second major toward this requirement. Independent study or reading courses and internships cannot be used to satisfy distribution requirements. To see a complete list of excluded courses, run a degree audit through MyRED.

Courses from interdisciplinary programs will count in the same area as courses from the home/cross-listed department(s).

Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science (16 credits + Language)

A. Written Communication: 3 hours

To be selected from courses approved for ACE outcome 1.

B. Natural, Physical and Mathematical Sciences: 4 hours

Must include one lab in the natural or physical sciences. Lab courses may be selected from biochemistry, biological sciences, chemistry, geology, meteorology, physics and astronomy, geography*, and anthropology*. All other courses select from: biochemistry, biological sciences, chemistry, computer science and engineering, geology, meteorology, mathematics, physics and astronomy, and statistics.

* See degree audit or College of Arts and Sciences adviser for approved geography and anthropology lab courses, approved non-lab psychology courses, or courses cross-listed with an Arts and Sciences department.

C. Humanities: 3 hours

Select from classics*, English, history, modern languages and literatures*, philosophy, and religious studies*.

*Language courses numbered 210 or below apply only for the foreign language requirement.

D. Social Sciences: 3 hours

Select from anthropology*, communication studies, geography*, political science, psychology*, or sociology

*See degree audit or College of Arts and Sciences adviser for list of natural/physical science courses in anthropology, geography, and psychology that do not apply as social sciences.

E. Languages Classical and Modern: 0-6 hours

Fulfilled by the completion of the 6-credit-hour second-year sequence in a single foreign language in one of the following departments: Classics and religious studies, modern languages and literatures, or anthropology. Instruction is currently available in Arabic, Chinese, Czech, French, German, Greek, Japanese, Latin, Omaha, Russian, and Spanish. A student who has completed the fourth-year level of one foreign language in high school is exempt from the languages requirement.

F. Additional Breadth Requirement (may not be used toward the primary major; may apply toward ancillary requirements and second majors): 3 hours

Select from natural, physical and mathematical sciences (Area B), humanities (Area C), or social sciences (Area D).

Scientific Base

In addition to University ACE requirements and the College distribution requirements, the bachelor of science degree requires students to complete 60 semester hours in mathematics and natural sciences, including:

1. At least one of the following quantitative courses: CSCE 235, MATH 104, PHIL 211, or any mathematics or statistics course numbered 106 or above, except MATH 200 and MATH 201.

2. At least one natural or physical science course and at least 1 credit of laboratory work, taken as part of a course or separately, from the following departments: biochemistry, biological sciences, chemistry, geosciences, or physics and astronomy, ANTH 242/ANTH 242L, ENVR 201, GEOG 155, and the following geography techniques courses also apply: GEOG 317, GEOG 412, GEOG 414, GEOG 415, GEOG 417, GEOG 418, GEOG 419, GEOG 420, GEOG 422, GEOG 425, and GEOG 432. Other courses that may be applied toward the 60 hour total include courses in actuarial science for which calculus or above is a prerequisite and up to 12 hours of scientific and technical courses offered by other colleges with approval of the academic adviser.

Foreign Languages/Language Requirement

Languages Exemption Policy

UNL and Arts and Sciences will exempt or waive students from the UNL entrance requirement of two years of the same foreign language or from the College’s language distribution requirement based on documentation only. The following are the options and procedures for documentation:

High School Transcripts

1. For the University entrance requirements, students must show an official high school transcript with two or more years of the same foreign language in high school.

2. For the College of Arts and Sciences College Distribution Requirements Area 5 languages requirement, students must show an official high school transcript with four or more years of the same foreign language in high school, or show evidence of graduation from a non-English-speaking foreign high school.

3. For the College of Arts and Sciences College Distribution Requirements Area 5 languages requirement, students whose native language is not English must show English as a Second Language study on an official high school transcript. Four years of ESL at the high school level (9th, 10th, 11th and 12th grades) will be the basis for a waiver of the Area I Language requirement.

Proficiency Examination at UNL

1. For the University entrance requirement, students who do not have transcript documentation can request to take a proficiency exam in the language. (This is not the same test as the Modern Languages Placement Exam.) However, UNL will provide testing only in the languages it teaches. Currently, these languages are:

Arabic

French

German

Spanish

Russian

Czech

Japanese

Chinese

The Department of Modern Languages will oversee the test and provide written documentation to the Admissions Office that the student has passed the proficiency test at the 102 level.

2. For the College of Arts and Sciences College Distribution Requirements Area 5 requirement, the Department of Modern Languages will oversee the test at the 202 level. If the student passes the test, the department will sign the College Request for Waiver form and indicate the level of proficiency. The form is then forwarded to the Arts and Sciences Advising Center for approval.

Distance Education

1. For the University entrance requirement, students without transcript documentation who claim proficiency in a language not taught at UNL, have the option of seeking out a distance education program in languages. If the student completes the equivalent of 102 from an approved distance education program, the student will meet the UNL entrance requirement. The student must have the course work approved before he/she takes/completes the course as equivalent to 102 by the modern languages department. The student then completes the course and has the distance education program send the transcript to the Admissions Office.

2. For the College of Arts and Sciences College Distribution Requirements Area 5 languages, the student can seek out a distance education program and complete the equivalent of the 202-level course. The student must submit the request on the College Request for Substitution form and have the course work approved by the Department of Modern Languages and the assistant dean for Advising Services. The student then completes the course and has the distance education program send the transcript to the Admissions Office.

Third Language Option

If a student demonstrates knowledge of two foreign languages at the 102 level, the College of Arts and Sciences may consider waiving two semesters of the four semester College Distribution Requirements Area 5 languages requirement. If this waiver were granted, the student would then be required to complete 101 and 102 in another (3rd language) at UNL.

Minimum Hours Required for Graduation

A minimum of 120 semester hours of credit is required for graduation from the College of Arts and Sciences. A total grade point average of at least 2.0 is required.

Grade Rules

Restrictions on C- and D Grades

The College will accept no more than 15 semester hours of C- and D grades from other schools except for UNO and UNK. No transfer C- and D grades can be applied toward requirements in a major or a minor. No UNL C- and D grades can be applied toward requirements in a major or a minor.

Pass/No Pass Privilege

University regulations for the Pass/No Pass (P/N) privilege state:

The Pass/No Pass option is designed for your use by seeking to expand your intellectual horizons by taking courses in areas where you may have had minimal preparation.
For students in Arts and Sciences, the University regulations for Pass/No Pass apply as follows:

1. Neither the P nor the N grade contribute to your GPA.

2. P is interpreted to mean C or above.

3. A change to or from a Pass/No Pass may be made until mid-term (1/2 of the course).

4. The Pass/No Pass or grade registration cannot conflict with the policy of the professor, department, college, or University governing the grading option.

5. Changing to or from Pass/No Pass requires using the MyRED system to change the grading option or filing a Drop/Add form with the Office of the University Registrar, 107 Canfield Administration Building. After mid-term of the course, a student registered for Pass/No Pass cannot change to a grade registration unless the Pass/No Pass registration is in conflict with the policy of the professor, department, college, or University governing Pass/No Pass. The Pass/No Pass grading option is not available to students on academic probation unless the course is offered only on a Pass/No Pass basis.

6. The Pass/No Pass grading option cannot be used for the removal of C- or D or F grades.

Pass/No Pass privileges in the College of Arts and Sciences are extended to students according to the following additional regulations:

1. Pass/No Pass hours can count toward fulfillment of University ACE requirements and college distribution requirements up to the 24-hour maximum.

2. Many Arts and Sciences departments and programs do not allow courses in the major or minor to be taken Pass/No Pass; students should refer to the department’s or program’s section of the bulletin for clarification. By college rule, departments can allow up to 6 hours of Pass/No Pass in the major or minor.

3. Freshmen and sophomores may enroll for no more than 6 hours of P/N work per semester.

4. Departments may specify that certain courses of theirs can be taken only on a P/N basis.

5. The college will permit no more than a total of 24 semester hours of P/N grades to be applied toward degree requirements. This total includes all Pass grades earned at UNL and other U.S. schools. NOTE: This 24-hour limit is more restrictive than the University regulation.

Students who wish to apply P/N hours to their major and minor(s) must obtain approval on a form that is available in the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall.

Grading Appeals

A student who feels that he/she has been unfairly graded must ordinarily take the following sequential steps in a timely manner, usually by initiating the appeal in the semester following the awarding of the grade:

1. Talk with the instructor concerned. Most problems are resolved at this point.

2. Talk to the instructor’s department chairperson.

3. Take the case to the Grading Appeal Committee of the department concerned. The Committee should be contacted through the department chairperson.

4. Take the case to the College Grading Appeals Committee by contacting the Dean’s Office, 1223 Oldfather Hall.

Course Level Requirements

Courses Numbered above 299

Thirty of the 120 semester hours of credit must be in courses numbered above 299. Of the 30 hours above 299, 15 hours (1/2) must be completed in residence at UNL. NOTE: ALEC 397E and ALEC 397K do not count toward these 30 hours.

Graduate Courses

Seniors in the University who have obtained in advance the approval of the dean for Graduate Studies may receive up to 12 hours credit for graduate courses taken in addition to the courses necessary to complete their undergraduate work, provided that such credits are earned within the calendar year prior to receipt of the baccalaureate. For procedures, inquire at the Office of Graduate Studies.

Course work taken prior to receipt of the baccalaureate may not always be accepted for transfer to other institutions as graduate work.

Residency

Residency Requirement and Open Enrollment and Summer Independent Study Courses

Students must complete at least 30 of the 120 total hours for their degree at UNL. Students must complete at least 1/2 of their major course work including 6 hours above 299 in their major, and 15 of the 30 hours required above 299 in residence. Credit earned during education abroad may be used toward the residency requirement if students register through UNL and participate in prior-approved education abroad programs. UNL open enrollment and summer independent study courses count toward residence.

DEGREES & MAJORS

Degree Programs and Areas of Study

The College of Arts and Sciences offers curricula leading to the degrees of bachelor of arts and bachelor of science.

Cross-listed Course Policy

The College of Arts and Sciences recognizes cross-listed courses as equivalent for the purposes of degree requirements. Therefore, a course taken under one department which is cross-listed can be used in all the majors and minors affected by all the cross-listings of the course.

Requirements for the Bachelor of Arts Degree

Students who wish to graduate with a bachelor of arts degree must complete the College graduation requirements, the University ACE requirements, the College of Arts and Sciences distribution requirements, the requirements for a major, and the requirements for a minor or minors if required by the major.

Requirements for the Bachelor of Science Degree

The bachelor of science degree is characterized by a strong prescriptive major, an essential scientific base, and the inclusion of a general liberal education as an important aspect of the degree. Requirements for the BS are the same as those for the BA, with the following exceptions:

1. The major must include between 50-70 credit hours including required collateral courses in other departments. For students who wish to acquire two majors in two departments, the departments will be asked to make some accommodation for the students.

2. In addition to the College of Arts and Sciences distribution requirements, the bachelor of science degree requires students to complete 60 semester hours in the natural and mathematical sciences. (See scientific base information under College General Education Requirements.)

Areas of Study for the Major

Students are advised to choose a major before the end of the sophomore year to avoid extending the period of time necessary to complete the degree. By gaining a deeper knowledge of one field, the student will further his or her general liberal education, prepare for a career in his or her specialization, and possibly advance to graduate work or a professional program. It is sometimes possible, through careful planning, for students to complete more than one undergraduate major. Students should consult their advisers about this possibility. The student who majors in more than one field will be assigned to an adviser in each field.

If a student receives a grade lower than C in a course in his or her chosen major, it will not count toward the major.

Students must complete at least 1/2 of the course work in their chosen major field in residence including 6 hours above 299, regardless of the number of hours transferred.

Areas of Study

The College of Arts and Sciences offers study toward the major and minor in many areas.

A summary of the major areas of study for degrees offered by the College of Arts and Sciences includes:

Bachelor of Arts and Bachelor of Science

Actuarial Science

Anthropology

Biochemistry (BS only)

Biological Sciences

Chemistry

Classical Languages

Classics & Religious Studies

Communication Studies

Computer Science

Economics

English

Environmental Studies

Ethnic Studies

European Studies

Film Studies

French

Geography

Geology

German

Global Studies

Great Plains Studies

History

Individualized Program of Studies

Latin American Studies

Mathematics

Medieval and Renaissance Studies

Meteorology-Climatology (BS only)

Microbiology (BS only)

Philosophy

Physics

Plant Biology

Political Science

Psychology

Russian

Sociology

Spanish

Speech-Language Pathology and Audiology

University Studies

Women’s and Gender Studies

MINORS & AREAS OF SPECIALIZATIONS OFFERED

The Minor

The requirement of minors is variable within the College and depends upon the student’s major department. Some departments require either one or two minors, and other departments require none. Two minor plans are available.

Plan A. Students must complete at least 6 hours of course work in a Plan A minor in residence regardless of the number of hours transferred.

Plan B. Plan B minors consist of either two minors which are completed with fewer hours in each subject than required for a single Plan A minor or two majors and one Plan B minor. Hour requirements for individual Plan B minors are stated in each department’s or program’s listings.

Minors in Other Colleges

A student with a major leading to a bachelor of science or bachelor of arts degree in the College of Arts and Sciences who wants to obtain a minor in another college should use the following procedure in making his/her request:

1. In consultation with the student’s major adviser, prepare the list of courses required for the other college’s minor as indicated in the bulletin.

2. Submit the College-Degree-Major-Adviser Change form to the College of Arts and Sciences Advising Center prior to the deadline for submitting the application for graduation.

Students who have questions related to the minor after it is declared should consult an adviser in the college through which it is offered. The minor will be recorded on the student’s transcript.

Minors Offered by Arts and Sciences

Actuarial Science

Aerospace Studies

African American Studies

African Studies

Anthropology

Archaeology

Asian Studies

Biochemistry

Biological Sciences

Chemistry

Classical Languages

Classics

Communication Studies

Computational Biology and Bioinformatics

Computer Science

Conflict and Conflict Resolution

Czech

Digital Humanities

Economics

English

Environmental Studies

Ethnic Studies

European Studies

Film Studies

French

Geography

Geology

German

Global Security Studies

Global Studies

Great Plains Studies

Greek (See Classical Languages)

History

Human Rights and Humanitarian Affairs

Humanities in Medicine

Individualized Program of Studies

Japanese

Jewish Studies

Latin (See Classical Languages)

Latin American Studies

Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender, Queer/Sexuality Studies

Mathematics

Medieval and Renaissance Studies

Meteorology-Climatology

Native American Studies

Philosophy

Physics

Plant Biology

Political Science

Psychology

Public Policy Analysis and Evaluation (Certificate)

Religious Studies

Russian

Sociology

Spanish

Statistics

U.S. Latina/Latino Studies (See Latin American Studies)

University Studies

Women’s and Gender Studies

Pre-Health, Pre-Law, and Combined Degree Programs

Pre-Chiropractic

Pre-Clinical Laboratory Science

Pre-Clinical Perfusion Science

Pre-Cytotechnology

Pre-Dental Hygiene

Pre-Dentistry

Pre-Law

Pre-Medicine

Pre-Mortuary Science

Pre-Nursing

Pre-Occupational Therapy

Pre-Optometry

Pre-Pharmacy

Pre-Physical Therapy

Pre-Physician Assistant

Pre-Radiation Science Technology

Pre-Veterinary Science

Business Administration

ADMISSION

College Admission

The entrance requirements for the College of Business Administration are the same as the UNL General Admission Requirements.

Admission Deficiencies/Removal of Deficiencies

Students admitted to the College of Business Administration with core course deficiencies will be advised to remove these deficiencies according to the Office of Admissions’ Removal of Core Course Admission Deficiency guidelines.
College-level course work taken to remove deficiencies MAY NOT be used to meet degree requirements in CBA.

ADVISING

Academic Advising

Dean’s Office for Undergraduate Programs

Students are encouraged to obtain information and advice through the Dean’s Office for Undergraduate Programs, CBA 114.

The staff, which includes both professional staff and peer advisers, are well trained, easily accessible, and can provide academic counseling and answer questions on specific degree requirements, transfer credits, prerequisites, changes in major or college, waivers, procedures or policies, and other available campus services.

Professional Staff: Mark Davis, Jeff Burdic, Betsy Klemme, D’Vee Buss, Megan Friesen, Alison TePoel, Erin Burnette, Ashley Wegener

Career Services. While staff and faculty advisers may assist in career advising, the College works closely with the University’s Career Services Office to provide assistance to CBA students. Students should schedule time each semester to visit with the Career Coaches located in CBA 138.

Student Responsibility

The University of Nebraska–Lincoln and the College of Business Administration are committed to providing effective academic advising to students.

Academic advisers are available to assist students in assessing educational goals, planning programs of study, understanding program requirements, and following policies and procedures.

Students are ultimately responsible for fulfilling all the requirements of the curriculum in which they are enrolled.

Students are responsible for initiating advising contacts and preparing for advising sessions.

The mentoring relationship between academic advisers and students is confidential and is strengthened by advisers’ listening with understanding to student concerns.

Students are expected to take responsibility for a successful university experience and effective advising session. For this to occur the student must:

Participate in New Student Enrollment, priority registration programs, and any other University/College programs designed to enhance the student-life experience.
Review My Degree Audit Report each semester and each time you make a change to your schedule. Schedule appointments with advisers well in advance of priority registration and at other times as needed. Keep appointments and be punctual, or call to reschedule if necessary.
Read the appropriate sections of the Undergraduate Bulletin.
Identify specific questions to address prior to meeting with an adviser and be prepared to do long-term planning.
Provide honest and accurate information to the adviser regarding any concerns, questions, special needs, deficiencies or barriers that might affect academic success.
Follow academic policies and procedures and meet academic calendar deadlines (e.g. registration, fee payment, degree audit, filing for degree, etc.).
Know and complete program requirements.
Seek assistance from the various student support services provided by the University and College.
Immediately notify the University of any change in postal address, email address, and/or phone number.

ACADEMIC PROGRAMS & POLICIES

Academic Load

A maximum of 19 credit hours (including online and independent study courses through On-line and Distance Education) may be taken each semester without special permission from the Dean’s Office for Undergraduate Programs. The summer sessions have a maximum load of 15 hours. The three week session limit is 3 hours and each five week session has a 7 hour limit.
A minimum of 12 credit hours must be taken each semester to remain a full time student.

To complete the requirements for a degree in eight semesters, a student must earn an average of 15 credit hours each semester. Most students need a minimum of two hours of preparation for every hour in class, so a schedule of 15 credit hours is actually equivalent to a 45 hour a week job (15 classroom + 30 preparation).

The student who must work or one who may need additional study time, should plan to take a lighter load and consider taking some summer sessions or an extra semester or two to complete the work required for a degree. In the event that a student’s cumulative grade point average falls below 2.5, a lighter academic load may be required.

Course Exclusions and Restrictions

No credit for graduation is allowed for non-college level courses or for courses that deal primarily with the development of skills including the following:

BSAD 150
LIBR 110
MATH 100A or any math credit lower than 100A
Driver training education
Industrial arts (including courses concerned primarily with manual skills, tools, machines, or industrial processes and design)
Vocational and Adult Education classes
Any introductory computer course training in word processing, spread-sheets, data base management, or other business software packages
Certificate program credit (such as the Nebraska Bankers Association, CEP credit, etc.)
Courses required for the business minor (for non-business students) cannot be used towards the BSBA degree. This would include ACCT 200, ECON 200, BLAW 300, FINA 300, MNGT 300, MRKT 300.

Maximum/Minimum hour restrictions:

Maximum semester hour restrictions:

Transfer Hour Restrictions

14 hours of military credit
6 hours Pass/No Pass (allowable only as electives)
The college limits the transfer of credit into the BSBA degree to 60 semester hours of credit from two-year schools and international schools. Students who have transferred 60 hours of credit from these institutions may not go back and enroll in additional transfer hours after they begin their studies in the College of Business Administration.

A maximum of 15 hours of business course work may transfer towards the Business Core and Business Electives from another institution. Actuarial Science students may additionally transfer STAT 462 and STAT 463.
A maximum of 3 hours of business course work may transfer towards the Business Core Intermediate level.
A maximum of 3 hours of business course work may transfer towards the Business Core Advanced level.
Any variation to the above rules may only occur through an appeal made through an adviser in the Office of Undergraduate Programs.

Minimum semester hour restrictions:

120 hours of applicable degree credit for the degree
60 hours of business course work
45 hours of business core course work completed at UNL (with further BCI and BCA restrictions)
75% of required business course work must be taken at UNL (with further BCI and BCA restrictions)

Other Course Restrictions/Exclusions:

Any restrictions noted specifically by departments. Credit towards the degree may be earned in only one course, including honors section from each group of courses listed below:

ACCT 200 or ACCT 201 and ACCT 202

BIOS 312 or AGRO 360

BIOS 313 or BIOS 314

BLAW 300 or BLAW 371 and/or BLAW 372

CHEM 105, CHEM 109, CHEM 111, CHEM 113, CHEM 195

CHEM 116 or CHEM 221

CHEM 251 and more than 1 cr of CHEM 263

CHEM 471 or CHEM 481

CSCE 252D or CSCE 155N

CSCE 252D or ELEC 121

CSCE 340 or CSCE 480

ECON 200 or ECON 211 and ECON 212

ECON 210 or ECON 211 and ECON 212

ECON 215, CRIM 300, EDPS 459 or STAT 218

FINA 300 or FINA 361

FREN 201 and FREN 202, or FREN 210

GEOG 150 and/or GEOG 152 or GEOG 155

GEOL 100 or GEOL 101 or GEOL 101H

GEOL 103 or GEOL 105

GERM 201 and GERM 202, or GERM 210

GREK 102 or GREK 151

LATN 102 or LATN 201

MATH 101 and/or MATH 102 or MATH 103

MATH 104 or MATH 106

MATH 200 or MATH 300

MATH 201 or MATH 301

MATH 340 or MECH 480

MNGT 300 or MNGT 320

MRKT 300 or MRKT 341

PHYS 141 or PHYS 151

PHYS 151 or MSYM 109

SOCI 205 or CRIM 251

SOCI 311 or CRIM 337

SOCI 474 or CRIM 413

SPAN 201 and SPAN 202, or SPAN 210

SPAN 300 or SPAN 303 and SPAN 304

Maintenance of 2.5 cumulative grade point average
A 2.5 cumulative grade point average is required to enroll in ACCT 201 and ACCT 202, ECON 215, BLAW 371, BLAW 372, FINA 361, MNGT 331, MNGT 360, MNGT 475, MNGT 350/SCMS 350, MRKT 350, and MRKT 341.
Grades of C or better are required to transfer courses from other institutions.
Grades of C or better in specified prerequisite course work (i.e. MATH 101 to enroll in MATH 104; ACCT 201 to enroll in ACCT 202, etc.)

Credit Rules

Credit by Examination

Credit by examination is generally not available for courses offered by the College of Business Administration, with the exceptions noted.

Students who feel substantial work experience should satisfy course requirements may approach the appropriate school or department for possible credit by exam options. Credit, however, is not simply given for work experience.

BSAD 150 Credit by Examination is offered several times each year for BSAD 150. See http://cba.unl.edu/academics/busadmin/resources/bsad150/index.aspx

The College Level Examination Program (CLEP) is available for students wishing to test out of Macro- and Microeconomics and Principles of Marketing and several non-business courses. Additional information can be found at: http://www.unl.edu/ous/student_programs/credit.shtml

Dual Degrees

Students may obtain a dual degree by simultaneously enrolling in and completing requirements in the College of Business Administration and another college on campus. Students will need to consult with both colleges to ensure all requirements are satisfied.

Secondary Teaching Certification

Teaching certification is granted by the Nebraska Department of Education after completing endorsement requirements in one or more approved area(s). A list of approved endorsement areas can be found under “Endorsements” in the College of Education and Human Sciences section. Given the number of elective course options in the business program and with early planning and careful selection, students may integrate the certification requirements with CBA graduation requirements. Students interested in obtaining a teaching certificate should contact the director of the College of Education and Human Sciences Student Services Center, 105 Henzlik Hall.

Honors Program

The College of Business Administration participates in the Nebraska Honors Program both in and out of the classroom. University Honors Program courses are accepted to fulfill degree requirements and the College works with departments and individual students to design upper-level course work of specific interest to honors students. For additional information concerning the program, see “Nebraska Honors.”

In addition to the university-wide Nebraska Honors Program, the College of Business Administration also offers the CBA Honors Academy and the Jeffrey Raikes School of Computer Science and Management, two cohort-based honors programs. Students accepted into these cohort-based programs are also automatically accepted into the Nebraska Honors Program.

CBA Honors Academy

The CBA Honors Academy is a unique cohort-based program for high-ability students with demonstrated leadership potential. The goal of the Academy is to develop critical thinking, problem-solving and communications skills to prepare graduates to be strategic decision-makers and innovators. The Academy combines a rigorous curriculum (including approximately 40 credit hours of cohort-based courses), with leadership training, co-curricular activities and corporate involvement. Academy students will complete MNGT 475H Honors Business Policies and Strategies in place of the thesis requirement for the UNL Honors Program.

Students interested in learning more about the CBA Honors Academy should call 402-472-2310402-472-2310, or visit the Academy website at http://cba.unl.edu/honorsacademy.

CBA Honors Academy requirements differ from those listed in the bulletin. Students work closely with the Academy’s advisers on appropriate sequencing and enrollment in Academy-specific requirements.

Jeffrey S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management

The purpose of the Jeffrey S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management is to produce unique graduates who combine business knowledge and computing fundamentals for enterprise information and software systems. Graduates will be professionals who understand the multiple levels of new information systems and who become the technology sector’s innovators, product developers, entrepreneurs, chief information officers, and CEOs.

The program is designed to not only improve students’ ability to create information technology applications and solutions, but also the capacity to understand the implications of information technology for business and society. The program will produce graduates with high technical proficiency as well as a strong sense of the business problems and organizational needs that information systems are intended to serve.

Students interested in learning more about the Jeffrey S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management program are encouraged to call 402-472-6000402-472-6000 or visit the program website at raikes.unl.edu.

Jeffrey S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management requirements differ from those listed in the bulletin. Students work closely with the program’s advisers on appropriate sequencing and enrollment in Raikes-specific requirements.

Student Recognition

Dean’s List/Degrees with Distinction/Scholarships

Dean’s List

The College recognizes students for academic achievement during the fall and spring semesters by placement on the College Dean’s List. To qualify for the Dean’s List, students must complete 12 or more credit hours for a grade (excluding hours with P, NP, NR and I marks) during the semester and attain a grade point average of 3.6 or higher.

Degrees with Distinction

In recognition of outstanding academic excellence, the college recommends the bachelors degree With Distinction, With High Distinction, and With Highest Distinction. Students are recommended for this honor by the Scholarship, Honors, and Awards Committee of the College.

To be eligible for consideration students must:

complete 45 credit hours for a letter grade (excluding Pass/No Pass marks) at UNL prior to the semester in which they graduate, and
must have completed 60 such credit hours at UNL at the time they graduate.

To determine the level of distinction, the Committee uses the cumulative grade point average based on all credit hours taken at UNL prior to the beginning of the term in which the student receives his or her degree. No specific cumulative grade point average is required but the honor is limited to approximately ten percent of the graduating class. This usually means a 3.8 (or higher) GPA. Students will be notified of the distinction, high, or highest distinction designation approximately one month before graduation.

International Study/Education Abroad

Education Abroad

The College of Business Administration has several outstanding education abroad programs where students may enroll and complete course work for their degree requirements at a foreign institution or at an international site. Students should identify their intentions early in their program to ensure the appropriate sequencing and transfer of credit. More information can be found at: http://cba.unl.edu/studyabroad and http://educationabroad.unl.edu.

The Nebraska at Oxford program allows undergraduate students to study British political and economic policy at Oxford University during a 4-week summer program. Business students earn credit for ECON 466 (3 hrs) and ECON 467 (3 hrs); non-business students may also participate and earn credit for ECON 466 (3 hrs) and ENGL 386/THEA 386 (3 hrs). ECON 211 and ECON 212 must be complete prior to program participation for business students.

Senshu University in Japan gives students an opportunity to study and earn 17 hours in business and Japanese language in Tokyo, Japan. Credit for BSAD 491 (up to 6 hours) may count for BSAD and IBUS majors, and 3 hours for MNGT, MRKT, and FINA majors. BSAD 491 credit for IBUS majors (or BSAD majors with an IBUS minor) can only be applied once toward the BSAD or IBUS course requirement and cannot be double counted between the two separate requirements. BSAD 491 credit not already applied to a specific major may count toward business elective, free elective, and/or upper-level elective hours and IBCR credit. Study abroad transfer rules do apply. The advisers in CBA 114 can explain how Senshu credit applies to specific business majors/minors, including the language credit options for IBUS majors.

The Consortium of Universities for International Business (CIMBA) offers summer and semester undergraduate courses and summer graduate courses in the Veneto region in Italy. Due to the extensive credit options available, students should reference an academic adviser or the website above for applicable degree credit.

The France Business School (FBS), School of Business and Management (formally ESCEM) in Poitiers, France, offers undergraduate courses in a variety of business areas, such as management, marketing and European business studies. Depending on the fall/spring semester options, students should reference the UNL Education Abroad Office and a CBA academic adviser for applicable degree credit options. Credit will be determined based through a pre-departure evaluation process.

Economic and Cultural Discovery in China is a 3-week summer program visiting businesses and cultural sites. Through this program, undergraduate students earn a minimum of 3 hours of BSAD 491 and graduate students earn 3 hours of GRBA 896.

Other study abroad programs are available in many other countries with many credit hour and semester options. Students should refer to http://educationabroad.unl.edu for more information.

Senior Check/My Degree Audit

My Degree Audit

In the term after which a student has completed 85 hours, Graduation Services (109 Canfield Administration Building) will perform a “senior check.” Students will be sent an email notification with a link to MyDegreeAudit. This will inform students about requirements that need to be completed to receive the degree. This information will also be accessible by students through the MyRED Message Center.

Senior Check

In the term after which a student has completed 85 hours, Graduation Services (109 Canfield Administration Building) will perform a “senior check.” Students will be provided with a copy of the degree audit which informs students about requirements that need to be completed to receive the degree.

Graduation Requirements

Each student who expects to receive a diploma must have a minimum 2.5 cumulative grade point average to file an application for degree candidacy.

Students should access their Degree Audit via MyRed at least once each term to review degree requirements and progress toward graduation. It is the student’s responsibility to make sure their Degree Audit accurately reflects their current College and program of study.

Students are expected to develop a clear understanding of degree requirements and to plan their course of study with a College adviser. Students requiring clarification of outstanding degree requirements should visit with a College adviser promptly. Students who believe their Degree Audit has errors or omissions should visit with a College adviser promptly. It is important that you resolve these matters as soon as practicable to avoid a delay in graduation.

Each student must submit an Application for Graduation plus $25.00 check or cash fee for each degree to be received to the Office of the University Registrar by:

The last Friday in January for May graduation
The last Friday in June for August graduation
The last Friday in September for December graduation

An electronic Application for Graduation and payment is available via MyRed. Those students choosing to apply for graduation in person may visit the Office of the University Registrar, 107 Canfield Administration Building. Applications for Graduation submitted in person or by mail must be accompanied by payment. Failure to submit a timely Application for Graduation may preclude the awarding of a degree in the intended term.

Announcements regarding graduation deadline dates are posted on campus bulletin boards and published in the Daily Nebraskan and the College. DEADLINES ARE EARLY IN THE SEMESTER.

Students are responsible for informing the Office of the University Registrar of the manner in which they are completing their requirements (i.e., by independent study, clearance of incompletes, enrollment at another institution, special examinations, etc.); and of any revision of such plans. In addition, any change in address, email, or phone number should be specifically directed to this office (and updated through MyRED) to avoid a postponement of graduation until a later semester.

Student Standing/Classification

Second semester freshmen who have completed MATH 104 (or higher) with a grade of “C” or better and have a cumulative 2.5 GPA over at least 14 credit hours earned at UNL, may enroll in ACCT 201 (which normally requires sophomore standing). Freshmen are also permitted to enroll in ECON 211 or ECON 212 upon completion of 12 hours of UNL credit.

Sophomore Standing. For admission to sophomore standing, a student must have earned a minimum of 27 semester hours of credit. It is expected that students will have removed any entrance deficiencies by this point in the program and should maintain a 2.5 cumulative GPA to remain on sequence for graduation.

Junior Standing. A student has junior standing after meeting the requirements for sophomore standing and completing 53 semester hours of credit. It is expected that students will maintain a 2.5 cumulative GPA to remain on sequence for graduation.

Senior Standing. A student has senior standing after meeting the requirements for junior standing and completing 89 semester hours of credit. It is expected that students will maintain a 2.5 cumulative GPA to remain on sequence for graduation.

Substitutions and Waivers

Curriculum and/or Policy Appeals

The faculty of the College has established degree requirements and policies and procedures. Any exceptions to the rules (substitutions and/or waivers) are made as a written appeal to the faculty through the Undergraduate Committee of the College. This request can be made only in unusual circumstances and cannot serve as an excuse for not following college guidelines. Students should meet with an adviser in CBA 114 to discuss options, specific instructions, and procedures for consideration of an appeal.

Grade Appeal

Students who believe they have received an unfair grade may take the following sequential actions to appeal a grade:

The student must discuss the situation with the instructor involved.
If no acceptable solution is reached, the student may file a written grade appeal with the Grade Appeal Committee of the specific department or school in the College within the first 20 days of the academic semester following receipt of the course grade. In making his or her appeal, the student must allege that the guarantees contained in Section II, Part B, of The Student in the Academic Community, have been violated. The Committee may be contacted through the department chair or school director.
If either the instructor or the student disagrees with the decision of the Grade Appeal Committee, a written appeal may be filed with the Collegiate Grade Appeals Committee, which may be contacted through the Dean’s Office for Undergraduate Programs.

Grade Option Appeal/Late Withdrawal Appeal:

Appeals to change the grade option in a course after the deadline, as well as any late withdrawal requests must be made in writing to the College Grading and Examinations Committee. Restrictions, options, and forms for either of these procedures may be obtained from the Dean’s Office for Undergraduate Programs, CBA 114. The College generally expects any appeal request to be made within a reasonable time frame.

Call

Send SMS

Add to Skype

You'll need Skype CreditFree via Skype

ACE REQUIREMENTS

All students must fulfill the Achievement Centered Education (ACE) requirements. Information about the ACE program may be viewed at ace.unl.edu. Students may also use the Bulletin’s course search facility to search for ACE groups. Example: Enter ACE one in the search to generate a list of all possible ACE 1 courses.

ACE Achievement-Centered Education—Ten Courses (normally 30 hours)

This is the university’s innovative, outcomes-focused general education component designed to enhance the undergraduate experience by providing broad exposure to multiple disciplines, complementing the major and helping students develop important reasoning, inquiry, and civic capacities.

Important rules to remember when selecting course work to meet this requirement:

There are 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO) and at least one course, equivalent to 3 credit hours, must be taken for each of the 10 SLO’s.
Up to three ACE Student Learning Outcomes (SLO), 4-10, may be satisfied by work in one subject area;
ACE SLO’s must be satisfied by work in at least three subject areas;
No ACE course may satisfy more than one ACE SLO in a student’s program;
If an ACE course addresses two ACE SLO’s, the student decides which one of the two outcomes the course will satisfy in that student’s program. (My Degree Audit will make an automatic decision based on first course taken; first SLO needed.)
As part of the college requirements of non-business and business courses, many courses will also work for ACE. Students should carefully review required course work with ACE options to make the best use of courses to fulfill both degree requirements as well as UNL ACE requirements.

BULLETIN TO USE

Students (including transfer students) must follow the Undergraduate Bulletin in effect when they enroll in the College of Business Administration. Students who leave the college and return or those applying for ‘readmission’ to the College are subject to requirements in place at the time of their re-enrollment in the College.

COLLEGE DEGREE REQUIREMENTS

Professional Enhancement Program (PrEP) (4 hours)

Designed to develop professional,confident and polished students for lifelongcareer success, the PrEP program consists of four required one hour courses. These courses are labeled BSAD 111, BSAD 222, BSAD 333, BSAD 444 and are offered across the four year curriculum. Raikes students complete this requirement as a part of their other courses.

College General Education Requirements

The curriculum requirements for the College consist of course work in three areas.

All course work (except electives and where otherwise noted) must be taken for a grade.

The three areas include the following:

Non-Business Requirements (NBR)

– which consist primarily of College and University ACE (Achievement-Centered Education) course work

Business Core

– Foundation (BCF), which also includes ACE 6 & 8

– Intermediate (BCI)

– Advanced-Major (BCA-M)

– Advanced-Capstone (BCA-C), (ACE 10)

Electives

Non-Business Requirements (NBR)

(Most of the ACE requirements)

Eight Courses (normally 24-26 hours)
All students in the College of Business Administration will take the following non-business courses (unless otherwise noted).
While NBR 1, 2, 7 and 8 identify specific ACE options to choose from or identify an ACE course specifically required for the College, NBR 3, 4, 5, and 6 allow for students to select courses according to their personal interests (and meet ACE 4, 5, 7, and 9).
Most students will take course work to fulfill these requirements during the freshman/sophomore year. However, if hours are still needed during the junior/senior year, there may also be options to ‘double count’ course work for NBR 3 (ACE 4) and/or NBR 6 (ACE 9) toward the major (BCA-M) or a minor. This is likely to be of most benefit to ‘transfer-in students’ due to the nature of the program and when ACE requirements are traditionally taken.
All course work for NBR must be taken for a grade.

NBR 1: Written Communication (ACE 1)

Choose ONE of the following:

ENGL 101 Writing: Rhetoric & Reading

ENGL 150 Writing: Rhetoric as Inquiry

ENGL 151 Writing: Rhetoric as Argument

Students should refer to the course descriptions to select the one course best suited to individual interests. While several communication courses can be selected to fulfill the university ACE 1 outcome, one of the above is a specific requirement for the College of Business Administration and will fulfill both requirements with one course.

NBR 2: Mathematical, Computational, Statistical or Formal Reasoning Skills (ACE 3)

Choose ONE of the following:

MATH 104 Applied Calculus (3 cr)

MATH 106 Calculus I (5 cr)

Any advanced calculus course above the 106 level

Notes regarding the selection of course work for NBR 2 (ACE 3):

Credit cannot be given for both MATH 104 and MATH 106. Students must determine the appropriate course early in their program.
A first semester student’s score on the Math Placement Exam will determine eligibility for MATH 104 or 106. The student should select between these classes based on the following sets of circumstances.
Actuarial Science majors MUST take MATH 106 (or a higher-level calculus).
Actuarial science majors will also take MATH 107 (4 cr) and MATH 208 (4 cr) and CSCE 101 & CSCE 101L (4 cr).
RAIKES students MUST take MATH 106 (or a higher-level calculus)
MATH 106 (or higher calculus) is strongly encouraged for those students considering graduate school.
While several courses can be selected to fulfill the university ACE 3 outcome, one of the above is a specific requirement for the College of Business Administration and will fulfill both requirements with one course.

Math Placement Exam (MPE)

Students admitted to the College of Business Administration are required to take a Math Placement Examination prior to enrolling in the college math requirement of MATH 104 or MATH 106 (or higher math).

The results of this examination determine which math course students will enroll in their first semester on campus.
Students lacking sufficient high school preparation in math may need to enroll in equivalent high school preparatory courses, as will be determined by the MPE.
Preparatory courses should be taken as soon as possible to avoid future sequencing problems.
Additional information about the exam can be found at www.math.unl.edu.

Whether required to enroll in preparation course work first, as indicated on the MPE (MATH 100A, MATH 101 and/or MATH 103), or in one of the required courses, it is critical to begin MATH the first semester on campus.

NBR 3: The Study of Scientific Methods and Knowledge of the Natural and Physical World (ACE 4)

Choose one course from ACE 4 Certified Courses. (Course credit will vary between 3-4 credit hours.)

ABUS majors – NBR 3 (ACE 4) – AGRI 115, AGRO 131, ENTO 115, MSYM 109, NRES 108, PLPT 110 may be taken to fulfill the science requirement (NBR 3–ACE 4) as well as a requirement for the major (BCA-M).

NBR 4: Study of Humanities (ACE 5)

Choose one course from ACE 5 Certified Courses.

IBUS majors – NBR 4 (ACE 5) – FREN 301, FREN 302; RUSS 301, RUSS 302, RUSS 482, RUSS 483 can be taken to fulfill NBR 4–ACE 5 as well as a requirement for a language minor.

NBR 5: Study of the Arts to Understand Their Context (ACE 7)

Choose one course from ACE 7 Certified Courses.

NBR 6: Global Awareness or Knowledge of Human Diversity Through Analysis of an Issue (ACE 9)

Choose one course from ACE 9 Certified Courses.

Students enrolling for their first semester with junior standing (or more), will see that the list of approved courses includes a few business courses. While this section is labeled “non-business requirements,” students may elect to enroll in one of the business courses to fulfill the ACE 9 requirement as long as prerequisites are completed (which are generally reserved for juniors or seniors). Work closely with your adviser to bring this to their attention and to question how this course may potentially satisfy other degree program requirements, including the major. The options include:

ACTS majors – must complete an International Business Course as part of the degree requirements. Actuarial science majors may choose to take ECON 321 International Economics to fulfill the IBCR as well as the global awareness requirement (NBR 6–ACE 9).
ABUS majors – AECN 346, AECN 367, AECN 420, AECN 425, AGRI 282, ENSC 110, HORT 200, may be taken to fulfill the global awareness requirement (NBR 6–ACE 9) as well as a requirement for the major.
BSAD majors – ECON 321, MNGT 365, MNGT 414 may be taken to fulfill the global awareness requirement (NBR 6–ACE 9) as well as a requirement for the major. (ECON 321 and MNGT 414 are also IBCR course options.)
ECON majors – ECON 321 may be taken to fulfill the global awareness requirement (NBR 6–ACE 9) as well as a requirement for the major. (ECON 321 is also an IBCR option.)
IBUS majors – ECON 321 or MNGT 414 may be taken to fulfill the global awareness requirement (NBR 6–ACE 9) as well as a requirement for the major. (Both are also IBCR options.)
MNGT majors – MNGT 365, MNGT 414 may be taken to fulfill the global awareness requirement (NBR 6–ACE 9) and may be able to fulfill a requirement for the major depending on the option selected. (MNGT 414 is also an IBCR option.)
An alternative to the above options is allowance of the course to count for NBR 6–ACE 9 and the associated minor—but only one or the other (major OR minor).

In any of the above instances where a double counting is an option, only 3 hours of credit are awarded; student will still need to meet the 120 hours for graduation.

NBR 7: Business Communication (ACE 1)

JGEN 220 Business Communication Strategies

This is a business writing course with sophomore standing with 3 hours of composition as a prerequisite. While it is also an ACE 1 course, as is ENGL, BOTH ENGL and JGEN are specific requirements for the College of Business Administration.
RAIKES students will complete RAIK 287H and RAIK 288H instead of JGEN 220.

NBR 8: Oral Communication Skills (ACE 2)

MRKT 257 Sales Communication

Or

COMM 286 Business & Professional Communication

Due to the importance of this course to the business curriculum, the college recommends taking this course on campus.
Sophomore standing is a prerequisite to enroll in this oral business speaking class; and while several other courses may be selected to fulfill the university ACE 2 requirement, COMM 286 is a specific requirement for the College of Business Administration.
RAIKES students will complete RAIK 187H and RAIK 188H instead of COMM 286.

NOTE: In the selection of course work for any of the above NBR’s, prerequisites, when stated anywhere in this bulletin, means course work MUST BE COMPLETED to enroll in the class. Concurrent enrollment in any identified prerequisite(s) is NOT permitted unless so indicated in the course description.

Business Core – Four Sections (approximately 56-69 hours)

Business Core Foundation (BCF) – 18 hours (1 hour not applicable toward 120 hours)
Business Core Intermediate (BCI) – 20 hours
Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M) (hours vary from 18-33 hrs)
Business Core Advanced–Capstone (BCA-C) (3 hours + 0 hour assessment)

The foundation and intermediate courses are designed to expose students to the various business disciplines. The advanced courses are those courses identified for each of the nine majors, and the capstone course is taken the final semester of the program. All course work for the Business Core (except where noted differently), must be taken for a grade.

Business Core Foundation (BCF) – Eight Courses (18 hours)

All students in the College of Business Administration will take the following courses (unless otherwise noted).

All course work (except 111 & 150) must be taken for a grade.
RAIKES students will complete a different series of course work for the Business Core Foundation:
Foundation: RAIK 181H, RAIK 182H, RAIK 282H, ACCT 202 & ECON 215
Leadership Series: RAIK 185H, RAIK 186H, RAIK 285H, RAIK 286H
Computer Science Foundation: RAIK 183H, RAIK 184H, RAIK 283H, RAIK 383H

BCF 1–BSAD 111 Professional Enhancement I (1 hr)

1-credit-hour course (offered Pass/No Pass only).
Required of all new freshmen.
An active exploration, examination, and pursuit of fundamental concepts and principles of leadership development and how they relate to all fields within business administration. Also covered is a broad orientation to all domains of business administration, including activities, assignments, and exercises.
Take this course as a freshman (preferably first semester).
BSAD 111 is waived for Chancellor’s Leadership, Raikes, and transfer students who have completed 27 hours.

BCF 2–BSAD 150 Business Computer Applications (1 hr)

1-credit-hour course (offered Pass/No Pass only).
Hour not applicable toward 120 hours for degree.
Take second semester of freshman year OR first semester of sophomore year.
Required basic-skills computer course, use Access, Microsoft Word, PowerPoint, and Excel; students will complete group projects and group tests.
Advanced computer applications students may wish to “test out” via the Credit by Exam option instead of taking the class. Refer to the BSAD 150 website for additional information.
RAIKES students do not need to complete this requirement.

BCF 3–ACCT 201 and ACCT 202 Introductory Accounting I & II (3 hrs ea)

ACCT 201 Introductory Accounting I

Sequential; take ACCT 201 first
Prerequisite: Sophomore standing, 2.5 cumulative GPA; or freshman standing with completion of MATH 104 with a grade of C or better, and a 2.5 cumulative GPA earned in 14 hours of UNL credit

ACCT 202 Introductory Accounting II

Sequential; take ACCT 202 following completion of ACCT 201
Prerequisite: Sophomore standing; grade of C or better in ACCT 201; 2.5 cumulative GPA
Grade of C or better in ACCT 202 is required to enroll in upper-level ACCT classes

BCF 4–ECON 211 and ECON 212 Principles of Macro & Microeconomics (ACE 8/6) (3 hrs ea)

ECON 211 Principles of Macroeconomics

Not sequential
Prerequisite: Completion of 12 hours of UNL course work
RAIKES students will satisfy their ACE 8/6 requirement with RAIK 182H/BSAD 182H & RAIK 282H/BSAD 282H

ECON 212 Principles of Microeconomics

Same as above

BCF 5–ECON 215 Statistics (ACE 3) (3 hrs)

Prerequisites: Sophomore standing; MATH 104/MATH 104H or MATH 106/MATH 108H; BSAD 150; 2.5 GPA
Must take ECON 215 (not STAT 218 nor EDPS 459 nor CRIM 300 nor SOCI 206)
Actuarial science majors MUST take STAT 380 instead of STAT 215; will also take STAT 462 and STAT 463

BCF 6–BSAD 222 Professional Enhancement II (1 hr)

1-credit-hour course (offered Pass/No Pass only)
Prerequisites: Majors in College of Business Administration; Sophomore standing; 2.5 GPA.
Take this course as a sophomore.

Business Core Intermediate (BCI) – Eight Courses (20 hours)

Prerequisites for the BCI courses include MATH (NBR2), ACCT 201, ACCT 202, ECON 211, ECON 212, ECON 215 and a 2.5 GPA
Required of all business students regardless of major (except where noted under individual courses)
RAIKES students will take RAIK 281H and RAIK 381H in place of FINA 361, MNGT 331/SCMS 331, and SCMS 350. They will also take RAIK 341H in place of MRKT 341.
In addition to differences noted above, RAIKES students will also complete:
Design Studio courses: RAIK 301H, RAIK 302H, RAIK 401H, and RAIK 402H
Computer science electives: 6 hrs from the following: CSCE 378, CSCE 475, CSCE 476, RAIK 384H (which may be taken Pass/No Pass)
Enrollment in BCI normally occurs during the sophomore and junior year
All course work must be taken for a grade
Sequence with the following recommendations/restrictions:
Plan complete sequence of intentions to take BCI (and necessary prerequisites) to remain on schedule for graduation
The management courses are all different; while they can be taken in the same semester, many students choose one or two for each semester.
Enroll in courses most applicable to major as soon as possible, particularly MRKT or FINA, to stay on sequence for major.
There are exceptions to these requirements for specific majors (ACCT, MRKT, ACTS). Please note those exceptions under the courses.
If transferring, a maximum of 3 hours may apply with further restrictions on applicability to not exceed the 75% rule.
See the links for each course to know the specific prerequisites and course descriptions.

BCI 1–BLAW 371 Legal Environment or BLAW 372 Business Law (3 hrs)

BLAW 371 Legal Enironment

OR

BLAW 372 Business Law (Accounting majors must take BLAW 372.)

BCI 2 – SCMS 350/MNGT 350 Introduction to Management Information Systems or MRKT 350 Introduction to Marketing Information Systems

MRKT and ABUS majors may choose to take MRKT 350, which carries an additional prerequisite of MRKT 341.
RAIKES students will take RAIK 281H in place of MNGT 350/SCMS 350.

BCI 3 – FINA 361 Finance (3 hrs)

Actuarial science majors will take FINA 461 instead of FINA 361.
RAIKES students will take RAIK 381H in place of FINA 361.

BCI 4 – MRKT 341 Marketing (3 hrs)

RAIKES students will take RAIK 341H in place of MRKT 341.

BCI 5 – MNGT 331/SCMS 331 Operations & Supply Chain Management (3 hrs)

RAIKES students will take RAIK 281H in place of MNGT 331/SCMS 331.

BCI 6 – MNGT 360 Managing Behavior in Organizations (ACE 6) (3 hrs)

Professional Enhancement Program – Upper level

PrEP–BSAD 333 Professional Enhancement III (1 hr)

1-credit-hour course (offered Pass/No Pass only).
Prerequisites: Majors in College of Business Administration; 2.5 GPA; BSAD 222.
Take this course as a junior (preferably first semester).

PrEP–BSAD 444 Professional Enhancement IV (1 hr)

1-credit-hour course (offered Pass/No Pass only).
Prerequisites: Majors in College of Business Administration; 2.5 GPA; BSAD 333 or by permission.
Take this course as a senior (preferably first semester) or junior (preferably second semester).

Business Core Advanced-Major (BCA-M) – (18-36 hours)

Students may pursue and reference specific major requirements by clicking on the major: accounting, actuarial science, agribusiness, business administration, economics, finance, international business, management, marketing, or suppy chain management.

Course work for the major requires completion of specific, required courses of the department, along with other guidelines.
Refer to the major page for a listing of requirements.
Careful and advanced planning is necessary as some courses for the major may not necessarily be available every semester (particularly summer).
ALL course work for the major must be taken for a grade (no Pass/No Pass).
Students may be able to take their International Business Course Requirement (IBCR) as part of their major.
Although a 2.5 GPA may not be required to take these courses, a 2.5 is required to apply for graduation; thus, students are expected to maintain this level throughout their collegiate career.
Sequencing of classes is critical, particularly for agribusiness, actuarial science, and international business; plan the major courses well in advance of enrollment.
By this point in time, the curriculum was designed for ACE (except ACE 10) to have been completed through other course work. If missing an ACE 4 or 9, there may be options through the major to fulfill both requirements.
A maximum of 3 hours of course work may transfer if the 75% rule has not been exceeded. Further restrictions may apply.

Business Core Advanced-Capstone (BCA-C) – Two Courses (3 hours)

BCA-C 1 – MNGT 475 Business Policies & Strategies (ACE 10) (3 hrs)

Reserved for graduating seniors, this course requires the Business Core Foundation (BCF) and Intermediate (BCI) course work to be completed for enrollment.
A capstone course integrating business concepts covered throughout the program.
Course MUST be taken at UNL and taken for a grade (no Pass/No Pass).

BCA-C 2 – BSAD 98 Senior Assessment (0 hrs)

A 0 credit-hour seminar required of ALL CBA graduating seniors.
Taught via Blackboard – all components must be completed to a satisfactory level to graduate.
Major Field Test required as part of assessment, which must be passed to graduate.

Electives – Hours vary to meet 120 hour minimum to graduate

Electives round out the rest of the 120 hour curriculum where students have the option to choose courses toward a second major, a dual degree, a minor (or two); or, students can simply select courses of personal interest.

Some hours may need to be additional business course work (to meet the requirement that 60 hours of course work be in business). This requirement will vary by major.
There may be a need to enroll in an international business course requirement (IBCR) if not taken as part of the major or for the business elective(s) requirement.
A minimum of 12 hours of 300/400 upper-level course work beyond the business core is required for most majors to ensure depth is achieved through enrollment in elective hours. See 300/400-level Elective Requirement below for additional information.
In addition to the Foundation, leadership, and computer science foundation courses listed earlier, RAIKES students will also complete the following courses as part of the degree requirements:
Raikes Design Studio Courses (must be taken for a grade):
RAIK 301H, RAIK 302H, RAIK 401H, RAIK 402H (ACE 10)
Raikes Computer Science Electives – Choose 6 hours from: CSCE 378, CSCE 475, CSCE 476 or RAIK 384H (can be taken Pass/No Pass)
If not completed through the other area requirements, any remaining ACE requirements will need to be completed as required electives.
In a 21-hour major, students will average 32 hours of elective credit; 2nd major options and/or minors may be appropriate to consider for elective hours.

Other Requirements

International Business Course Requirement (IBCR)

The international business course requirement (IBCR) is to broaden the student’s international perspective.
Each student, excluding accounting majors, must include one course which emphasizes an international perspective.
Actuarial Science majors are encouraged to take FINA 450 if they have not met this requirement with completion of NBR 6 – ACE 9 with ECON 321 or MNGT 414.
The IBCR must be taken for a grade.

The course must be chosen from the following approved list of International Business Course Requirement (IBCR) courses. Many of these courses have prerequisites. Some are restricted for education abroad and others may only be offered once a year. Thus, you are advised to plan ahead in scheduling this requirement into your program.

IBCR Courses

BSAD 491 International Studies in Business and Economics (1-15 hrs)

Available only to students studying abroad for which there is no UNL equivalent course.
Available also for the Senshu, Japan, CIMBA Italy, and for the China Education Abroad Programs.
Senshu program students may apply 3 hours towards electives in the FINA, MNGT, or MRKT major; 6 hours applicable for BSAD or IBUS major/minor.
BSAD 491 credit from any other study abroad program should be based on course topics directly associated with a specific major in MNGT, MRKT or FINA, and may need department consent. Students should visit with an academic adviser for assistance.

ECON 321 Introduction to International Economics (If not completed at this point, MNGT 414 may double count for ACE 9.)

ECON 421 International Trade (credit cannot be earned in both ECON 421 and AECN 420)

ECON 422 International Finance

ECON 423 Economics of the Less Developed Countries

ECON 466 & ECON 467 Pro-Seminar in International Relations I & II (Credit option for students participating in the Nebraska at Oxford Program.)

FINA 450 International Financial Management

MNGT 414 Leadership in a Global Context (If not completed at this point, MNGT 414 may double count for ACE 9.)

MNGT 459/SCMS 459 Global Information Systems

MRKT 453 International Marketing (prerequisite requires completion of 6 hours of MRKT course work)

SCMS 439 Global Sourcing & Distribution

Although the following courses may also be used to fulfill requirements in the international business major/minor/IBCR, students should be aware that they are not necessarily offered on a consistent basis.

ECON 322 Introduction to Development Economics (credit cannot be earned in both ECON 322 and AECN 367)

ECON 323 The Economic Development of Latin America

ECON 388 Comparative Economics Systems

ECON 440 Regional Development

ECON 487 Economies in Transition

If planned carefully, the IBCR course can count in two places. It is not an extra 3 hours of credit, but rather, is 3 hours embedded within other requirements. If selected carefully, it can also count for 3 hours of credit in the major (i.e. MRKT 453 counts for MRKT elective in MRKT major and would count for the IBCR; FINA 450 counts for FINA elective in FINA major and would fulfill the IBCR as well; etc.). On the other hand, if course work for the major is already determined by personal choices, the IBCR can count in electives, and more specifically, for one of the ‘business’ electives needed for most majors.

300/400 Upper-level Requirement

As part of the degree requirements, all students must complete 12 hours of 300/400 level course work.

This can be business or non-business course work.

Business course work from the Business Core Intermediate (BCI), Business Core Advanced-Major (FIRST Major) or Business Core Advanced-Capstone may NOT be used to fulfill this requirement with exceptions noted below:
If more than 21 hours of course work for the major are taken at the 300/400-level and of those hours, course work is not being double counted toward the NBR and major, the additional 300/400-level hours can be used to fulfill the 300/400-level requirement. You will need to consult your Degree Audit to determine your requirements.
BSAD majors will complete a 24 hour major and only need to complete 9 upper level hours.
FINA majors, will take between 24 and 30 hours for their major; consult the major section in this document or your Degree Audit to determine how many hours will double count for this requirement. This will depend on which option you select for the major.
Actuarial science, agribusiness majors, international business majors and RAIKES students do not need to meet this requirement due to the additional hours at the 300/400 level required for the major/program.
Business Core Advanced-Major course work used for a SECOND major (if picked), or course work selected for a minor MAY count.
Non-business course work (NBR) taken at the 300/400 level may be double counted to fulfill this requirement if it is not being used to double count for the 1st major.
No course may be taken on a Pass/No Pass basis unless it is 398/399 credit. Only 3 hours of 398/399 is allowed for this requirement.

Business Course/Business Elective Hours

Sixty (60) hours of business courses are required for the BSBA degree.

The required hours WILL VARY BY MAJOR, dependent on how requirements have been accepted and/or completed throughout the previous components of the program. While GENERAL MINIMUM guidelines by major are noted below, My Degree Audit will specify minimum business credit hour expectations for each student. You will generally see this addressed under the ELECTIVE section (BUSINESS ELECTIVES) on My Degree Audit.

ACCT, ECON, MRKT majors – 3 hours
BSAD – no additional business course work as your major consists of 24 hours of business course work
ACTS – no additional business course work as your major consists of 28 hours of business course work.
FINA – no additional business course work as your major consists of 24-28 hours of business course work. UNLESS you select AECN 495A under the Banking and Financial Institutions options, and then you will need 3 hours of business electives.
ABUS and RAIK – no additional business course work required due to intent of major as being ‘business-related’ course work.
Additional hours may be required if there is a variation in hours for NBR, BCF, BCI or BCA, or if there is a violation of the 75% rule, the 15 hour rule, etc.

Course work must be taken for a grade except for 398/399 options where grades are generally not permitted

Foreign Languages/Language Requirement

Other than meeting the minimum requirement for admission to the University, the College does not require any additional work in foreign languages except for the international business major. Students, however, are always encouraged to take language courses.

Minimum Hours Required for Graduation

A minimum of 120 semester hours of credit is required for graduation; more may be necessary if specific degree requirements have not yet been completed. Most students will graduate with 121 hours as BSAD 150 is not applicable toward degree requirements.

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

While students may earn grades of C- or D, there are restrictions and recommendations for such grades and further enrollment options:

Grade of C or higher in ACCT 201 required to enroll in ACCT 202.
Grade of C or higher in ACCT 202 required to enroll in any 300/400-level ACCT course.
Grade of C or higher required in other departmental higher-level sequencing courses (i.e. MATH 101 to take MATH 104, etc.). See course descriptions to determine enrollment restrictions.
Minimum 2.5 cumulative GPA required to enroll in many business courses.
ACCT 201, ACCT 202, ECON 215, FINA 361, BLAW 371, BLAW 372, MNGT 331, MNGT 350/SCMS 350, MNGT 360, MNGT 475, MRKT 341, MRKT 350
Grades of C- or lower can be removed by retaking the course at UNL or within the University system (UNK, UNO).
Grades of C or better are required to transfer courses from other institutions.
Academic bankruptcy options may be considered for students who have one or two semesters of poor performance.

Pass/No Pass Limits

The Pass/No Pass option is designed for students who want to study areas or topics in which they may have minimum preparation. If used for this purpose, the option can enrich the student’s academic experience without lowering the student’s grade point average. Several restrictions apply when considering the Pass/No Pass option:

BSAD 111 and BSAD 150 are offered only as Pass/No Pass. Both are required and BSAD 150 does not count toward the 120 hours required for the degree
Students may apply no more than 6 hours of elective credit using the Pass/No Pass option (excludes BSAD 111, BSAD 150, BSAD 222, BSAD 333, BSAD 444).
No student in any College enrolled at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln may take business courses in the College of Business Administration using the Pass/No Pass option.
College of Business Administration students may NOT take course work to satisfy ACE requirements, the International Business Course Requirement (IBCR), nor any required business course work, including the major and minor, using the Pass/No Pass option.
Students majoring in actuarial science through the College of Business Administration may NOT take any math, actuarial science, or required courses using the Pass/No Pass option.
Students taking courses to fulfill the requirements of a minor in an area of study outside the College of Business Administration are subject to CBA rules restricting use of the Pass/No Pass option if courses in their minor are used to meet ACE or any college-specific requirements.
Students seeking any minor outside the College should verify rules applying to minimum grade expectations and Pass/No Pass options with the adviser for their minor as additional restrictions may apply and they often vary.
Students from UNO/UNK/UNMC and from other institutions are subject to the same restrictions listed here of UNL students.

Exceptions to the above rules are limited to the following and no other exceptions will be made.

An independent study course (398, 399) may be taken in the College of Business Administration using the Pass/No Pass option with the permission of the instructor and the department chair but College of Business Administration students who qualify for this exception may use the independent study course (398, 399) only as elective credit.
Advanced Placement grades of P and Credit By Exam grades of P will be accepted to fulfill degree requirements (with the exception of BSAD 150). These hours will not count against the 6-hour-maximum hours permitted.
Students who travel abroad and return with “credit” rather than grades from the institution where they studied may use P grades to fulfill degree requirements. These hours will not count against the 9-hour-maximum number of hours permitted.

GPA Requirements

A 2.5 cumulative grade point average is required to apply for graduation, as well as a requirement for enrollment in ACCT 201 and ACCT 202, ECON 215, BLAW 371 and BLAW 372, FINA 361, MNGT 331, MNGT 360, MNGT 475, MNGT 350/SCMS 350 or MRKT 350, and MRKT 341. In some instances, a specific grade is required in certain courses to continue with upper-level course work.

Transfer Credit Rules

See Maximum/Minimum hour restrictions under Course Exclusions and Restrictions

Course Level Requirements (Hour Requirement 300+)

In addition to the Business Core Intermediate and Business Core Advanced and Business Course Advanced Capstone requirements, business students must complete an additional 12 hours of 300/400-level course work in their program (not required for ACTS majors and RAIKES students). Students generally fulfill this requirement through their electives, but there may be a few upper-class students who can fulfill the requirement with the ACE course requirements. Twelve hours is based on a 21 hour major. The number is adjusted when there are larger majors.

Residency

At least 30 of the last 36 hours of credit must be registered for and completed in residence at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln.
Students electing to study abroad in their final semester are exempted for the hours earned abroad, but no additional hours may be transferred in the last 36 hours. This exemption requires filing a written appeal in the Undergraduate Programs office.

DEGREES & MAJORS

Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

Majors

Accounting

Actuarial Science (also offered through the College of Arts & Sciences)

Agribusiness (also offered through the College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources)

Business Administration

Economics (also offered through the College of Arts & Sciences)

Finance

International Business

Management

Marketing

Supply Chain Management

Dual Degrees

Given the number of elective hours available to most CBA students, consideration should be given to the opportunity to pursue a dual degree, which allows simultaneous enrollment in CBA and another college on campus. Students will need to consult with both colleges to ensure all requirements are satisfied in a timely, efficient manner and that double counting of course (where appropriate) is identified in advance of enrollment.

MINORS & AREAS OF SPECIALIZATIONS OFFERED

Minors Outside the College

The faculty of the College encourages students to minor in a discipline outside the College to develop logical and critical thinking, curiosity, understanding of the external environment and sensitivity to ethical issues. By developing these abilities, students can enrich their lives and provide a broader basis for informed and responsible decision making.

Minors are not required; only recommended.
Course work for the minor may be counted for the minor and ACE if so designated as ACE.
“PLAN A” requires completion of one minor; “Plan B” requires two minors be completed.
The actuarial science minor is NOT an option for a FINA major.
Double counting of credit towards minors is determined by the department and college offering the minor.
RAIKES students should designate a computer science minor as most course work is taken as part of the program requirements.

These are the only minor options available outside the College of Business Administration.

Actuarial Science

African Studies

African-American Studies

Agricultural Economics

Anthropology

Applied Science (formerly Diversified Agricultural Studies)

Art or Art History

Asian Studies

Astronomy (see Physics)

Biological Chemistry

Biological Sciences

Chemistry

Child, Youth and Family Studies

Classics

Communication Studies

Community and Regional Planning

Computer Science

Conflict and Conflict Resolution

Criminal Justice

Czech (see Modern Languages)

Dance

Education

English

Environmental Studies

Ethnic Studies

Film Studies

French (see Modern Languages)

Geography

Geology

German (see Modern Languages)

Gerontology

Global Studies

Great Plains Studies

Greek (see Classics & Religious Studies)

History

Human Rights and Human Diversity

Individualized Program of Studies

Japanese

Jewish Studies

Latin (see Classics & Religious Studies)

Latina/Latino Studies (see U.S. Latina/Latino Studies)

Mathematics

Medieval and Renaissance Studies

Meteorology-Climatology (see Geosciences)

Military Science

Music

Native American Studies

Philosophy

Physics

Political Science

Psychology

Public Policy Analysis and Evaluation

Religious Studies (see Classics & Religious Studies)

Russian (see Modern Languages)

Sociology

Spanish (see Modern Languages)

Statistics

Textiles, Merchandising and Fashion Design

Theatre Arts

U.S. Latina/Latino Studies

University Studies

Women’s and Gender Studies

Minors Within the College

The College of Business Administration offers the following business minors to business students only.

Business Minors are not required.
Course work for the minor may be counted for the minor and ACE if so designated as ACE.
The actuarial science minor is NOT an option for a FINA major.
Business course work used for any of these minors cannot be double counted toward the major or other minor requirements, BCF, BCI, BCA-M or BCA-C. (See Finance Department for exceptions.)
Business students choosing to minor in economics must follow the CBA economics minor requirement.

Business Minors

Accounting

Actuarial Science

Economics

Finance

International Business

Management

Marketing

Supply Chain Management Systems

Other Emphases/Tracks

Finance Majors

There are several options available to finance majors:

general finance
banking & financial institutions
risk management & insurance
CFA® – investments option

Management Majors

Management majors will select an option from the list below. See the Management major section for details.

human resources management
entrepreneurship and innovation
leadership in organizations
general management

Marketing Majors

Marketing majors can pursue tracks (as described under the marketing major) in:

merchandising (minor)
merchandising/design (minor)
advertising

Unlike the major and minor, recognition of completion of these emphases/tracks do not appear on the student’s transcript.

General Business Minor—Plan A Only

The minor consists of the following 18 hours:

ACCT 200 Accounting for Business Decisions (3 hrs)

ECON 200 Economic Essentials & Issues (3 hrs)

BLAW 300 Business Government & Society (3 hrs)

FINA 300 Financial Decision Making (3 hrs)

MNGT 300 Management Essentials for Contemporary Organizations (3 hrs)

MRKT 300 Contemporary Marketing (3 hrs)

Please note the following information.

This minor is available to all other colleges at UNL.
Only nonbusiness students can complete this minor.
Courses in the minor can’t be used towards a degree in business
Prerequisites are enforced.
No more than one course may be transferred into the minor.
Students with previous credit in business should see their college adviser for further information.

Military Leadership Minor—Plan A Only

This is an 18 hour minor.

The Military Leadership Minor is designed for CBA students who are involved in one of the three ROTC programs. The requirements for each are listed below.

Military Leadership Minor (Army ROTC)

1. MLSC 401 Leadership & Management (3 cr) Lec 3.

2. MLSC 402L Leadership Lab VII (0 cr) Lab.

3. MLSC 402 Officership (3 cr) Lec 3.

4. MLSC 402L Leadership Lab VIII (0 cr) Lab.

5a. HIST 303 United States Military History, 1607-1917 (3 cr) Lec 3.

OR

5b. HIST 304 United States Military History Since 1917 (3 cr) Lec 3.

6. MNGT 311 Leadership, Communications & Teams (3 cr) Lec 3.

Students must take two of the four courses below:

7. MNGT 411 Leading People & Projects (3 cr) Lec 3.

8. MNGT 412 Negotiating & Conflict Management (3 cr) Lec 3.

9. MNGT 413 Building Ethical & Sustainable Organizations (3 cr) Lec 3.

10. MNGT 414 Leadership in a Global Context (3 cr) Lec 3.

NOTE: If MNGT 311 is a required course for your major, you may take three of the four above courses to complete the minor as long as none of the courses above are used in their major. To complete their minor, if any of the above courses are used in their major, they may select from the courses below as substitutes:

MNGT 361, MNGT 461, SCMS 335, SCMS 437, SCMS 459, SCMS 444, ECON 416, ECON 417, ECON 433, MRKT 453, or MRKT 458.

A total of 18 credit hours must be completed for the minor. No double counting is allowed between majors and minors.

Military Leadership Minor (Navy ROTC)

1. NAVS 100 Naval Orientation Lab (0 cr)

2. NAVS 401 Naval Leadership & Management (3 cr) Lec 3.

3. NAVS 412 Leadership and Ethics (3 cr) Lec 3.

4a. HIST 303 United States Military History, 1607-1917 (3 cr) Lec 3.

OR

4b. HIST 304 United States Military History Since 1917 (3 cr) Lec 3.

5. MNGT 311- Leadership, Communications & Teams (3 cr) Lec 3.

Students must take two of the four courses below:

6. MNGT 411 Leading People & Projects (3 cr) Lec 3.

7. MNGT 412 Negotiating & Conflict Management (3 cr) Lec 3.

8. MNGT 413 Building Ethical & Sustainable Organizations (3 cr) Lec 3.

9. MNGT 414 Leadership in a Global Context (3 cr) Lec 3.

NOTE: If MNGT 311 is a required course for your major, you may take three of the four above courses to complete the minor as long as none of the courses above are used in their major. To complete their minor, if any of the above courses are used in their major, they may select from the courses below as substitutes:

MNGT 361, MNGT 461, SCMS 335, SCMS 437, SCMS 459, SCMS 444, ECON 416, ECON 417, ECON 433, MRKT 453, or MRKT 458.

A total of 18 credit hours must be completed for the minor. No double counting is allowed between majors and minors.

Military Leadership Minor (Aerospace ROTC)

1. AERO 441 National Security Affairs & Preparation for Active Duty I (3 cr) Lec.

2. AERO 441L Leadership Lab (0 cr) Lab.

3. AERO 442 National Security Affairs & Preparation for Active Duty II (3 cr) Lec 3.

4. AERO 442L Leadership Lab (0 cr) Lab.

5a. HIST 303 United States Military History, 1607-1917 (3 cr) Lec 3.

OR

5b. HIST 304 United States Military History Since 1917 (3 cr) Lec 3.

6. MNGT 311 Leadership, Communications & Teams (3 cr) Lec 3.

Students must take two of the four courses below:

7. MNGT 411 Leading People & Projects (3 cr) Lec 3.

8. MNGT 412 Negotiating & Conflict Management (3 cr) Lec 3.

9. MNGT 413 Building Ethical & Sustainable Organizations (3 cr) Lec 3.

10. MNGT 414 Leadership in a Global Context (3 cr) Lec 3.

NOTE: If MNGT 311 is a required course for your major, you may take three of the four above courses to complete the minor as long as none of the courses above are used in their major. To complete their minor, if any of the above courses are used in their major, they may select from the courses below as substitutes:

MNGT 361, MNGT 461, SCMS 335, SCMS 437, SCMS 459, SCMS 444, ECON 416, ECON 417, ECON 433, MRKT 453, or MRKT 458.

A total of 18 credit hours must be completed for the minor. No double counting is allowed between majors and minors

Sales Certificate

The ability to sell is a universal skillset and there is some form of selling involved in almost every job. Students who are interested in developing their sales skills and potentially pursuing a career in sales can get a certificate or advanced certificate in sales through the Center for Sales Excellence in the College of Business Administration (CBA). The sales certificate program is open to all UNL undergraduates – students do not have to be CBA majors/minors to be a part of this program.

To pursue the certificate or advanced certificate, all students must first take MRKT 257 Sales Communication (3 cr). This prerequisite class introduces students to the fundamentals of the sales communication process. MRKT 257 also meets the ACE 2 communication requirement. Following this class, interested students can apply for admission into the sales certificate program. Selected students will need to take the following courses to obtain a Certificate in Sales Excellence:

MRKT 357 Advanced Professional Selling (3 cr)

MRKT 371 Sales Practicum I (1 cr)

MRKT 457 Customer Relationship Management (3 cr)

MRKT 458 Sales Force Management (3 cr)

After taking these courses, students interested in earning an Advanced Certificate in Sales Excellence must take the following additional course:

MRKT 460 Key Account Selling (3 cr)<

The certificate and advanced certificate will be awarded by CBA. Both complement the student’s existing major/minor and serve as a formal recognition that the student has satisfactorily completed the aforementioned course requirements. Certificates will not be listed on the student’s transcripts. However, given the value of the certificates’ curricula to prospective employers, students will benefit by mentioning these certificates on their resume.

GRADUATE STUDENT INFORMATION

Graduate program options include:

MBA Programs

Master of Business Administration (MBA)

Joint Programs

Master of Business Administration/Master of Architecture

Master of Business Administration/Juris Doctorate

Master of Professional Accountancy/Juris Doctorate

Other Masters Programs

Master of Professional Accountancy (MPA)

Master of Science in Actuarial Science

Master of Arts in Business with a specialization in Marketing

Master of Arts in Economics

Ph.D. Programs

Economics

Business with specializations in:

Accountancy

Finance

Management

Marketing

Additional information on all graduate degree programs, including those listed above, can be found in the Graduate Studies Bulletin. For more information, please go to www.unl.edu/gradstudies.

Education & Human Sciences

DESCRIPTION

Marjorie Kostelnik, Ph.D., Dean and Associate Director Agricultural Research Division; Professor of Child, Youth and Family Studies

Beth Doll, Ph.D., Associate Dean and Professor of Educational Psychology

Debra Mullen, Ph.D., Associate Dean and Lecturer in Educational Administration

For additional information or questions, contact:

Dean’s Office, 105 Home Economics Building, 402-472-2916

or

Dean’s Office, 231 Mabel Lee Hall, 402-472-5400

Website: http://cehs.unl.edu

The College of Education and Human Sciences (CEHS) is dedicated to enhancing the lives of individuals, families, schools, and communities and to strengthening the relationships among them. CEHS includes seven departments which collectively offer students a wide range of academic programs that can lead to careers and professions in such areas as:

Education: Careers include teaching in elementary and secondary schools; special education; and speech-language pathology.
Health, Medical or Wellness: Careers include clinical and community nutrition; medical and health programs; fitness and wellness programs; and athletic training.
Human Sciences: Careers include early childhood education; human services; job, family and personal counseling; and social work.
Hotel, Restaurant and Tourism Management and Culinary Science: Careers include working in tourism; event planning; hotel operations; and food product development.
Journalism/Communication: Careers include broadcasting, news editorial and advertising.
Textiles, Merchandising and Fashion Design: Careers include textile design; apparel design; fashion illustration; visual merchandising; and product development.

The CEHS faculty, academic advisers, and the entire college staff welcome you to explore the many academic and career opportunities our college has to offer UNL students. Please let us know if there is any way we can be of assistance to you. This Web page is designed to conveniently help you find information and answers to any questions you may have. If you are unable to locate what you are looking for, please contact the Student Services Center at 402-472-8625.

ADMISSION

College Admission

Students accepted by the University must have an ACT of 20 or SAT of 950, or rank in the upper half of their high school graduating class, and have the following high school preparation to be eligible for guaranteed admission to the College of Education and Human Sciences:

Four years of English that include intensive reading and writing experience;
Two years of one foreign language;
Four years of mathematics, that include Algebra I, II, geometry and one year that builds on a knowledge of algebra;
Three years of natural sciences that include at least two years selected from biology, physics, chemistry, and earth science and one year of laboratory instruction;
Three years of social studies, to include at least one year of American and/or world history and one year of history, American government, and/or geography.

Transfer and Readmitted Students

Transfer students from universities or colleges outside of UNL and readmitted students seeking admission to the College of Education and Human Sciences must have an accumulated average of 2.0 on a 4.0 scale or above and no high school deficiencies. Students who do not meet these requirements must enroll as deciding students in the Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center or in another college. Once they have completed 12 graded hours at UNL with a minimum 2.0 grade point average, and have removed any high school deficiencies, UNL students may apply for admission to the College.

Transfer and readmitted students must meet the graduation requirements for the College of Education and Human Sciences as stated in the current catalog in effect at the time they enter or reenter the College.

Students who left the College on probation, or who were dismissed, may seek readmission to the College after two semesters by applying to the UNL Admissions Office. Readmission is not assured. However, the admissions committee is receptive to giving students a second opportunity to be successful. The committee is interested in knowing what the student has done in the intervening period that would suggest the student will be successful when readmitted. Successfully completing correspondence courses and/or community college courses is an effective way to demonstrate one’s commitment to academic success.

Transferring from Other Colleges within UNL

Students transferring to the College of Education and Human Sciences from another University of Nebraska–Lincoln college or from the Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center must have a minimum cumulative GPA of 2.0, be in good academic standing, and meet the freshman entrance requirements that exist at the time of their admission to the College of Education and Human Sciences. Students must fulfill degree requirements that exist at the time of their admission to the college, not at the time they enter UNL.

To remain current, College of Education and Human Sciences students must enroll in, and complete, at least one UNL course that will apply toward degree requirements during a 12 month period. Students who readmit following an absence of one year or more must meet all requirements in the Undergraduate Bulletin in effect at the time of readmission and enrollment. Students who transfer to another UNL college and later return to the College of Education and Human Sciences will be considered readmitted students. Students who transfer out of a teacher education program, but who continue their certification program while seeking a degree in another UNL college, are exempt from this policy.

International Students

The College of Education and Human Sciences welcomes undergraduate international students. As a part of admission to the College, international students must present a TOEFL score of 550 or higher and TSE score of 230 or higher.

Students seeking teacher education and state certification must meet the same requirements as any other undergraduate students, including the CORE examination or other basic skills test approved by the Nebraska Department of Education. Students who have received a degree outside of the United States and are interested in teacher certification are required to have a transcript review completed by an approved agency not directly associated with the University of Nebraska. For more information, please contact the Student Services Center.

Removal of Deficiencies

Students admitted to the University with core deficiencies are expected to remove those deficiencies in a timely manner. Students with deficiencies are not eligible for graduation. The courses that students use to clear core deficiencies may also be used to meet ACE requirements or other graduation requirements. The Dean of the College of Education and Human Sciences will make the final decision concerning any problems or questions that may arise in satisfying requirements to remove deficiencies.

ADVISING

College of Education and Human Sciences students are encouraged to meet with their assigned academic adviser prior to registration for any term (fall, spring, and summer session). Every CEHS student is assigned to an adviser. If you do not know the name of your academic adviser, please call the advising center at 402-472-8625 or drop-by 105 Henzlik Hall.

The College of Education and Human Sciences Student Services Center is staffed with professional advisers who assist students with assessing educational goals, planning programs of study, understanding program requirements and knowing policies and procedures. As course selection and registration are critical to the timely completion of their academic goals, students are well advised to seek regular academic counseling from their assigned advisers in the Center to obtain the most up-to-date information regarding current requirements and timely completion of degree programs. The Center is also staffed with professionals to coordinate field placements, student teaching, and teaching certificate application.

Ultimately, students are themselves responsible for fulfilling all the requirements of the curriculum in which they are enrolled. The intellectual mentoring relationship between academic adviser and student is protected by confidentiality and strengthened by listening with understanding to student concerns. A student remains with an adviser for the duration of the educational program unless the student changes his/her program of study.

ACADEMIC PROGRAMS & POLICIES

Academic Load

A maximum of 18 credit hours may be taken each semester (up to 4 hours in the Pre-Session; up to 7 in each five-week session; up to 9 in the eight-week session) without special authorization from the Director of Advising. UNL students must be enrolled in 12 hours in a semester to be considered full time. Most first-year students are advised to take no more than 12-15 credit hours in the first semester. This allows new students to make an easier transition from high school to college study. Most students require 2-3 hours of preparation for every hour in class, so a schedule of 12 credit hours is actually equivalent to a 36-48 hour a week job.

Outside work may interfere with academic success. The student who must work should plan to take a lighter load and consider taking some summer sessions or an extra semester or two to complete the work required for a degree.

Students should check if restrictions on the number of graded hours each term govern their continued eligibility for medical/auto insurance, scholarships, and/or financial aid.

Credit Rules

Credit by Exam

Students who believe that previous experience satisfies course requirements may approach the appropriate academic department for possible credit by exam options. Credit is rarely given simply for work experience.

Dual Degrees

Students in the College of Education and Human Sciences may earn a bachelor of science degree from the College of Education and Human Sciences and a bachelor of science degree from another UNL college. Students must complete the degree requirements for both colleges and a minimum of 30 credit hours beyond their primary college.

Student Recognition

Dean’s List

A Dean’s List of Education and Human Sciences and dual matriculated students who meet the stated criteria is published in the fall and spring semesters. To be eligible, students must have a minimum semester grade point average of 3.75 in 12 or more graded semester hours. Exceptions are made for students taking required courses offered only on a Pass/No Pass basis.

Student teachers and practica students who either (1) enter the semester of student teaching with a cumulative GPA of 3.75 or above, or (2) earn a 3.75 GPA during the preceding semester on the basis of 12 or more graded semester hours, will be eligible for the Dean’s List with recommendation from the University supervisor.

Post-baccalaureate students working on certifications are eligible upon request to the Director of Advising, but only undergraduate hours apply.

Degrees with Distinction

In recognition of outstanding academic excellence, the College of Education and Human Sciences recommends the bachelors degree With Distinction, With High Distinction and With Highest Distinction. All students graduating with distinction must meet the following criteria:

Candidates must have completed at least 60 hours at UNL (Child, Youth and Family Studies students enrolled at UNO) by the time of graduation.
Persons in teaching endorsement programs must satisfactorily complete student teaching; persons in non-endorsement programs must satisfactorily fulfill practica or other internship experiences as required by their programs of study.
Eligibility is based on the cumulative grade point average of all credit hours taken at UNL (UNO) prior to the beginning of the term in which the student receives his or her degree.

Highest Distinction. Candidates for the bachelors degree who have successfully completed the program to which they were admitted and achieved a 4.0 cumulative grade point average.

High Distinction. Candidates for the bachelors degree who have successfully completed the program to which they were admitted and achieved a 3.950 thru 3.999 cumulative grade point average.

Distinction. Candidates for the bachelors degree who have successfully completed the program to which they were admitted and have achieved a 3.850 thru 3.949 cumulative grade point average.

Undergraduate Scholarships and Fellowships

In addition to the scholarships awarded by the University, the College of Education and Human Sciences awards a number of scholarships funded by various donors—individuals, organizations and foundations. Criteria for awarding these scholarships vary to meet the wishes of the donors but often include financial need, academic performance, major area of study and class standing.

Scholarships which vary in amount are awarded annually to incoming first time, transfer, and continuing College of Education and Human Sciences students. First-time freshmen need to complete the UNL Application for Admission and the FAFSA. Continuing students should complete, annually, the scholarship application through their MyRED account, and include a resume. Completion of the FAFSA is also recommended.

Substitutions and Waivers

In rare cases, there may be a need for students to request a special substitution or waiver to curriculum requirements. Such a request is made only in exceptional and unusual circumstances and cannot serve as an excuse for not following correct degree requirements. Specific instructions and procedures are available from students’ academic advisers in the Student Services Center, 105 Henzlik Hall.

BULLETIN TO USE

Students are responsible for following the rules, policies and requirements found in the UNL Undergraduate Bulletin for the academic year in which they were last admitted to a program in the College of Education and Human Sciences. Students must complete all program requirements from a single bulletin year. In consultation with their adviser, a student may choose to move to and follow a subsequent bulletin if it is in their best interest.

COLLEGE DEGREE REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Minimum Grade Requirements

Grade requirements vary from major to major. Please see the appropriate major listing or check with your adviser regarding minimum grade requirements.

Pass/No Pass Option

CEHS students are allowed to take up to 12 hours of Pass/No Pass (P/N) credit. The college departments vary on P/N policies. Students should check with their adviser to be certain they qualify for the Pass/No Pass option.

Grade Appeals

Any student enrolled in a course in the College of Education and Human Sciences who wishes to appeal alleged unfair and prejudicial treatment by a faculty member shall present his/her appeal in writing to the Dean’s Office no later than 30 days after notice of the student’s final course grade has been mailed from campus.

Students may use and are encouraged to use the following sequential procedures to appeal the grade. The problem may be solved at any of the levels of the appeal procedure.

1. Contact the instructor. Frequently the problems can be solved at this point.

2. Submit a request to the chair of the department.

3. Take the case to the departmental Grading Appeals Committee. The Committee is contacted by the department chair.

4. Take the case to the College Appeals, Retention and Certification Committee by contacting the Dean’s Office.

The complaint will be forwarded to a committee consisting of faculty and student representatives. After a hearing, the Committee will make a written recommendation regarding the appeal. The Committee’s recommendation is binding on the appealing student and faculty member.

Transfer Credit Rules

Acceptance of Transfer Grades

Grades earned at UNL, UNO, UNK
Grades of D-, D, D+, and C- satisfy requirements in all programs in the College unless specified otherwise. Students who receive a grade of D-, D, D+, C-, however, are encouraged to retake the course.
Grades earned outside the University of Nebraska system

The college will accept no more than 9 credit hours of grades less than a C from any program outside the University of Nebraska system. Grades below a C can only be applied to general education requirements and elective classes.

Maximum Number of Hours for Transfer

Transfer courses are evaluated by the University and by the College to determine UNL and College course equivalencies. The College determines which courses will be accepted and how they will apply toward degree requirements. Sixty (60) is the maximum number of hours that will be accepted on transfer from a two-year college. Ninety (90) is the maximum number of hours that will be accepted on transfer from accredited four-year colleges and universities.

Courses taken 10 years before admission or readmission to the College will be evaluated by the major department to determine if it is appropriate to accept those courses for transfer credit and for application to degree requirements. Specific courses will be reviewed in keeping with the guidelines specified by each department.

Transfer Credit from Technical, Non-Accredited and Foreign Institutions

Students who desire to transfer from these institutions must have each course evaluated by the appropriate departmental representative. All rules stated above in reference to grades and maximum credit hours apply. For additional information and guidance in this process contact the Dean’s Office.

Transfer Agreements with UNO and UNK

Transfer agreements between the three institutions within the University System allow for a smooth transition for students interested in taking courses from UNO, UNK, and/or UNL. Although restrictions noted above on grades and maximum transfer hours still apply, there are some exceptions. For purposes of residency, courses from UNO and UNK fulfill these requirements. Students planning to major in a program in the college should read the specific requirements noted with individual programs. Questions about academic transfer should be addressed to the Advising Office.

Transfer Agreements with Community Colleges

Articulation agreements and “Transfer with Ease Programs” with Nebraska community colleges indicate how courses and programs will transfer to UNL and the College of Education and Human Sciences. The same guidelines noted above on the acceptance of courses, grades, and hours also apply to these institutions. Students interested in transferring from a community college should consult with their school or the Student Services Center to determine which courses will transfer to fulfill specific College of Education and Human Sciences requirements.

Courses from accredited two-year institutions will generally not be substituted for 400-level human sciences classes in the College. The 300-level courses will be considered on an individual basis by the respective departments in the College of Education and Human Sciences.

Courses taken prior to course articulation agreements will be accepted contingent upon departmental validation of the credit.

Residency Rules

Students must earn a minimum of 120 credit hours to earn a degree.

All students are expected to complete at least 30 of their final 36 hours of credit at UNL.

Degree Application Process

It is the student's responsibility to notify the University Registrar of their intent to graduate.  This should be done very early in the semester the student plans to graduate.  Students should access their Degree Audit via MyRed at least once each term to review degree requirements and progress toward graduation.  It is the student’s responsibility to make sure their Degree Audit accurately reflects their current College and program of study.

Students are expected to develop a clear understanding of degree requirements and to plan their course of study with a College adviser.  Students requiring clarification of outstanding degree requirements should visit with a College adviser promptly.   Students who believe their Degree Audit has errors or omissions should visit with a College adviser promptly. It is important that you resolve these matters as soon as practicable to avoid a delay in graduation.

Each student must submit an Application for Graduation plus $25.00 check or cash fee for each degree to be received to the Office of the University Registrar by:

            The last Friday in January for May graduation

            The last Friday in June for August graduation

            The last Friday in September for December graduation

An electronic Application for Graduation and payment is available via MyRed.  Those students choosing to apply for graduation in person may visit the Office of the University Registrar, 107 Canfield Administration Building.  Applications for Graduation submitted in person or by mail must be accompanied by payment.  Failure to submit a timely Application for Graduation may preclude the awarding of a degree in the intended term.

MINORS & AREAS OF SPECIALIZATIONS OFFERED

Minors Available

Child, Youth and Family Studies Minor – 18 hours

Coaching Minor – 15 hours

Education Minor – 18 hours

Hospitality, Restaurant and Tourism Management Minor – 18 hours

Textiles, Merchandising and Fashion Design Minor – 15 hours

Supplemental Education Endorsements

To pursue a supplemental endorsement, students must either hold a valid teaching certificate or be pursuing a teacher education program. Please contact an academic adviser or the specified contact person for information regarding any of the following supplemental endorsements.

Coaching (Grades 7-12) 15 hours: Persons with this endorsement may coach interscholastic athletic events for participants in grades 7 through 11. ATHT 235 (3 hrs); ATHC 279 (3 hrs); ATHC 494 (3 hrs). Select three from the following: ATHC 311, ATHC 312, ATHC 317, ATHC 318 (6 hrs). Contact: Dr Tom Wandzilak, 116 Henzlik Hall, twandzilak1@unl.edu, 402-472-8626.

Cooperative Education–Diversified Occupations (Grades 9-12) 6-8 hours: An endorsement in Business, Marketing and Information Technology or Industrial Technology is required. Persons with this endorsement may coordinate, teach and supervise programs of instruction that develop career and life skills. TEAC 425/825 or ALEC 234 (3 hrs); SPED 434/834 or ALEC 424 (3 hrs); 1,000 hours of approved work experience or TEAC 297 or ALEC 390 0-2 hrs. Contact your adviser.

English as a 2nd Language–Undergraduate (Grades K-12) 9-18 hours: Persons with this endorsement may teach English as a second language in grades K through 12. There are three undergraduate courses that may be taken to prepare for this endorsement or which may qualify an undergraduate student for a provisional endorsement in ESL, however, the ESL endorsement cannot be completed at the undergraduate level; graduate level courses must be taken to complete the endorsement. TEAC 413A, TEAC 413K and TEAC 413M. Please see adviser and/or Joyce Richter at jrichter1@unl.edu or 402/ 472-8635 for list of graduate courses to complete the endorsement.

Information Technology (Grades K-12) 17 hours: Persons with this endorsement may teach information technology courses in grades K through 12.

NOTE: Endorsement in business and marketing education required. TEAC 323, 444 and 451L (3 hrs ea); 397L (1 hr); CSCE 101 and 150 (3 hrs ea); CSCE 101L (1 hr). Contact your CEHS adviser.

GRADUATE STUDENT INFORMATION

Post-Baccalaureate & Graduate Teacher Certification Programs

General & Admission Information

Students who have received a bachelors degree or higher and desire to obtain an initial teaching certificate may do so by pursuing an initial teaching certification program with a masters degree. Students must apply to the Graduate College for admission to the University of Nebraska–Lincoln at: www.unl.edu/gradstudies and apply online.

Graduate-Level Initial Teacher Certification Programs

Business, Marketing & Information Technology (Grades 6-12) 46-76 hours: Must also enroll in a masters degree program. Students need 1,000 hours paid business-related work experience or TEAC 297J for 0-2 hrs. EDPS 851, EDPS 854 (3 hrs ea); SPED 834 (3 hrs); TEAC 229, TEAC 323, TEAC 397J, TEAC 443, TEAC 444, TEAC 451K, TEAC 452J, TEAC 803B, TEAC 825, (TEAC 830 or TEAC 831 or TEAC 834), TEAC 861 (3 hrs ea); TEAC 897J (4 hrs). The following are also required but may have already been completed with an undergraduate degree and may transfer into the program: ACCT 201, ACCT 202 (3 hrs ea); BLAW 371 (3 hrs); ECON 211, ECON 212 (3 hrs ea); FINA 260 (3 hrs); MNGT 121 or ENTR 121 (3 hrs); MRKT 341, MRKT 345, MRKT 347 (3 hrs ea). Contact: Department of Teaching, Learning and Teacher Education, 402-472-2231.

Early Childhood Special Education (Birth thru K) 52+ hrs: Prerequisites: Bachelor’s degree from accredited institution; acceptance into the teacher education program in CEHS and the masters degree program in Department of Special Education and Communication Disorders; Prerequisites (22 hrs): CYAF 474/874, EDPS 362/854, SPED 362, 800, 818, 3 hrs each; SPED 496Y (1 hr); TEAC 330/861, 331/831 (3 hrs each).  Required completion (or equivalent) (30 hrs):  CYAF 970, SPED 860, 861, 862, 863, (SPED 876 or SLPA 251), 882, 879Q and 960, TEAC 410/810; (3 hrs each).  Contact Department of Special Education and Communication Disorders at 472-2141 for advising.

Elementary Education (Grades K-6 and MAET masters degree) 44 hours: A 14-month accelerated program with masters degree. TEAC 893, 894A (1 hr ea); TEAC 800, TEAC 801, TEAC 808, TEAC 811A, TEAC 822A, TEAC 840D, TEAC 841, TEAC 842A, TEAC 889, TEAC 890, (3 hrs ea); TEAC 897A (6 hrs), CYAF 971 (3 hrs); SPED 801A (3 hrs). Contact: Department of Teaching, Learning and Teacher Education, 402-472-2231.

Family and Consumer Science Education (Grades 6-12) 90-91 hours: CYAF 160, CYAF 222, CYAF 280, CYAF 333, CYAF 380, CYAF 382, CYAF 803B, CYAF 851 (3 hrs ea); CYAF 852 (4 hrs); CYAF 894J (2 hrs); CYAF 897J (10 hrs); NUTR 244 (3 hrs); NUTR 245 (1 hr); NUTR 250, 372, (TMFD 123 or CYAF 493) (3 hrs ea); EDPS 851, 854 (3 hrs ea); EDPS 297 (1 hr); SPED 801B (3 hrs); TEAC 825, (830 or 831 or 834), 861, 880A (3 hrs ea). Select one of three plans for additional content from the following areas 15-16 hrs: Nutrition and Health: NUTR 100, NUTR 131, NUTR 251, NUTR 253, NUTR 344, NUTR 430 (15 hrs); Hospitality and Food Service: HRTM 289, HRTM 373, HRTM 477, HRTM 489; NUTR 370, NUTR 371 (16 hrs); Textiles, Merchandising and Fashion Design: TMFD 123 or CYAF 493, TMFD 206, TMFD 212, TMFD 213, TMFD 325, TMFD 325, TMFD 407, TMFD 408, TMFD 410 (15 hrs); Family Studies: CYAF 285, CYAF 322, CYAF 446, CYAF 458, CYAF 488, CYAF 493, CYAF 495 (15 hrs); or Child Studies: CYAF 271/L, CYAF 371, CYAF 374, CYAF 383, CYAF 384, CYAF 385, CYAF 474 (15 hrs); Health Occupations: CYAF 446, CYAF 471, CLAS 166, GERO 200, GERO 307, PSYC 280, PHIL 106, PHIL 206. Contact: Department of Child, Youth and Family Studies, 402-472-8209.

French Education (Grades 7-12) 80 hours: Must also enroll in a masters degree program. FREN 101, FREN 102 (5 hrs ea); FREN 201, FREN 202, FREN 203, FREN 204, FREN 301, FREN 302, FREN 303, FREN 304, FREN 319 (3 hrs ea); select two from the following: FREN 321, FREN 322, or FREN 323 (6 hrs); one FREN 400-level course (3 hrs); EDPS 851, EDPS 854 (3 hrs ea); SPED 801B (3 hrs); TEAC 803B, (TEAC 830 or TEAC 831 or TEAC 834), TEAC 851R, TEAC 852R, TEAC 861, TEAC 880A, TEAC 894R (3 hrs ea); TEAC 897R (4 hrs). Contact: Department of Teaching, Learning and Teacher Education, 402-472-2231.

German Education (Grades 7-12) 80 hours: Must also enroll in a masters degree program. GERM 101, GERM 102 (5 hrs ea); GERM 201, GERM 202, GERM 203, 204, GERM 301, GERM 302, GERM 303, GERM 304, GERM 321, GERM 398 (3 hrs ea); two GERM 400-level courses (3 hrs ea); EDPS 851, EDPS 854 (3 hrs ea); SPED 801B (3 hrs); TEAC 803B, (TEAC 830 or TEAC 831 or TEAC 834), TEAC 851R, TEAC 852R, TEAC 861, TEAC 880A, TEAC 894R (3 hrs ea); TEAC 897R (4 hrs). Contact: Department of Teaching, Learning and Teacher Education, 402-472-2231.

Inclusive Early Childhood Education (Birth-Grade 3) 98 hours: CYAF 160 or CYAF 170, CYAF 271, CYAF 374, CYAF 380, CYAF 874 (3 hrs ea); CYAF 270 (2 hrs); CYAF 270L, CYAF 271L and CYAF 374/L (1 hr ea); CYAF 497A (9 hrs); EDPS 851 (3 hrs); MATH 300 (3 hrs); SLPA 251 (3 hrs); SPED 201, SPED 303, SPED 362, SPED 815 (3 hrs ea); SPED 496Y and SPED 815A (1 hr ea); TEAC 297A (2 hrs); TEAC 302, TEAC 305, TEAC 397D, TEAC 403A, TEAC 816A, TEAC 816B, TEAC 816D, (TEAC 830 or TEAC 831 or TEAC 834), TEAC 861, TEAC 880A (3 hrs ea); TEAC 497A (8 hrs). Contact: Department of Special Education and Communication Disorders, 402-472-2141.

Latin Education (Grades 7-12) 72-79 hours: Must also enroll in a masters degree program. LATN 101 and LATN 102 (5 hrs ea) or LATN 151 (3 hrs) if a student has had 2-4 years of Latin or Greek in high school); LATN 301, LATN 302, LATN 303, LATN 304, LATN 350, LATN 399, LATN 456, LATN 491, LATN 492 (3 hrs ea); GREK 102 (5 hrs); select one course from the following: ENGL 322A, ENGL 322B, ENGL 420, ENGL 427 or TEAC 438 (3 hrs); EDPS 851, EDPS 854 (3 hrs ea); SPED 801B (3 hrs); TEAC 803B, (TEAC 830 or TEAC 831 or TEAC 834), TEAC 851R, TEAC 852R, TEAC 861, TEAC 880A, TEAC 894R (3 hrs ea); TEAC 897R (4 hrs). Contact: Department of Teaching, Learning and Teacher Education, 402-472-2231.

Math Education (Grades 7-12 and MAMT masters degree) 42 hours: A 14-month program with masters degree. Must have a bachelors degree in science, technology, engineering or mathematics and have completed 21 hours in mathematics at the calculus level with a grade of B or better. Successful completion of the Praxis II Math Content Exams (0061) and (0063) required for application. TEAC 800, TEAC 801, TEAC 840D, TEAC 851P, TEAC 852P, TEAC 889, (3 hrs ea); TEAC 894P (2 hrs); TEAC 897P (4 hrs); SPED 801B (3 hrs); EDPS 991 (3 hrs); MATH 810T, MATH 896, MATH 896 (3 hrs ea); MATH elective (3 hrs)—chosen with adviser. Contact: Department of Teaching, Learning and Teacher Education, 402-472-2231.

Russian Education (Grades 7-12) 80 hours: Must also enroll in a masters degree program. RUSS 101, RUSS 102 (5 hrs ea); RUSS 201, RUSS 202, RUSS 301, RUSS 302, 303, RUSS 304, RUSS 398 (3 hrs ea); select five courses from the following: RUSS 399, RUSS 408, RUSS 441, RUSS 442, RUSS 482, RUSS 498 (3 hrs ea); EDPS 851, 854 (3 hrs ea); SPED 801B (3 hrs); TEAC 803B, (TEAC 830 or TEAC 831 or TEAC 834), TEAC 851R, TEAC 852R, TEAC 861, TEAC 880A, TEAC 894R (3 hrs ea); TEAC 897R (4 hrs). Contact: Department of Teaching, Learning and Teacher Education, 402-472-2231.

Science Education (Grades 7-12 and MAST masters degree) 42 hours: A 14-month program with masters degree. All content course requirements must be completed prior to starting the program. For a single subject endorsement (biology or chemistry or physics or earth and space science), must have 24 hrs of lab-based courses in one subject area and 12 hrs of lab-based courses distributed equally among the other three ancillary areas. For a field endorsement in science, must have 24 hrs of lab-based courses in one core subject area and a minimum of 12 hrs each of lab-based courses in the other ancillary science areas. TEAC 800, TEAC 801, TEAC 803B, TEAC 813M, TEAC 842E, TEAC 851V, TEAC 852V, TEAC 861, TEAC 880A, TEAC 889 (3 hrs ea); TEAC 894V (2 hrs); TEAC 897V (4 hrs); SPED 801B (3 hrs); EDPS 991 (3 hrs). Contact: Department of Teaching, Learning and Teacher Education, 402-472-2231.

Spanish Education (Grades 7-12) 80 hours: Must also enroll in a masters degree program. SPAN 101, SPAN 102 (5 hrs ea); SPAN 201, SPAN 202, SPAN 203, SPAN 204, SPAN 303, SPAN 304, SPAN 319, SPAN 321, SPAN 331, SPAN 403 or SPAN 405 (3 hrs ea); select two classes from the following: SPAN 304, SPAN 311, SPAN 312, SPAN 314, SPAN 315, SPAN 317, SPAN 398 (3 hrs ea); EDPS 851, 854 (3 hrs ea); SPED 801B (3 hrs); TEAC 803B, (TEAC 830 or TEAC 831 or TEAC 834), TEAC51R, TEAC 852R, TEAC 861, TEAC 880A, TEAC 894R (3 hrs ea); TEAC 897R (4 hrs). Contact: Department of Teaching, Learning and Teacher Education, 402-472-2231.

Special Education–Mild/Moderate Disabilities (Grades K-6) 44 hours: TEAC 430/830 or TEAC 431/831 or TEAC 434/834, TEAC 861, TEAC 259 or TEAC 880A (3 hrs ea); EDPS 450/850 and EDPS 454/854 (3 hrs ea); SPED 400/800, SPED 412/812, SPED 414/814, SPED 303 or SPED 818, SPED 820, SPED 480/880 (3 hrs ea); SPED 415/815 and SPED 415A/815A (2 hrs ea); SPED 496M/896M (1 hr); SPED 497M/897M (6 hrs). Contact: Department of Special Education and Communication Disorders, 402-472-2141.

Special Education–Mild/Moderate Disabilities (Grades 7-12) 44 hours: TEAC 430/830 or TEAC 431/831 or TEAC 434/834, TEAC 861, TEAC 259 or TEAC 880A (3 hrs ea); EDPS 451/851 and EDPS 454/854 (3 hrs ea); SPED 400/800, SPED 407/807, SPED 412/812, SPED 303 or SPED 818, SPED 820, SPED 480/880 (3 hrs ea); SPED 406/806, SPED 406A/806A (2 hrs ea); and SPED 496M/896M (1 hr); SPED 497M/897M (6 hrs). Contact: Department of Special Education and Communication Disorders, 402-472-2141.

Special Education–Mild/Moderate Disabilities (Grades K-12) 54 hours: TEAC 430/830 or TEAC 431/831 or TEAC 434/834, TEAC 861, TEAC 259 or TEAC 880A (3 hrs ea); EDPS 450/850, EDPS 451/851, EDPS 454/854 (3 hrs ea); SPED 400/800, SPED 407/807, SPED 412/812, SPED 414/814, SPED 303 or SPED 818, SPED 820, SPED 480/880 (3 hrs ea); SPED 406/806, SPED 406A/806A, SPED 415/815, SPED 415A/815A (2 hrs ea); SPED 496M/896M (1 hr); SPED 497M/897M (6 hrs). Contact: Department of Special Education and Communication Disorders, 402-472-2141.

Graduate-Level Added or Supplementary Endorsements and Administrative Certificates/ Endorsements

Assessment Leadership (Grades P-12) 18 hours: Must have or qualify for a standard teaching certificate and complete a masters degree or specialist program. Persons with this endorsement may assist in or facilitate the development of assessment programs for students in Pre-Kindergarten through grade 12. TEAC 849A, TEAC 849B, TEAC 849E, TEAC 849J (3 hrs ea); 991 (6 hrs). Contact: Department of Teaching, Learning and Teacher Education, 402-472-2231.

Counselor, School Guidance (Grades K-6) 47 hours: Must have a valid initial teaching certificate and 2 years of teaching experience and must also be admitted into a masters degree program in Educational Psychology. EDPS 800, EDPS50, EDPS53, EDPS 859, EDPS 866, EDPS 868, EDPS69 or EDPS 985, EDPS 870, EDPS 964, EDPS 965A, EDPS 974, EDPS 975, EDPS 984 (3 hrs ea); EDPS 997A, EDPS 997B (4 hrs ea). To add a 7-12 endorsement to this, a student must also take EDPS 851 and EDPS 997B at the 7-12 grade level. Contact: Department of Educational Psychology, 402-472-2223.

Counselor, School Guidance (Grades 7-12) 47 hours: Must have a valid initial teaching certificate and 2 years of teaching experience and must also be admitted into a masters degree program in Educational Psychology. EDPS 800, EDPS 851, EDPS 853, EDPS 859, EDPS 866, EDPS 868, EDPS 869 or EDPS 985, EDPS 870, EDPS 964, EDPS 965A, EDPS 974, EDPS 975, EDPS 984 (3 hrs ea); EDPS 997A, EDPS 997B (4 hrs ea). To add a K-6 endorsement to this, a student must also take EDPS 850 and 997B at the K-6 grade level. Contact: Department of Educational Psychology, 402-472-2223.

Curriculum Supervisor (Grades PK-12) 36 hours: This is an Administrative Certificate/Endorsement that requires the completion of 36 graduate hours. For admission to the masters degree or certificate program and to be recommended for administrative certification and endorsement, students must also satisfy additional NDE state requirements, including but not limited to, possession of a valid Regular Teaching Certificate, evidence of two years of successful teaching experience, human relations training, special education training, and basic skills competency. Candidates must apply to both the Department of Educational Administration and to the Department of Teaching Learning and Teacher Education. EDAD 811, EDAD 830, EDAD 851, EDAD 903, EDAD 948 (3 hrs ea); select 3 hrs from the following: EDAD 833, EDAD 837, EDAD 852; TEAC 800, TEAC 801, TEAC 888 (3 hrs ea); 6 hrs of approved graduate courses selected from TEAC 846A, TEAC 846B, TEAC 848, TEAC 944, TEAC 944A, TEAC 944B, TEAC 944D, TEAC 944E (3 hrs ea); 3 hrs of foundations of education selected from TEAC 830, TEAC 831, TEAC 832, TEAC 834, TEAC 840, TEAC 840A, TEAC 840B, TEAC 840D, TEAC 861, TEAC 902 (3 hrs ea). Each student must satisfactorily complete a Professional Portfolio, approved by an adviser. Contact: Department of Educational Administration, 402-472-3728 and the Department of Teaching Learning and Teacher Education 402-472-2231.

Deaf or Hard of Hearing/Subject (Grades P-12) 30-45 hours: Must have a valid initial teaching certificate in Elementary Education, Middle Grades, or Special Education-Mild/Moderate Disabilities. Students without a Special Education certificate are required to take the listed prerequisite courses. Proficiency requirements: Demonstrated proficiency in American Sign Language: successful completion of SLPA 202 or minimum score on Sign Communication Proficiency Interview or EIPA or other approved measure before completion of the program. Prerequisites: SPED 400/800, SPED 412/812, SPED 414/814, SPED 303/818 (3 hrs ea); SLPA 250 or SLPA 251 or SPED 876 (3 hrs). Core Requirements: SPED 472/872, SPED 873, SPED 874, SPED 875, SPED 896D, SPED 897D, SPED 960, (3 hrs ea); SLPA 450/850, SLPA/SPED 884, SLPA/SPED 956 (3 hrs ea). Contact: Department of Special Education and Communication Disorders, 402-472-2141.

Early Childhood Special Education (Birth thru K) 39 hours: Must have a valid initial teaching certificate in Elementary Education (K-6), Special Education (K-6 or K-12), Early Childhood Education (P-3) or Inclusive Early Childhood (Birth thru grade 3) and application to the masters degree program in special education. Prerequisite course work of 9 hrs: SPED 800, (SPED 812 or CYAF 874), SPED 818 (3 hrs ea). Required completion (or equivalent) of 30 hrs: CYAF 970, SPED 860, SPED 861, SPED 862, SPED 863, SPED 876, SPED 882, SPED 960 and SPED 879Q (3 hrs ea), TEAC 810. Contact: Department of Special Education and Communication Disorders, 402-472-2141.

NOTE: There is a masters degree program (52+ credit hours) available that includes an initial teaching certificate with this endorsement focus for student with undergraduate degrees outside education. Contact Special Education and Communication Disorders at 472-2141.

English as a 2nd Language (Grades K-12) 18 hours: Must have a valid initial teaching certificate or parallel with one in progress. TEAC 813A, TEAC 813B, TEAC 813J, TEAC 813K or TEAC 838, TEAC 813M, TEAC 897E (3 hrs ea). Contact: Department of Teaching, Learning and Teacher Education, 402-472-2231.

Information Technology (Grades K-12) 19 hours: Must have a valid initial teaching certificate or parallel with one in progress. TEAC 851L, 860, TEAC 882A, TEAC 882B, TEAC 882D, TEAC 882J (3 hrs ea); TEAC 894L (1 hr). Contact: Department of Teaching, Learning and Teacher Education, 402-472-2231.

Middle Level (Grades 4-9) 47-56 hours: Must have a valid Elementary Education certificate from the University of Nebraska–Lincoln. TEAC 446/846, 897Q (3 hrs ea). (TEAC 897Q can be waived if student teaching was completed in a 6th grade classroom.) Choose two subject areas from the four listed below 20-25 hrs: Language Arts (20-21 hrs): ENGL 252/852 or ENGL 253/853 (3 hrs); select one course from ENGL 254, ENGL 354/854 or ENGL 357 (3 hrs); select one course from ENGL 361A, ENGL 332/832 or ENGL 333/833 (3 hrs); TEAC 302, TEAC 439/839, TEAC 441/841 (3 hrs ea); TEAC 317 (2 hrs). Math (23-25 hrs): MATH 106 (5 hrs); MATH 107 (4 hrs) or MATH 302 (3 hrs); MATH 300M or MATH 800T (3 hrs); STAT 218 (3 hrs); STAT 203 or STAT 405/805T (3 hrs); STAT 302 or STAT 350 (3 hrs); select one course from STAT 304/804T or STAT 306 or STAT 310/858T (3 hrs). Natural Science (21-25 hrs): BIOS 101 (3 hrs) and BIOS 101L (1 hr); BIOS 232 or NRES 814 (3 hrs); GEOL 101 (4 hrs) or NRES 822 (3 hrs); select one course from AGRO 131 (3 hrs) & AGRO 132 (1 hr) or ENTO 108 (3 hrs) & ENTO 116 (1 hr) or ENTO 115 (3 hrs) & ENTO 116 (1 hr) or ENTO 410/810 (3 hrs); and select one option: Option 1: PHYS 260, PHYS 261 (3 hrs ea); PHYS 262 (1 hr) (7 hrs); Option 2: CHEM 109 (4 hrs); ASTR 103 (3 hrs); PHYS 115 (3 hrs) (10 hrs). Social Science 24 hrs: ECON 211 or ECON 850 (3 hrs); GEOG 272 (3 hrs); HIST 101, HIST 120, HIST 201, HIST 201, HIST 202, either HIST 359 or HIST 360 (3 hrs ea); POLS 100 (3 hrs). Contact: Department of Teaching, Learning and Teacher Education, 402-472-2231.

Pre-School Disabilities (Birth-K) 30-39 hours: Must have a valid initial teaching certificate in Special Education or Speech Pathology. Prerequisites: SPED 800, SPED 812, SPED 818 (or equivalents) (3 hrs ea). Required completion (or equivalent): SPED 860, SPED 861, SPED 862, SPED 863, SPED 876, SPED 882, SPED 960 or SLPA 251 (3 hrs ea); SPED 897Q (6 hrs); CYAF 970 or equivalent (3 hrs). Contact: Department of Special Education and Communication Disorders, 402-472-2141.

Principal, Elementary (Grades PK-8) 36 hours: This is an Administrative Certificate/Endorsement that requires the completion of 36 graduate hours. For admission to the masters degree or certificate program and to be recommended for administrative certification and endorsement, students must also satisfy additional NDE state requirements, including but not limited to, possession of a valid Regular Teaching Certificate, evidence of two years of successful teaching experience at the PK-8 level, human relations training, special education training, and basic skills competency. EDAD 811, EDAD 830, EDAD 833, EDAD 837, EDAD 851, 852, EDAD 903, EDAD 981 (3 hrs ea); TEAC 801 or TEAC 848 or TEAC 944 (3 hrs); TEAC 800 or TEAC 946 or TEAC 948 (3 hrs); and an approved College of Education and Human Sciences course outside the departments of EDAD or TLTE (3 hrs); an elective approved by an adviser (3 hrs). Each student must satisfactorily complete a Professional Portfolio approved by an adviser. Contact: Department of Educational Administration, 402-472-3728.

Principal, Secondary (Grades 7-12) 36 hours: This is an Administrative Certificate/Endorsement that requires the completion of 36 graduate hours. For admission to the masters degree or certificate program and to be recommended for administrative certification and endorsement, students must also satisfy additional NDE state requirements, including but not limited to, possession of a valid Regular Teaching Certificate, evidence of two years of successful teaching experience, human relations training, special education training, and basic skills competency. EDAD 811, EDAD 830, EDAD 833, EDAD 837, EDAD 851, EDAD 852, EDAD 903, EDAD 981 (3 hrs ea); TEAC 801 or TEAC 848 or TEAC 944 (3 hrs); TEAC 800 or TEAC 946 or TEAC 948 (3 hrs); and an approved College of Education and Human Sciences course outside the departments of EDAD or TLTE (3 hrs); and an elective approved by an adviser (3 hrs). Each student must satisfactorily complete a Professional Portfolio, approved by an adviser. Contact: Department of Educational Administration, 402-472-3728.

Reading Specialist (Grades P-12) 30-32 hours: Must have a valid initial teaching certificate and one year of teaching experience. Persons with this endorsement may teach, provide leadership for professional development in the area of reading, and assess and interpret data to determine and implement instructional options for teaching students. TEAC 802, TEAC 811, TEAC 836A, TEAC 838, TEAC 839, TEAC 841, TEAC 886/SPED 886, 886B (3 hrs ea); TEAC 957B/ENGL 957B (6 hrs) or select 6-8 hrs from the following list: TEAC 817, TEAC 854B, TEAC 890, TEAC 990, TEAC 921, TEAC 950, TEAC 951, TEAC 952, TEAC 953 (3 hrs ea) or TEAC 989/EDPS 989 (3 hrs) or SPED 805 (3 hrs) parallel with 805A (1 hr) or TEAC 806/SPED 806 (3 hrs) parallel with TEAC 806A/SPED 806A (1 hr) or SPED 815 (3 hrs) parallel with SPED 815A (1 hr). Contact: Department of Teaching, Learning and Teacher Education, 402-472-2231.

School Psychologist (Grades P-12) 65 hours: Must have an undergraduate degree in psychology, educational psychology, education or a related field. This is an educational specialist degree program. EDPS 850 or EDPS 851, EDPS 854, EDPS 860, EDPS 863, EDPS 867, EDPS 869, EDPS 900B (3 hrs ea); EDPS 950 (4 hrs); EDPS 951, EDPS 952, EDPS 954 (3 hrs ea); EDPS 957B (8 hrs); EDPS 948 or EDPS 868 (3 hrs); EDPS 958A (8 hrs); EDPS 996A (6 hrs); SPED (6 hrs). Contact: Department of Educational Psychology, 402-472-2223.

School Transition Specialist (Grades 7-12) 18 hours: Persons with this Special Services Counseling Endorsement may counsel and provide services for youth with disabilities and consult with teachers, parents, and students. There are three undergraduate courses that may be taken to prepare for this endorsement or which may qualify an undergraduate student for a provisional endorsement as a Transition Specialist, however the Transition Specialist endorsement cannot be completed at the undergraduate level; graduate level courses must be taken to complete the endorsement. SPED 400/800 or SPED 434/834, SPED 407/807, SPED 408/808 or SPED 893, SPED 436/836, SPED 896T, and SPED 908 (3 hrs ea). Contact: Department of Special Education and Communication Disorders, 402-472-2141.

Severe/Multiple Disabilities-Autism (Grades P-12) 23 hours: Must have a valid initial teaching certificate in Special Education, Mild/Moderate Disabilities or equivalent. SPED 480/880, SPED 809, SPED 881, SPED 882, SPED 897P (3 hrs ea); SPED 810, SPED96P, SPED 980, SPED 981 (2 hrs ea). Contact: Department of Special Education and Communication Disorders, 402-472-2141.

Superintendent (Grades PK-12) 66 hours: This is an Administrative Certificate/Endorsement that requires the completion of 60 graduate hours and completion of a specialist of doctoral program in educational administration. For admission to the six year specialist program or the Ed.D. and to be recommended for administrative certification and endorsement, students must also satisfy additional NDE state requirements, including but not limited to, possession of a valid Regular Teaching Certificate, evidence of two years of successful teaching experience, human relations training, special education training, and basic skills competency. EDAD 801, EDAD 811, EDAD 830, EDAD 833, EDAD 835, EDAD 837, EDAD 851, EDAD 852, EDAD 901, EDAD 903, EDAD 905, EDAD 906, EDAD 981, EDAD 998 (3 hrs ea); select 3 hours from the following: TEAC 801 or TEAC 848 or TEAC 944; select 3 hours from the following: TEAC 800 or TEAC 946 or TEAC 948; an approved College of Education and Human Sciences course outside the departments of EDAD or TLTE (3 hrs); approved electives (15 hrs) with the recommendation of no more than 6 hrs from the department of EDAD. Each student must satisfactorily complete a Professional Portfolio, approved by an adviser. Contact: Department of Educational Administration, 402-472-3728.

Supervisor of Special Education Programs (Grades PK-12) 36 hours: This is an Administrative Certificate/Endorsement that will appear as “Curriculum Supervisor, Special Education P-12” and requires the completion of 36 graduate hours. For admission to the masters degree or certificate program and to be recommended for administrative certification and endorsement, students must also satisfy additional NDE state requirements, including but not limited to, possession of a valid Regular Teaching Certificate in Special Education, evidence of two years of successful teaching experience, human relations training, and basic skills competency. Candidates must apply to both the Department of Educational Administration and to the Department of Special Education and Communication Disorders and will have two advisers. EDAD 811, EDAD 830, EDAD 981 (3 hrs ea); select 9 hrs from the following: EDAD 833, EDAD 837, EDAD 851, EDAD 852, or EDAD 903 (3 hrs ea); EDAD 857/SPED 857, EDAD 858/SPED 858 (3 hrs ea); 12 hrs of approved graduate courses in special education, taken within the past 6 years; 6 of these hours must be outside of the person’s endorsement area. (EDAD 856/SPED 856, Supervising Special Education is highly recommended.) Each student must satisfactorily complete a Professional Portfolio, approved by an adviser. Contact: Department of Educational Administration, 402-472-3728 and the Department of Special Education and Communication Disorders, 402-472-2141.

Visual Impairment (Grades P-12) 33-39 hours: Must have a standard teaching certificate and be admitted into the Visually Impaired program. Persons with this endorsement may teach students with visual impairments from birth through age 21. Visual impairment includes blindness, low vision (legal blindness and low vision) and vision loss associated with other impairments. If your endorsement is not in special education, the following core classes must be completed: SPED 800 and SPED 814 (3 hrs ea). Requirements: SPED 846, SPED 847, SPED 849, SPED 851, SPED 852, SPED 853, SPED 882 (3 hrs ea); SPED 852A (1 hr), SPED 852B (2 hrs); SPED 897V (3 hrs); guided electives in special education (6 hrs) selected with adviser; braille proficiency exam. Contact: Department of Special Education and Communication Disorders, 402-472-2141.

DEGREES & MAJORS &/or ENDORSEMENTS

Alphabetical Listing

Athletic Training

Biology Education (7-12)

Business, Marketing and Information Technology Education (6-12)

Chemistry Education (7-12)

Child Development/Early Childhood Education

Child, Youth and Family Studies/Journalism and Mass Communications

Culinary Science

Early Care and Education (age 3 to grade 3)

Earth and Space Science Education (7-12)

Elementary Education (K-6)

Elementary Education (K-6) and Deaf or Hard of Hearing Education (Pre-Professional)

Elementary Education (K-6) and Mild/Moderate Disabilities (K-6)

Elementary Education (K-6) and Early Childhood Education (Birth-K)

English Education (7-12)

English/Journalism and Mass Communications Education (7-12)

Family and Consumer Science Education (6-12)

Family Science

French Education (7-12)

German Education (7-12)

Hospitality, Restaurant and Tourism Management

Inclusive Early Childhood Education (Birth-3)

Language Arts Education (7-12)

Latin Education (7-12)

Mathematics Education (7-12)

Merchandising

Nutrition and Dietetics

Nutrition Science

Nutrition, Exercise and Health Science

Physics Education (7-12)

Russian Education (7-12)

Science Education (7-12)

Social Science Education (7-12)

Spanish Education (7-12)

Special Education–Mild/Moderate Disabilities Education (7-12) (listed under Mild/Moderate)

Speech and English Education (7-12)

Speech-Language Pathologist

Textile and Apparel Design

Textile Science

Textiles, Merchandising and Fashion Design/Communications

Theatre and English Education (7-12)

Departmental Listing

Child, Youth and Family Studies

Child Development/Early Childhood Education

Child, Youth and Family Studies/Journalism and Mass Communications

Early Care and Education (age 3 to grade 3)

Family and Consumer Science Education (6-12)

Family Science

Inclusive Early Childhood Education (Birth-3)

Nutrition and Health Sciences

Athletic Training

Culinary Science

Hospitality, Restaurant and Tourism Management

Nutrition and Dietetics

Nutrition Science

Nutrition, Exercise and Health Science

Special Education and Communication Disorders

Elementary Education (K-6) and Deaf or Hard of Hearing Education (Pre-Professional)

Elementary Education (K-6) and Mild/Moderate Disabilities Education (K-6)

Special Education–Mild/Moderate Disabilities Education (7-12)

Speech-Language Pathology

Teaching, Learning and Teacher Education

Biology Education (7-12)

Business, Marketing and Information Technology Education (6-12)

Chemistry Education (7-12)

Earth and Space Science Education (7-12)

Elementary Education (K-6)

Elementary Education (K-6) and Deaf or Hard of Hearing Education (Pre-Professional)

Elementary Education (K-6) and Mild/Moderate Disabilities (K-6)

Elementary Education (K-6) and Early Childhood Education (Birth-K)

English Education (7-12)

English/Journalism and Mass Communications Education (7-12)

French Education (7-12)

German Education (7-12)

Language Arts Education (7-12)

Latin Education (7-12)

Mathematics Education (7-12)

Physics Education (7-12)

Russian Education (7-12)

Science Education (7-12)

Social Science Education (7-12)

Spanish Education (7-12)

Speech and English Education (7-12)

Theatre and English Education (7-12)

Textiles, Clothing and Design

Merchandising

Textile and Apparel Design

Textiles Science

Textiles, Merchandising and Fashion Design/Communications

Teaching Endorsements Leading to Certification

Biology Education (7-12)

Business, Marketing and Information Technology Education (6-12)

Chemistry Education (7-12)

Early Care and Education (age 3 to grade 3)

Earth and Space Science Education (7-12)

Elementary Education (K-6)

Elementary Education (K-6) and Deaf or Hard of Hearing Education (Pre-Professional)

Elementary Education (K-6) and Mild/Moderate Disabilities (K-6)

Elementary Education (K-6) and Early Childhood Education (Birth-K)

English Education (7-12)

English/Journalism and Mass Communication Education (7-12)

Family and Consumer Science Education (6-12)

French Education (7-12)

German Education (7-12)

Inclusive Early Childhood Education (Birth-3)

Language Arts Education (7-12)

Latin Education (7-12)

Mathematics Education (7-12)

Physics Education (7-12)

Russian Education (7-12)

Science Education (7-12)

Social Science Education (7-12)

Special Education–Mild/Moderate Disabilities Education (7-12) (listed under Mild/Moderate)

Spanish Education (7-12)

Speech and English Education (7-12)

Theatre and English Education (7-12)

Engineering

DESCRIPTION

Timothy Wei, Ph.D., Dean

David Jones, Ph.D., Associate Dean for Undergraduate Programs (Lincoln Campus)

John S. Thorp, M.S., Associate Dean for Undergraduate Programs (Omaha Campus)

Role and Mission

The College of Engineering enthusiastically embraces its unique role as the singular intellectual and cultural resource for engineering instruction, research, and outreach within the state. It provides the people of Nebraska with comprehensive engineering academic programs to fulfill their highest aspirations and ambitions.

The missions of the College of Engineering at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln are:

to deliver relevant and challenging educational programs to attract an outstanding diverse student body, prepare graduates for rewarding careers in their chosen professions, and encourage graduates to extend their level of knowledge through lifelong learning;
to conduct leading edge research advances in engineering science, and stimulate the intellectual development and creativity of both students and faculty; and,
to extend exemplary engineering service and transfer knowledge that contributes to the well-being and betterment of society.

Administrative Structure

The College of Engineering is located on three campuses (Lincoln City Campus, Lincoln East Campus, and Omaha), and has two Dean’s Offices, 114 Othmer Hall in Lincoln and 100 Peter Kiewit Institute in Omaha. The College is subdivided into units, each under the leadership of a chairperson, department head, or director.

ADMISSION

College Admission

College Entrance Requirements

Students must have high school credit for (one unit is equal to one high school year):

1. 4 units of mathematics: 2 of algebra, 1 of geometry, 1 of precalculus and trigonometry.

2. 4 units of English.

3. 3 units of natural science that must include 1 unit of physics and 1 unit of chemistry (chemistry requirement waived for students in construction management).

4. 2 units of a single foreign language.

5. 3 units of social studies.

6. Students having a composite ACT score of 28 or greater (or equivalent SAT score) will be admitted to the College of Engineering even if they lack any one of the following: trigonometry, chemistry, or physics.

7. Students having an ACT score of 19 or less in English (or equivalent SAT score) must take ENGL 150 or ENGL 151.

A total of 16 units is required for admission.

Students must have an ACT (enhanced) score of 24 or greater (or equivalent SAT). Students who lack entrance requirements may be admitted based on ACT scores, high school rank and credits, or may be admitted to pre-engineering status in the Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center. Pre-engineering students are advised within the College of Engineering.

Students for whom English is not their language of nurture must meet the minimum English proficiency requirements of the University.

Students who lack entrance units may complete precollege training by Independent Study through the UNL Office of On-line and Distance Education, in summer courses, or as a part of their first or second semester course loads while in the Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center or other Colleges at UNL.

Students should consult their adviser, their department chair, or the Office of the Dean if they have questions on current policies.

Other Admission Requirements

Students who transfer to the University of Nebraska–Lincoln from other accredited colleges or universities and wish to be admitted to the College of Engineering (COE) must meet COE freshman entrance requirements and have a minimum cumulative GPA of 2.5 for Nebraska residents or 3.0 for non-residents. Students not meeting either of these requirements must enroll in the Explore Center or another UNL college until they meet COE admission requirements.

The COE accepts courses for transfer for which a C or better grade was received. Although UNL accepts D grades from the University of Nebraska at Kearney and at Omaha, not all majors in the COE accept such low grades. Students must conform to the requirements of their intended major and, in any case, are strongly encouraged to repeat courses with a grade of C- or less.

All transfer students must adopt the curricular requirements of the undergraduate bulletin current at the time of transfer to the COE—not that in use when they entered UNL. Upon admission to UNL, students wishing to pursue degree programs in the COE will be classified and subject to the policies defined in the subsequent section.

ADVISING

Academic Advising

Advisers assigned to students are either part of the Engineering Student Services located in the Engineering Library, or are in the student's major department.

Student Responsibility

Application for the Diploma

Students should access their Degree Audit via MyRed at least once each term to review degree requirements and progress toward graduation. It is the student’s responsibility to make sure their Degree Audit accurately reflects their current College and program of study.

Students are expected to develop a clear understanding of degree requirements and to plan their course of study with a College adviser. Students requiring clarification of outstanding degree requirements should visit with a College adviser promptly. Students who believe their Degree Audit has errors or omissions should visit with a College adviser promptly. It is important that you resolve these matters as soon as practicable to avoid a delay in graduation.

Each student must submit an Application for Graduation plus $25.00 check or cash fee for each degree to be received to the Office of the University Registrar by:

The last Friday in January for May graduation
The last Friday in June for August graduation
The last Friday in September for December graduation

An electronic Application for Graduation and payment is available via MyRed. Those students choosing to apply for graduation in person may visit the Office of the University Registrar, 107 Canfield Administration Building. Applications for Graduation submitted in person or by mail must be accompanied by payment. Failure to submit a timely Application for Graduation may preclude the awarding of a degree in the intended term.

ACADEMIC PROGRAMS & POLICIES

Honors Program

Honor Societies

These recognize students who excel in scholarship and give promise of being leaders in professional areas. They are branches of national societies and are generally open upon invitation to juniors and seniors: Alpha Epsilon (agricultural engineering), Chi Epsilon (civil engineering, both campuses), Eta Kappa Nu (electrical engineering), Pi Tau Sigma (mechanical engineering), Sigma Lambda Chi (construction management), Sigma Xi (scientific, all colleges), Tau Alpha Pi (engineering technology, Omaha campus), and Tau Beta Pi (all engineering).

Student Recognition

Graduation with Distinction

Students with outstanding scholastic records may obtain the special honor of graduation With Distinction, With High Distinction, or With Highest Distinction upon the recommendation of the faculty of the College. Check with your major department for specific requirements of each degree.

Student Standing/Classification/Professional Admission

Explore Center Pre-Engineering Students. These are students who aspire to enter the College of Engineering but who are not immediately admitted due to not meeting one or more admission criteria such as required high school mathematics, chemistry or physics course(s), ACT, or other qualifications. These students are admitted to the Explore Center and receive advising services from the Engineering Student Services Center. These students may enroll in ENGR 10 and 100-level engineering courses provided they meet the prerequisites on a space-available basis. Once the student has earned a 2.5 cumulative GPA in at least 12 credit hours and has removed all entrance deficiencies they will be admitted to the College of Engineering (COE).

After being admitted to the COE, students wishing to pursue degree programs in the College of Engineering will be classified as described below.

Pre-Professionally Admitted COE Students. These are students who have been admitted to the College of Engineering and are in the process of establishing their academic credentials and confirming their choice of major. Transfer students from other colleges or universities, or from the Explore Center, will be classified as pre-professionally admitted for at least one semester (12 credits) while they confirm their career path and establish their academic credentials (see Professional Admission). Most students are in pre-professionally admitted status for one to four semesters. Pre-professionally admitted students may enroll in upper level engineering courses provided they meet the prerequisites, space is available, and no departmental restrictions exist.

Professionally Admitted COE Students. These students may register in engineering courses where they meet all prerequisites or have permission. A professionally admitted student who wishes to transfer from one COE major to another must re-apply for professional admission to gain professionally admitted status in the new major, subject to the admission criteria of the new major.

Students who are enrolled in the Explore Center or in other colleges may enroll only in ENGR 10 and 100-level engineering courses. Those with greater than a 2.5 cumulative GPA may register in upper-level engineering courses, but only on a space-available basis in courses where they meet all prerequisites and have permission of the department. These students may retake an engineering course for C-, D, and F removal no more than once, on a space-available basis and with permission. They may repeat courses with a previous withdrawal (W) only once.

Professional Admission must be earned by a student in order to move from pre-professionally admitted status to professionally admitted status within the College of Engineering. Review of the student’s academic history is completed by the department of the student’s intended major after the student has completed at least 43 credit hours within his or her intended degree program. Additional review criteria are based on the individual degree program and can be found under that major’s information in the undergraduate bulletin.

A student may be reviewed up to two times for professional admission in a single major. If the student is rejected for professional admission on the second review, the student will not be allowed to continue in that major. The student may choose to pursue a new College of Engineering major, but will be subject to the review criteria of the new major. If the student is rejected for professional admission by the new major, the student will be dismissed from the College of Engineering. Further reviews for professional admission will not be allowed and the student will no longer be eligible to enroll in College of Engineering courses.

College Probation. A student who receives a cumulative grade point average (GPA) of less than a 2.4 will be placed on college probation. The student will remain on probation until a semester is completed with a cumulative GPA at or above 2.4. Any student with two sequential semesters on college probation will be dismissed from the College of Engineering.

The first semester of probation is defined as the semester in which failure to meet a cumulative or semester GPA threshold, a course failure or withdrawal, or a code of conduct violation occurs.

Completion of the following semester (12 credits) with a semester GPA above 2.4 is required for a student to be removed from the college probation. Students may be placed on college probation (or dismissed) for violation of the UNL Student Code of Conduct at any time. A student cannot graduate from the College of Engineering while on college probation.

College Dismissal. A student will be dismissed from the College of Engineering at the end of any semester in which:

The student has been on college probation for two sequential semesters
The student is dismissed by UNL

Students may also be dismissed for violating the UNL Student Code of Conduct at any time. College dismissal will cause an administrative change in the student’s matriculation to the Explore Center or to a college indicated by the student. Students who have been dismissed from the College of Engineering may be readmitted (one time only) provided they have removed all academic deficiencies that led to dismissal.

General College Policies

These policies are applicable to all students in the College of Engineering:

1. Student priority for entrance into classes for which demand exceeds available class space will be based on accumulative GPA. This priority will be applied at the end of early registration (when applicable).

2. Students may repeat a maximum of three engineering courses. Students may take any one engineering course a maximum of two times.

3. At least 30 of the last 36 credit hours needed for a degree must be registered for and completed at UNL or UNO while identified with the College of Engineering. This means that, practically speaking, the last year of a student’s work must be spent in residence. Credit earned during education abroad may be used toward degree requirements if students participate in prior approved programs and register through UNL (see http://educationabroad.unl.edu).

4. Pass/No Pass courses: Students in the College of Engineering must take ENGR 10, ENGR 20, ENGR 30, and ENGR 400 with the grading option Pass/No Pass. In addition, students may take up to 12 credit hours of courses in the humanities and social sciences on a Pass/No Pass basis. Students in the College of Engineering may not take any other required courses or technical elective courses with the grading option of Pass/No Pass.

5. Credits for “English for Foreign Students who are Non-native Speakers” at UNL and “English as a Second Language” at UNO are not applicable to degree programs in the College of Engineering.

6. Six hours of English composition may be substituted for the written communications requirement in all degree programs.

7. Students who enroll at UNL, UNO, or UNK under the academic year (Fall, Spring, Summer) of this bulletin must fulfill the requirements stated in this UNL bulletin or in any other UNL bulletin which is published while they are enrolled in the College, provided that the bulletin is no more than 10 years old at the time of graduation. A student must, however, meet the graduation requirements from one bulletin only. A student may not choose a portion from one bulletin and the remainder from another bulletin.

Undergraduate Seminars. Freshmen engineering students are required to attend ENGR 10 Freshman Engineering Seminar, a 0 credit course. The Freshman Engineering Seminar provides information on engineering disciplines, resources and tools available to students at UNL, and opportunities to meet engineering faculty members. Sophomore engineering students are required to attend ENGR 20, Sophomore Engineering Seminar, a 0 credit course. The Sophomore Engineering Seminar provides information on career planning, interviewing, resumé preparation and coop/internship opportunities. International transfer engineering students are required to attend ENGR 30 Transfer Student Engineering Seminar, a 0 credit course. The International Transfer Student Engineering Seminar focuses on transfer issues, adapting to UNL and the College of Engineering, and cultural awareness.

Design Requirement. All engineering majors require a minimum of 48 credit hours of engineering topics (engineering topics include subjects in the engineering sciences or engineering design). Engineering design is the process of devising a system, component or process to meet desired needs. Engineering design work may be done by individuals; however, team efforts are encouraged where appropriate. Engineering majors are provided an integrated engineering design experience throughout the curriculum. In addition, all engineering programs include a meaningful major design experience that builds upon the fundamental concepts of mathematics, basic sciences, humanities, social sciences, engineering topics, and communication skills.

BULLETIN TO USE

Students must fulfill the requirements stated in the bulletin for the academic year in which they are first admitted at UNL. In consultation with advisers, a student may choose to follow a subsequent bulletin for any academic year in which they are admitted to and enrolled as a degree-seeking student at UNL in the College of Engineering. Students must complete all degree requirements from a single bulletin year. The bulletin which a student follows for degree requirements may not be more than 10 years old at the time of graduation.

COLLEGE DEGREE REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Grade Appeals

In the event of a dispute involving any college policies or grades, the student should appeal to his/her instructor, and appropriate department chair or school director (in that order). If a satisfactory solution is not achieved, the student may appeal his/her case through the College Academic Appeals Committee on his/her campus.

DEGREES & MAJORS

Engineering

To meet the need for innovative engineers, the College’s programs offer broad education in the physical sciences, social sciences, mathematics, information sciences, and humanities. This education is complemented by study of engineering methods of modeling, analysis, synthesis, and design in students’ areas of specialization. In addition to preparing students for careers in engineering, the College’s bachelors degree programs provide excellent preparation for graduate study in those fields.

Construction Management

This profession is allied with architecture, engineering, and business administration. Construction managers coordinate people, machines, and materials to produce (within the constraints of budget and time) buildings, highways, bridges, dams, and other structures essential to modern society. The College’s construction management program provides a solid technical background, develops business knowledge, and considers ethical issues of the profession.

Undergraduate Programs

Engineering. The College offers bachelor of science degree programs in each of the following engineering fields: agricultural engineering, architectural engineering (Omaha campus only), biological systems engineering, chemical engineering, civil engineering, computer engineering, construction engineering, electrical engineering, electronics engineering (Omaha campus only), and mechanical engineering. Over 85 percent of all the engineering degrees granted in the United States during the last five years were granted in these fields. Students with interests in specialty fields such as aerospace, environmental, or biomedical engineering should seek advice in the Office of the Dean on how to incorporate such emphases into the above degree programs.

Construction Management. The College offers the bachelor of science degree program in construction management, a program accredited by The American Council for Construction Education.

Double Majors. Students can major in two departments in the college by consulting their advisers (one from each department) and completing all the requirements for the departmental majors.

MINORS & AREAS OF SPECIALIZATIONS OFFERED

Approved Minors for College of Engineering Students

Policies:

1. A minor will not reduce or alter the existing course or degree requirements for students electing to pursue a minor.

2. A student’s minor program(s) must be organized and approved by an adviser prior to the submission of the senior check to the department chair or head.

3. The minor(s) must be approved by the Dean and the cognizant program offering the minor(s).

4. The College of Engineering will follow the “A/B” format of the Arts and Sciences College in which a student pursuing a single minor must complete the “A” requirements. A student pursuing a double (or greater) minor must fulfill either the “A” or “B” requirements for both minors depending on which plan is offered by the cognizant department.

5. Minors on the Lincoln or Omaha campuses may be added to the following list on approval of the College of Engineering Curriculum Committee and faculty.

Approved Minors

If not otherwise listed here, refer to the individual college sections for requirements on the following minors.

Agricultural Economics

Agricultural Leadership, Education and Communication

Agriculture and Natural Resources

Agronomy

Animal Science

Art History

Biochemistry

Biological Sciences

Biomedical Engineering Minor

Business Minor for Jeffrey S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management (Plan A only)

This minor is applicable only to students participating in the Jeffrey S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management. All courses must be taken for a letter grade.

Chemistry

NOTE: Chemical Engineering students cannot earn this minor.

Communication Studies

NOTE: Engineering students may not use internship credit to satisfy this minor.

Computational Biology and Bioinformatics

Computer Science

Refer to the College of Arts and Sciences for the computer science minor.

Construction Management (Plan A only)

All courses must be taken for a letter grade.

Economics

Energy Science

For information about the energy science minor, please contact Professor Adam Liska, 402-472-8744, aliska2@unl.edu..

Engineering Mechanics (Plan A only)

English

Ethnic Studies

General Business (Plan A only)

All courses must be taken for a letter grade.

Required Courses 18

ACCT 200 3

ECON 200 3

FINA 300 3

MRKT 300 3

MNGT 300 3

BLAW 300 3

Note: No more than one course may be transferred from another institution into the General Business minor.

Geography

Geology

Global Studies

History

International Agriculture and Natural Resources

International Engineering

Japanese

Mathematics and Statistics (Plan A only)

Meteorology-Climatology

Modern Languages (Only for engineering students)

Czech

French, German and Russian

Japanese

Spanish

Music

Philosophy

Physics

Political Science

Psychology

Robotics Engineering

Sociology

Water Science

Women’s and Gender Studies

GRADUATE STUDENT INFORMATION

Courses supporting several engineering graduate programs are offered both on and off campus. For details, see the University of Nebraska–Lincoln Graduate Studies Bulletin and contact the appropriate department or the Office of the Dean of the College of Engineering.

Seniors in this University who have obtained prior approval of the Dean of Graduate Studies may receive up to 12 hours credit for graduate courses taken in addition to their required undergraduate work. However, these credits must be earned within the calendar year prior to receipt of the bachelors degree. For procedures, inquire at the UNL Graduate Studies Office. Graduate credits earned prior to receipt of the bachelors degree may not always be accepted for transfer to other institutions as graduate work.

OTHER

Professional Licensure

The College encourages professional licensure. The majority of the College’s engineering seniors take the Fundamentals of Engineering (FE) examination prior to graduation. This examination is administered by the Nebraska Board of Engineers and Architects, a state agency, and the first step in the process of becoming a licensed professional engineer. To become a licensed professional engineer, one must pass the FE exam, have four years of experience, and pass a professional practice examination. Students may take the FE exam in the last semester of their baccalaureate program.

Accreditation

The agricultural engineering, biological systems engineering, chemical engineering, civil engineering (Lincoln and Omaha campuses), computer engineering (Lincoln and Omaha campus), electrical engineering, electronics engineering, and mechanical engineering programs are accredited by the Engineering Accreditation Commission of the Accreditation Board for Engineering and Technology (ABET), http://www.abet.org.

The master of architectural engineering is also accredited by the Engineering Accreditation Commission of the Accreditation Board for Engineering and Technology (ABET), http://www.abet.org.

The construction management program is accredited by the American Council for Construction Education.

Practical Training

For a student who anticipates pursuing a career as a practicing engineer, it is strongly recommended that the student engage in an internship or equivalent practical training experience.

Scholarships and Financial Aid

Each year the College awards scholarships to freshmen and upperclassmen worth more than $750,000. Scholarship awards are made possible through generous gifts of alumni and friends, local and national organizations, and through funding by the Nebraska Legislature. Contact the Office of the Dean or the Office of Scholarships and Financial Aid for information regarding these awards and for other financial assistance.

Application for UNL freshmen scholarships automatically makes you eligible for College of Engineering scholarships as well as other university awards such as the Regents and David scholarships. You must submit the UNL Application form (due January 15, prior to the beginning of the next academic year) to be eligible.

A significant number of entering students have academic records that qualify them for university-wide scholarship awards. Each year about 25 percent of the freshman Regent Scholarship recipients are engineering students.

A large number of students are able to find part-time employment in fields related to their interests.

Student Organizations in the College

Technical Societies

The technical student societies help develop a greater personal and professional interest and understanding in engineering, computer science and construction management. Student branches of the major national technical and scientific societies are sponsored by the academic programs and departments.

Lincoln Campus. American Institute of Chemical Engineers; The Society for Engineering in Agricultural, Food, and Biological Systems; American Society of Civil Engineers; American Society of Mechanical Engineers; Associated General Contractors; Association for Computer Machinery; Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineers; American Society for Metals; Student Advisory Board; Institute of Transportation Engineers; National Society of Black Engineers; Society of American Military Engineers; Society of Women Engineers; and Society of Automotive Engineers.

Lifelong Learning

The education of professionals in construction management and engineering is a continuing process. The groundwork in both technical and nontechnical studies is laid while in college, but education continues after graduation. For a professional, education will continue not only in the technical areas but in areas that relate to human and social concerns. A professional may expect to take a leadership role in the community and must have a broad awareness of human and social accomplishments, needs, values, and a willingness to take the responsibility for meeting these needs. For these reasons, an integrated program of course work in the humanities and social sciences is a part of the educational requirements.

Exploratory & Pre-Professional Advising Center

DESCRIPTION

127 Love (Library) South

402-472-3605

http://explorecenter.unl.edu

The Exploratory and Pre-Professional Advising Center (Explore Center) provides an academic home for students who have not decided upon a major or who are transitioning between majors. The Center also provides advising for students interested in pre-professional (pre-health and pre-law) programs. The Center does not award degrees.

ADVISING

Professional academic advisers in the Explore Center are available on an appointment and/or walk-in basis Monday through Friday in 127 Love (Library) South and can be reached at 402-472-3605 or explorecenter@unl.edu. Academic advising appointments can also be scheduled through the MyPLAN tab in Blackgoard.  Undeclared, pre-health, and pre-law students who have not yet chosen a major are assigned to an Explore Center academic adviser and may view their adviser assignment in MyRED through the Student Center. Students may receive advising from their assigned adviser or any other adviser in the center.

Undeclared Students

Professional academic advisers in the Explore Center engage undeclared students in major exploration, degree planning, and academic course work selection processes. By working closely with all of the UNL colleges, Explore Center advisers help students design a general academic plan for one or more semesters that will allow them to progress toward a degree, while also exploring the variety of opportunities offered by the University. Undeclared students are encouraged to meet with a professional academic adviser in the Explore Center early in their first semester at UNL to discuss interest areas and to develop a plan for major exploration. It is recommended undeclared students continue to meet with an Explore Center adviser once a semester and attend Explore Center workshops until they declare a major.  Additional information concerning major exploration can be found on the Explore Center (http://explorecenter.unl.edu) and Career Services (http://unl.edu/careers/explore) websites.

Pre-Health and Pre-Law Students

Professional academic advisers in the Explore Center provide academic advising for students interested in pursuing professional health and law degrees after completion of their undergraduate course work at UNL. Pre-health and pre-law areas of study are not majors at UNL but rather advising categories. Students may select any academic major while pursuing pre-health or pre-law areas of study and will be advised on degree requirements for graduation from UNL by their college/major adviser.  Students are advised in their pre-health and pre-law areas through the Explore Center. Pre-professional advising includes career exploration, course planning, extracurricular activity and involvement planning, entrance exam preparation, and application consultation. Students can receive specific advising in the following pre-health areas of interest: pre-chiropractic, pre-clinical laboratory science, pre-clinical perfusion, pre-cytotechnology, pre-dental hygiene, pre-dentistry, pre-law, pre-medicine, pre-mortuary science, pre-nursing, pre-occupational therapy, pre-optometry, pre-pharmacy, pre-physical therapy, pre-physician assistant, and pre-radiation science technology. Students who do not know which career path they might pursue are encouraged to explore the many options available by using the http://ExploreHealthCareers.org website in addition to the Career Services and Explore Center websites and resources.

ACE REQUIREMENTS

Consistent with the mission and values of the University, Achievement-Centered Education (ACE) is based on a shared set of four institutional objectives and 10 student learning outcomes. The ACE program was approved by faculty in all eight undergraduate colleges and endorsed by the Faculty Senate, the student government, and the Academic Planning Committee in January 2008 for implementation in the fall 2009. ACE aligns with current national initiatives in general education.

Key characteristics of ACE demonstrate the benefits of the program to students:

Students receive a broad education with exposure to multiple disciplines, critical life skills and important reasoning, inquiry, and civic capacities.
ACE is simple and transparent for students, faculty and advisers. Students complete the equivalent of 3 credit hours for each of the ten student learning outcomes.
Students connect and integrate their ACE experiences with their selected major.
Students can transfer all ACE certified courses across colleges within the institution to meet the ACE requirement and any course from outside the institution that is directly equivalent to a UNL ACE-certified course. Courses from outside institutions without direct equivalents may be considered with appropriate documentation for ACE credit (see academic adviser).

ACE allows faculty to assess and improve their effectiveness and facilitate students’ learning.

ACE Institutional Objectives and Student Learning Outcomes

To meet the ACE program requirement, a student will complete the equivalent of 3 credit hours for each of the ten ACE Student Learning Outcomes (a total of 30 ACE credit hours). See the ACE website at: http://ace.unl.edu for the most current information and the most recently certified courses.  Students should meet with an Explore Center adviser to discuss the planning and completion of ACE courses and requirements.

Fine & Performing Arts

DESCRIPTION

The Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts is comprised of the Department of Art and Art History, the Glenn Korff School of Music including the Dance Division, the Johnny Carson School of Theatre and Film, and the Mary Riepma Ross Media Arts Center. In addition, the Great Plains Art Museum, the Lied Center for the Performing Arts, and the Sheldon Museum of Art are affiliated with the College.

The College offers a wide range of degrees: the bachelor of arts, the bachelor of fine arts, the bachelor of music, and the bachelor of music education. The programs in the College provide students with both a general liberal education, as well as specialized training in their chosen field. Many of the degrees offered by the College are professionally oriented, and prepare students to enter an occupation directly or to attend graduate or professional schools. Students may major in art, art history, music, music education, theatre arts, or dance.
Each of the academic units in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts is accredited by the national accrediting organization in the field: the National Association of Schools of Art and Design, the National Association of Schools of Dance, the National Association of Schools of Music, and the National Association of Schools of Theatre.

The Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts is committed to facilitating the interaction between the many arts entities on campus, and to providing students with a high quality education and many opportunities to participate in cultural activities.

Mission

The College nurtures creative, artistic activity and scholarship; educates students to a high level of accomplishment as artists, teachers, and scholars; and enriches the education of all students through the study and practice of the arts. The College provides the citizens of Nebraska with opportunities to enjoy, appreciate, and participate in the arts through outreach programs. Through its creative activity, research, and exhibitions it contributes to the arts nationally and internationally. In fulfillment of its mission, the College:

provides comprehensive educational programs of study in the arts at the undergraduate and graduate levels.

fosters creative activity and scholarly research in the arts.

provides professional preparation for artists, historians, theorists, and arts educators.

sustains a strong commitment to liberal education for all UNL students through its course offerings and special programs.

provides opportunities for the performance, collection, preservation, publication, and exhibition of important works.

develops supportive and knowledgeable audiences and patrons for the arts.

maintains a strong interdisciplinary and continuing education emphasis by creating comprehensive cultural and educational opportunities.

supports and contributes to collaborative multicultural and intercultural programs.

serves the entire state and region as an important artistic and cultural resource through its exhibitions, performances, and educational outreach programs.

provides leadership for the understanding and development of the arts in the state and nation.

ADMISSION

College Admission

Requirements for admission to the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts are consistent with general University admission requirements. These include:

English (4 units)
Mathematics (4 units)
Social studies (3 units)
Natural sciences (3 units) and
Foreign language (2 units)

NOTE: One unit equals one year of high school credit.

One of the following performance standards must also be met: test score.

New Freshmen: Minimum ACT 20 (composite) or minimum SAT 950 (combined)

Transfer and Readmit Students: Completed twelve or more semester credits from a postsecondary institution with a minimum cumulative GPA 2.0 and GPA 2.0 during the last semester of record at the time of application. (Theatre majors with an emphasis in Film and New Media: minimum cumulative GPA 3.0 and GPA 3.0 during the last semester of record at the time of application.)

International Students: Minimum TOEFL 70 (Internet) or 523 (paper)

Individual departments may have higher standards for acceptance into the different degrees and emphases. Please check with the individual departments for these standards.

Auditions are required for admission to the Glenn Korff School of Music for music and dance majors and minors. Auditions are also required for admission to the Johnny Carson School of Theatre and Film for the BA Performance Emphasis. A separate application and portfolio review are required for acceptance into the BFA Film and New Media Emphasis, and the BA Directing and Management Emphasis.

Admission Deficiencies/Removal of Deficiencies

Students who are admitted through the Admission by Review process with core course deficiencies will have certain conditions attached to their enrollment at UNL. These conditions are in this bulletin under “Removal of Deficiencies.”

Students with one deficiency, two deficiencies but not in the same category, or two deficiencies in foreign language who receive a Deferred Admission or Admission by Review, may be considered for admission to the college. Students who are admitted through the Admission by Review process with core course deficiencies will have certain conditions attached to their enrollment at UNL. These conditions are explained under Admission to the University, Removal of Deficiencies in this bulletin.

ADVISING

Academic Advising

Primary academic advising for students in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts is provided by the student’s home department or school. A faculty adviser is assigned by the department or school to help students plan their academic careers and select appropriate courses. Incoming freshmen are counseled during New Student Enrollment by specially trained advisers. Students are responsible for meeting with their academic advisers on a regular basis so that timely and appropriate counsel can be received. Students should contact their department or school office for more information on advising policies and procedures. The Dean’s Office is also available upon referral, but the department or school is the principal source for advising information.

Students wishing to include credits transferred from another institution in their program of study must submit a transcript to the UNL Office of Admissions. The Dean’s Office will complete an evaluation of transfer credit upon receipt of Courses Presented for Transfer from the Office of Admissions. Students who have previously had transfer credits evaluated in another UNL college must have the credits reevaluated upon entering the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts.

The applicability of transfer credits toward major requirements is determined by the department or school offering the major. Students who wish to apply transfer credits toward major requirements or who wish to request any waiver or substitution of requirements must complete a Request for Waiver or Substitution form. The Request for Waiver or Substitution must first be approved by the appropriate Chief Adviser (listed below) and department chair, before being forwarded to the Dean’s Office for final approval. Requests for waiver or substitution involving courses not offered by the student’s home department or school must have the approval (on the Request for Waiver or Substitution form) of the appropriate UNL department.

Art and Art History: Christy Aggens, 120 Richards Hall

Dance: Susan Levine Ourada, 208 Mabel Lee Hall

Music: Jacqueline Mattingly, 351 Westbrook

Music Education: Robert Woody, 354 Westbrook

Theatre Arts (BFA): Janice Stauffer, 10 Temple

Theatre Arts (BA): Harris Smith, 213 Temple

ACADEMIC PROGRAMS & POLICIES

Academic Load

Full-time status is attained by registering for twelve or more credits each semester. The Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts allows a maximum of 20 credits per semester.

Course Exclusions and Restrictions

No credit for graduation is allowed for any course deemed to be high school-level (MATH 100A Intermediate Algebra, driver training education, etc.) or transfer credit from an institution with the primary purpose of vocational training (automotive repair, respiratory therapy, etc.).

The current Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts policy regarding elective credit in ROTC and activity or athletics practice courses in nutrition and health sciences, College of Education and Human Sciences is:

1. Students majoring in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts may count no more than 10 hours credit in military science, naval science or aerospace studies courses toward their degree. Credit for courses taken beyond this limit will not count toward the credit hour requirements for a degree from the College. This restriction does not apply to courses cross listed between military science, naval science or aerospace studies and departments of the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts.

2. Students majoring in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts may count no more than 4 hours credit (1 credit hour per semester) in activity or athletic practice courses, and/or basic military training toward their degree. Additional activity, athletic practice and basic military training courses may be taken, but the credit earned will not count toward a degree from the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts.

3. A maximum total of 10 hours credit in activity, athletic practice, and basic military training courses and military science, naval science, or aerospace studies courses combined can be counted toward a degree in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts. This restriction does not apply to courses cross-listed between military science, naval science, or aerospace studies and departments of the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts.

Credit Rules

Credit by Examination

Through study or experience that parallels a University of Nebraska–Lincoln course, a regularly enrolled University student may feel prepared to pass an examination on the course content of a specific course for credit in that course. To apply for credit, a student should:

1. Consult with the Department Chair.

2. Obtain a Credit by Examination Form at the Registrar's Office, 107 Canfield Administration Building, 402-472-3649. Current enrollment in the University must also be verified.

3. Secure the approval signature from the Department Chair, instructor, and the Dean of the student’s college.

4. Secure the bursar’s receipt for payment of the appropriate fee per course for Credit by Examination. Currently, the fee is one-half the resident tuition rate.

5. Present the completed form to the instructor designated by the Department Chair. The instructor will give the examination and report the results on the Credit by Examination Form to the Registrar's Office, 107 Canfield Administration Building, 402-472-3636.

Examination for credit through UNL departments may be taken only by currently enrolled students. A student is not permitted to receive Credit by Examination in a course which is a prerequisite for a course already taken unless the course and its prerequisites cover essentially different subject matter.

The Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts also gives credit for the subject and general examinations of the College Level Examination Program and the Advanced Placement Program administered by the College Entrance Examination Board. See the Dean’s Office, 102 Woods Art Building, for current policy regarding CLEP and AP examinations.

Dual Degrees/Inter College Majors

Dual Degrees

Students who wish to pursue two degrees at UNL must declare the additional degree on a Dual Matriculation form approved by both colleges involved. Generally, 30 credit hours will be added to the minimum number of credits needed to complete the secondary degree. Students in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts are allowed to declare two degrees within the college, provided that the degrees are different. Two degrees (diplomas) are awarded upon completion.

Inter-College Majors

A student in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts pursuing a bachelor of arts degree may also complete a second bachelor of arts major in the College of Arts and Sciences. Likewise, a student in the College of Arts and Sciences pursuing a bachelor of arts degree may also complete a second bachelor of arts major in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts. The student must complete all degree requirements in the degree college in addition to the course work for the second major in the visiting college. One degree (diploma) will be awarded upon completion.

Honors Program

The Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts encourages qualified students to participate in the University Honors Program. As far as their plans and programs permit, these students are enrolled in the special sections for superior students. In addition, departments in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts offer special honors sections of regular freshman courses to meet the needs of students with superior preparation in those subjects.

Student Recognition

Dean’s List

The College recognizes students for academic achievement during the fall and spring semesters by placement on the College Dean’s List. To qualify for the Dean’s List in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts, students must complete 12 graded hours by the time of the first grade reports and attain a minimum semester grade point average of 3.7. The following do not qualify as part of the 12 credit hours: Pass/No Pass credit, transfer hours, removals of incompletes, and grade changes submitted after the census grade reports. Music education students are not eligible for the Dean’s List during the semester in which they are enrolled in MUED 497 (Student Teaching).

Degrees with Distinction

In recognition of outstanding academic excellence, the College grants the bachelors degree with the designation of With Distinction, With High Distinction, and With Highest Distinction to qualified students. The College Academic Distinction and Awards Committee determines the level of distinction. To be recommended for distinction, candidates must fulfill the specific criteria for Highest Distinction, With High Distinction, or Distinction, as described below, in addition to all of the general criteria and procedures applicable to all distinction classifications.

Highest Distinction. Candidates for the bachelors degree may be awarded Highest Distinction on the basis of the following criteria: outstanding scholastic standing (a cumulative GPA above 3.9 as of the semester preceding graduation) and a thesis project of high quality.

High Distinction. Candidates for the bachelors degree may be awarded High Distinction by fulfilling one of two sets of criteria: 1) by achieving outstanding scholastic standing (a cumulative GPA above 3.9 as of the semester preceding graduation), or 2) by achieving excellent scholastic standing (a cumulative GPA above 3.8 as of the semester preceding graduation) and a thesis project of high quality.

Distinction. Candidates for the bachelors degree may be awarded Distinction by achieving one of two sets of criteria: 1) by excellent scholastic standing (a cumulative GPA above 3.8 as of the semester preceding graduation), or 2) by achieving high scholastic standing (a cumulative GPA of 3.5 as of the semester preceding graduation) and a thesis project of high quality.

The following criteria apply to all categories: an award of distinction on the basis of GPA alone (for Distinction or High Distinction) should not be considered automatic. In reviewing candidates, a consideration of the GPA is followed by an evaluation of the transcript, which includes: the general quality and breadth of the program, the quality of any transfer credit hours, the number of 300/400-level courses, the number of courses taken Pass/No Pass, and the number of courses retaken to remove D grades. Students must remove any incompletes by the end of the 8th week of classes in the term preceding graduation in order to be considered for recognition. In addition, ordinarily only students who have taken their last 48 hours of graded course work while registered in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts are considered. Consequently, it is possible for a student to have a GPA above the cut-off point and still not receive a recommendation for distinction. Also, graduation with any level of distinction is not automatic with the submission of a thesis project (a requirement for a degree with Highest Distinction, and an option for degrees with High Distinction or with Distinction). It does, however, make a student eligible to be considered for graduation with such honors.

Thesis Project. The thesis project should be substantially more extensive than a term paper. It must be the result of independent, sustained thought, and intellectual curiosity, and it must be completed outside of the structured assignments normally required for a course (excluding 499H courses). A survey of the literature about a particular topic is not sufficient. The project must include a significant written component. All of the following elements are required: 1) an abstract consisting of no more than one page; 2) a clear formulation of the problem, question, or project; 3) a scholarly study which illuminates it, and 4) a substantive conclusion supported by evidence. Students must write in a manner and style that can be understood by a non-specialist in the field. A bibliography and reference to existing literature in the field should be included where appropriate. The phrase “Thesis Project” acknowledges the possibility of having a scholarly honors endeavor which might not conform to the narrow definition of a “thesis”. The following are examples of previous Thesis Projects: 1) the arrangement of a particular symphony and a detailed description of the process of composing arrangements with literary references, 2) the creation of a portfolio of photographic works accompanied by a lengthy historical and literary background, 3) a complete set of costume designs with detailed information about the design, research and garment building process and photographs of the realized costumes. The project must have a significant written component, but it need not be in the format of a formal thesis.

Procedure: Students who elect to work on a thesis project must make arrangements before their senior year by consulting with a faculty member who will supervise the project. The student must register for an independent study course in their major area of study (499H) before proceeding with the preparation of the independent work. The Thesis Project Registration must be completed, with signatures, and filed in the Dean’s Office (102 Woods Art Building) by Tuesday of the second week of classes of the semester of graduation. The Thesis Project supervisor is expected to offer guidance to the student throughout the duration of the project. Two faculty members, the supervisor and the second reader, must complete a Thesis Project Evaluation Form. It is the responsibility of the faculty members to clearly address in their evaluations the extent to which the thesis project meets the three required elements listed above. Thesis projects and faculty evaluations must be submitted to the departmental unit head by the end of the 4th week of the semester of graduation. The unit heads signal departmental approval by forwarding the thesis project and faculty evaluations to the associate dean. Thesis projects not meeting the approval of the department will not be sent forward to the Dean’s Office for further consideration. The College Academic Distinction and Awards Committee conducts the final evaluation of the thesis project. Specific deadlines for each term are indicated on the Registration and Evaluation forms. Materials submitted after the stated deadlines will not be considered by the Academic Distinction and Awards Committee.

In general, every thesis project is reviewed by the Committee. However, if no member of the Committee feels qualified in the subject area of the thesis project submitted, the Committee solicits the help of another faculty member with an appropriate background. This outside reader then submits to the Committee a formal written evaluation. Even so, members of the Committee must depend heavily on the faculty evaluations.

Students in the UNL Honors Program may submit an Honors Thesis, providing all of the above requirements and deadlines are met.

Students graduating in August must meet deadlines set for May graduates.

Dean’s Award for Academic Excellence

This award is presented annually in the spring to the graduating student from the three graduations (May, August, and December) of the previous calendar year who has achieved the highest level of scholastic performance while in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts. The award is based on the final cumulative grade point average at graduation. In the event of a tie, other factors will be taken into consideration. It is expected that the last 48 hours of the student’s work will have been completed in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts.

International Study/Education Abroad

Credit earned during education abroad may be used toward degree requirements if students participate in prior approved programs and register through UNL. Credit awarded from an institution other than UNL will be subject to transfer credit and residency rules.

Senior Check/Degree Audit

In the term after which a student has completed 85 hours, Graduation Services in the Office of the University Registrar, 109 Canfield Administration Building, will perform a “senior check.” Students will receive notification about the requirements that still need to be fulfilled in their declared degree program. Questions about remaining requirements should be directed to the chief adviser for the major.

Student Standing/Classification

Sophomore Standing. For admission to sophomore standing a student must have completed all of the College entrance requirements; earned a minimum of 27 semester hours of credit; and attained a total grade point average of at least 2.0.

Junior Standing. A student has junior standing after meeting the requirements for sophomore standing and completing 53 semester hours of credit.

Senior Standing. A student has senior standing after meeting the requirements for junior standing and completing 89 semester hours of credit.

Substitutions and Waivers

Special requests concerning degree programs, including inquiries about exceptions to degree requirements, waivers, and substitutions should be made to the Dean’s Office, 102 Woods Art Building.

ACE REQUIREMENTS

All students must fulfill the Achievement Centered Education (ACE) requirements. Information about the ACE program may be viewed at ace.unl.edu.

BULLETIN TO USE

Students who first enroll at Nebraska under the 2014-2015 Undergraduate Bulletin must fulfill the requirements stated in this bulletin or in any other bulletin which is published while they are enrolled in the College provided the bulletin they follow is no more than ten years old at the time of graduation. A student must, however, meet the requirements from one bulletin only rather than choosing a portion from one bulletin and the remainder from another.

Exception: Students pursuing any degree in the Glenn Korff School of Music who fail to take at least one course that will fulfill their degree requirements during a 12-month period must apply for re-admission. They are then required to move to the new bulletin and fulfill the requirements in effect at the time of readmission.

COLLEGE DEGREE REQUIREMENTS

College General Education Requirements

Introduction to Library Research (1 cr)

All students will complete LIBR 110, a one-credit hour class designed to teach basic information literacy skills to first year and transfer students. The course familiarizes students with an array of online information resources and introduces them to specific UNL Libraries services and resources.

Students who have 27 or more transfer credits applied toward degree requirements are exempt from the LIBR 110 requirement.

Foreign Languages/Language Requirement

The languages requirement serves to help students gain a working familiarity with a language and a culture other than their own.

All students pursuing bachelor of arts or bachelor of music degrees are required to complete the intermediate level in one foreign language. Some or all of these courses may be completed while in high school. Courses approved to satisfy the languages requirement are offered by the Department of Classics and Religious Studies and the Department of Modern Languages and Literatures in the College of Arts and Sciences, and the Department of Speech-Language Pathology and Audiology in the College of Education and Human Sciences. A student is required to successfully complete 202 to fulfill the languages requirement. (Exceptions: In Japanese, a student must complete JAPN 201 and one additional course from JAPN 202, JAPN 203, and JAPN 204; In Greek, the student must complete two 300-level courses; in Latin, a student must take LATN 301 and LATN 302.) Instruction is currently available in Arabic, Chinese, Czech, French, German, Greek, Hebrew, Japanese, Latin, Omaha Native Language, Russian, Spanish, and American Sign Language.

NOTE:

A student who has completed three years of one foreign language study in high school may fulfill the languages requirement by taking a fourth-semester-level course.
A student who has completed the fourth-year level of one foreign language in high school is exempt from the languages requirement.
Any student who achieves a specified scaled score in the College Level Examination Program (CLEP) subject exam in French, German, and Spanish, levels 1 and 2, will be exempt from the languages requirement and will also receive credit for the fourth semester course in the language.
A transfer student with 11 or 12 semester hours of accepted credit has two choices: 1) to complete 6 hours in the same language at the 200 level; or 2) with permission of the chair of the department to enroll in a fourth semester course.
A student from a foreign country who has demonstrated acceptable proficiency in his or her native language (other than English) is exempted from the languages requirement without credit toward the degree. American students who present acceptable evidence that their second language is English are exempted from the languages requirement without credit toward the degree. All such students should see the Dean’s Office, 102 Woods Art Building, for this exemption.

Approved Courses

ANTH 204A Native Language: Omaha III (ETHN 204A) (3 cr)

ANTH 205A Native Language: Omaha IV (ETHN 205A) (3 cr)

ARAB 201 Second-Year Arabic I (3 cr)

ARAB 202 Second-Year Arabic II (3 cr)

CHIN 201 Second-Year Chinese I (3 cr)

CHIN 202 Second-Year Chinese II (3 cr)

CZEC 201 Second-Year Czech I (3 cr)

CZEC 202 Second-Year Czech II (3 cr)

FREN 201 Second-Year French I (3 cr)

FREN 202 Second-Year French II (3 cr)

FREN 203 Conversation & Composition I (3 cr)

FREN 210 Accelerated Second-Year French (6 cr)

GERM 201 Second-Year German I (3 cr)

GERM 202 Second-Year German II (3 cr)

GERM 203 Composition & Conversation I (3 cr)

GERM 210 Accelerated Second-Year German (6 cr)

GREK 301 Greek Prose I (3 cr)

GREK 302 Greek Poetry I (3 cr)

GREK 373 New Testament Greek (3 cr)

HEBR 301 Biblical Hebrew Prose (3 cr)

HEBR 302 Biblical Hebrew Poetry (3 cr)

JAPN 201 Second-Year Japanese I (3 cr)

JAPN 202 Intermediate Grammar & Reading I (3 cr)

JAPN 203 Second-Year Japanese II (3 cr)

JAPN 204 Intermediate Grammar & Reading II (3 cr)

LATN 301 Latin Prose I (3 cr)

LATN 302 Latin Poetry I (3 cr)

RUSS 201 Second-Year Russian I (3 cr)

RUSS 202 Second-Year Russian II (3 cr)

SLPA 201 Second Year American Sign Language I (4 cr)

SLPA 202 Second Year American Sign Language II (4 cr)

SPAN 201 Second-Year Spanish I (3 cr)

SPAN 202 Second-Year Spanish II (3 cr)

SPAN 203 Intensive Conversation (3 cr)

SPAN 210 Accelerated Second-Year Spanish (6 cr)

Minimum Hours Required for Graduation

A minimum of 120 semester hours of credit is required for graduation from the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts. Students in the College are required to maintain a minimum current and cumulative GPA of 2.0. Individual departments may require a higher current and cumulative GPA.

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

The College will accept no more than 15 semester hours of grades lower than C from schools outside of the University of Nebraska system.

Grades lower than C earned at UNL or transferred from other schools cannot be applied toward requirements in a major, but may be applied toward total hours.

Pass/No Pass Limits

University regulations for the Pass/No Pass privilege state: The Pass/No Pass option is designed to be used by a student seeking to expand his/her intellectual horizons by taking courses in areas where he/she may have minimum preparation without adversely affecting his/her grade point average.

1. Neither the P nor the N grade contribute to a student’s GPA

2. P is interpreted to mean C or above. Some professional education courses require a C+ or above.

3. A change to or from Pass/No Pass may be made until mid-term (1/2 of the course.) This date coincides with the final date to drop a course without the instructor’s approval.

4. The Pass/No Pass or grade registration cannot conflict with the professor’s, department’s, college, or University policy governing grading option.

5. Prior to the mid-term deadline, changing to or from the Pass/No Pass requires using the MyRED system to change the grading option or filing a Drop/Add form with the Office of the University Registrar, 107 Canfield Administration Building. After the mid-term deadline, a student registered for Pass/No Pass cannot change to a grade registration unless the Pass/No Pass registration is in conflict with a professor’s, department’s, college, or University policy governing Pass/No Pass.

6. The Pass/No Pass grading option cannot be used for the removal of C- or D or F grades.

Pass/no pass privileges in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts are extended to students according to the following additional regulations:

1. Pass/no pass hours can count toward fulfillment of ACE requirements up to the 24-hour maximum.

2. Freshmen and sophomores may enroll for no more than 6 hours of Pass/No Pass work per semester.

3. Students may not elect to take courses on a Pass/No Pass basis to fulfill degree requirements in the major. Departments may allow up to 6 hours of Pass/No Pass to be taken in the minor offered by the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts.

4. Departments may specify that certain courses can be taken only on a Pass/No Pass basis.

5. The College will permit no more than a total of 24 semester hours of Pass/No Pass grades to be applied toward degree requirements. This total includes all “pass” grades earned at UNL and other schools.

Individual departments vary in their policies regarding Pass/No Pass hours as applied to the major and minor. Consult the individual departmental listings for these policies. Students who wish to apply Pass/No Pass hours to their major and minor(s) must obtain approval on a form that is available in the Dean’s Office, 102 Woods Art Building.

GPA Requirements

Students are expected to maintain a minimum 2.0 grade point average each semester. Some programs within the College may have higher GPA requirements to keep in good academic standing.

Transfer Credit Rules

Ordinarily, hours earned at an accredited college are accepted by the University. The College, however, will evaluate all hours submitted on an application for transfer and reserves the right to accept or reject any of them. The maximum number of hours the University will accept on transfer from a two-year college is 60.

Normally credit is not given for pre-university work. In some instances, however, it may be possible to receive credit through satisfactory examination.

All transfer students must complete the Residency Requirement (see “Residency Requirement”), and at least 9 hours in the major field must be completed at the University regardless of the number of hours transferred.

The Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts will accept no more than 15 semester hours of D grades from schools other than UNO or UNK. All grades may be transferred from UNO or UNK. However, transfer courses within a student’s major or minor will be evaluated by that unit and held to the same minimum grade standards as courses taken at UNL.

Department of Art and Art History Transfer Credit Policy

A studio art or art history course presented for possible transfer to UNL is evaluated by the Department of Art and Art History using course descriptions and/or course syllabi to evaluate content, and course schedules to evaluate the hours of instruction.

Studio art courses that are eligible for transfer credit based on course content are awarded one credit hour for every 30 hours of instruction (with the assumption that the transfer course required 15 hours of work outside of class for every 30 hours spent in class with the instructor.) Credit is rounded to the nearest half-credit hour. If a course is presented for possible transfer, and the hours of instruction fall short of UNL’s NASAD-based standards, the course will receive a proportional reduction in credit.

BFA – At least 36 credit hours in studio art and 9 credit hours in art history of the required BFA courses must be taken at UNL. Courses taken at other academic institutions may be substituted for the remaining required courses subject to evaluation by the department.

BA in Studio Art – At least 12 credit hours in studio art and 9 credit hours in art history of the required BA courses must be taken at UNL. Courses taken at other academic institutions may be substituted for the remaining required courses subject to evaluation by the department.

BA in Art History – At least 18 credit hours of the required art history courses must be taken at UNL. Courses taken at other academic institutions may be substituted for the remaining required courses subject to evaluation by the department.

Glenn Korff School of Music Transfer Credit Policy

The following will be used by advisers as guidelines for the evaluation of transfer credits which are less than five years old:

If a transfer student has successfully completed (grade C or above) approved transfer credits which are equivalent to music major/minor requirements in terms of number of credit hours and scope of content, that area will be considered completed at the discretion of the chief degree program adviser.
For approved transfer credits which are lacking equivalency in either number of credit hours, scope of content, or grade received to music major/minor requirements in applied music, music theory, sight singing/aural skills, and keyboard skills, the number of transfer credits accepted and placement will be determined by audition/proficiency tests administered by designated area faculty.
For approved transfer credits which are lacking equivalency in other music areas (history and ensembles), the number of transfer credits accepted will be determined by the chief degree program adviser.

All music course work which is more than five years old must be validated by an audition or competency examination given by designated area faculty.

Johnny Carson School of Theatre and Film Transfer Credit Policy

There are no additional restrictions regarding transfer credit.

Transfer Credit from Foreign Institutions

Credit for courses taken at foreign universities and colleges will be transferred only after validation by the appropriate department. This evaluation may include examination of the student over subject matter studied at the foreign institution.

International Baccalaureate Credit

Students who have studied art, music, or theatre within the International Baccalaureate Program will be given credit for courses at UNL according to the guidelines established by each academic unit. Contact the department office for specific course information.

Course Level Requirements

Upper-Level Requirement: Thirty of the 120 semester hours of credit must be in courses numbered above 299.

Residency

Students must meet either of the following residency qualifications:

At least 30 of the last 36 hours of credit must be registered for and completed while enrolled at UNL.
A total of 90 credits must be registered for and completed while enrolled at UNL.

Thirty semester hours earned through On-line and Distance Education courses at UNL may be applied toward a degree from the College.

Credit earned during education abroad may be used toward degree requirements if students participate in prior approved programs and register through UNL. Credit awarded from an institution other than UNL will be subject to transfer credit and residency rules.

DEGREES & MAJORS

Areas offering Bachelor of Arts degree:

Art

Art History

Dance

Interdisciplinary Studies

Music

Theatre–Directing and Management

Theatre–Performance

Areas offering Bachelor of Fine Arts degree:

Art

Theatre–Design/Technical Production

Theatre–Film and New Media

Area offering Bachelor of Music degree:

Music

Area offering Bachelor of Music Education degree:

Music Education

MINORS & AREAS OF SPECIALIZATIONS OFFERED

Art

Art History

Dance

Music

Music Technology

Theatre

GRADUATE STUDENT INFORMATION

OTHER

College Scholarships and Student Support

Donors have provided a limited number of scholarships that are reserved for students in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts. Students interested in applying for one of these awards may obtain information from departmental chairpersons or from the Office of Scholarships and Financial Aid.

Undergraduate and graduate majors in the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts may qualify for financial support through three programs funded by the Hixson-Lied Endowment, including Student International Study Support, Student Domestic Study Support, Student Scholarly and Creative Activity, and the Undergraduate Creative Research Grant. Applications and deadline information for all grants are available on the College website.

Grading Appeals

A student who feels that he/she has been unfairly graded may take the following sequential steps:

1. Talk with the instructor concerned. Most problems are resolved at this point.

2. Talk to the instructor’s department chairperson.

3. Take the case to the Grading Appeal Committee of the department concerned. The Committee should be contacted through the department chairperson.

4. Take the case to the College Grading Appeals Committee by contacting the Dean’s Office, 102 Woods Art Building.

Application for a Degree

Students should access their Degree Audit via MyRED at least once each term to review degree requirements and progress toward graduation. It is the student’s responsibility to make sure their Degree Audit accurately reflects their current College and program of study

Students are expected to develop a clear understanding of degree requirements and to plan their course of study with a College adviser. Students who require clarification of outstanding degree requirements or believe their Degree Audit has errors or omissions should visit with an adviser promptly. It is important that these matters are resolved as soon as practicable to avoid a delay in graduation.

Each student must submit an Application for Graduation plus $25.00 check or cash fee for each degree to be received to the Office of the University Registrar by:

The last Friday in January for May graduation
The last Friday in June for August graduation
The last Friday in September for December graduation

An electronic Application for Graduation and payment is available via MyRED. Those students choosing to apply for graduation in person may visit the Office of the University Registrar, 107 Canfield Administration Building. Applications for Graduation submitted in person or by mail must be accompanied by payment. Failure to submit a timely Application for Graduation may preclude the awarding of a degree in the intended term.

Public Affairs & Community Service

DESCRIPTION

Administered by the University of Nebraska at Omaha

John Bartle, Ph.D., Dean

The College of Public Affairs and Community Service (CPACS) on the Lincoln campus offers all undergraduate course work required for the bachelor of science degree in criminology and criminal justice. A minor in criminology and criminal justice is also offered in Lincoln. The College also offers all course work for a certificate or minor in gerontology on the Lincoln campus.

ADMISSION

College Admission

Students who have been admitted to the University may apply for entrance to the College of Public Affairs and Community Service during initial registration by indicating their preference in the appropriate place on the University Application for Admission form.

Students who wish to transfer into the College from another institution or one of the schools or colleges within the University must request permission from the Dean’s Office and the department or school offering the student’s intended major. A minimum cumulative grade point average (GPA) of 2.5 is required to transfer into the College.

Students who wish to readmit to the College must also have a minimum 2.5 cumulative GPA.

Admission Deficiencies/Removal of Deficiencies

Students with high school admission deficiencies that have been admitted to UNL may enter the College of Public Affairs and Community Service but must remove any deficiencies according to University policy.

ADVISING

Academic Advising

Students are responsible for knowing and completing all requirements of their chosen degree program. The aim and purpose of academic advising is to assist students in career planning, meeting the requirements of the degree program and in interpreting College policy regarding academic requirements.

Students should see an adviser whenever questions arise concerning their academic programs. Students are encouraged to seek advisement with their assigned academic adviser at least two times per year, particularly, when registering for the senior year.

ACADEMIC PROGRAMS & POLICIES

Course Exclusions and Restrictions

Credit earned in courses below the 100 level may not be applied toward the degree offered by the College of Public Affairs and Community Service.

Any restrictions noted specifically by departments. Credit towards the degree may be earned in only one course, including honors sections, from each group of courses listed below:

BIOS 313 or BIOS 314

CHEM 105, CHEM 109, CHEM 111, CHEM 113, CHEM 195

CHEM 116 or CHEM 221

CHEM 251 and more than 1 cr of CHEM 263

CHEM 471 or CHEM 481

CSCE 252A or CSCE 155N

CSCE 252A or ELEC 121

CSCE 340 or CSCE 480

ECON 210 or ECON 211 & ECON 212

ECON 215, CRIM 300, EDPS 459 or STAT 218 (was STAT 180)

FREN 201 & FREN 202, or FREN 210

GEOL 100 or GEOL 101 or GEOL 101H

GEOL 103 or GEOL 105

GERM 201 & GERM 202, or GERM 210

GREK 102 or GREK 151

LATN 102 or LATN 201

MATH 101 and/or MATH 102 or MATH 103

MATH 104 or MATH 106

MATH 200 or MATH 300

MATH 201 or MATH 301

MATH 340 or MECH 480

PHYS 141 or PHYS 151

PHYS 151 or MSYM 109

SOCI 205 or CRIM 251

SOCI 311 or CRIM 337

SOCI 474 or CRIM 413

SPAN 201 & SPAN 202, or SPAN 210

Credit Rules

Credit by Examination

The student should refer all questions concerning the acceptability of credits earned in programs such as Cooperative Education and Credit by Examination to the department in which enrolled.

Dual Degrees

A student who wishes to meet the requirements for two baccalaureate degrees must complete a minimum of 30 additional semester hours at the University beyond the first degree in order to be awarded a second degree.

Student Recognition

Dean’s List

Students enrolled in the College of Public Affairs and Community Service who maintain a grade point average of 3.5 or better while carrying 12 graded hours or more will earn the distinction of being placed on the Dean’s Honor List at the end of each semester.

Degrees with Honors

The baccalaureate degrees with honors are awarded as follows:

1. To all graduates whose scholastic average for their entire university career and at NU is 3.51 or above, but below 3.63, the degree cum laude.

2. To all graduates whose scholastic average for their entire university career and at NU is 3.63 or above, but below 3.87, the degree magna cum laude.

3. To all graduates whose scholastic average for their entire university career and at NU is 3.87 or above, the degree summa cum laude.

To qualify for honors, a student must have earned at least 60 semester hours within the University of Nebraska system, 30 hours of which must be completed at the University of Nebraska at Omaha and/or the University of Nebraska-Lincoln and in which letter grades of “A,” “B,” “C,” or “D” are received. Grades awarded in all courses taken at all colleges and universities attended are included in computing the Grade Point Average (GPA) for determining eligibility for honors. It should be noted that the GPA included in the student grade reports issued by the Registrar’s Office reflects only courses taken at UNO, UNL, UNMC and UNK.

Senior Check/Degree Audit

During the second semester of their junior year, or after completing approximately 89 hours, students should apply for an audit of their academic records to be sure that all requirements will be met before the anticipated date of graduation. Criminology and criminal justice majors may request the audit at the CPACS Office, 310 Nebraska Hall.

Criminology and criminal justice majors must also file an application for graduation at Graduation Services, 109 Canfield Administration Building, either just prior to or early in the semester they intend to graduate. Failure to meet the published deadline may delay graduation until the next semester.

BULLETIN TO USE

Choice of Catalog Policy

A student registering in the College of Public Affairs and Community Service for the first time may, except for limitations described below, complete work for the degree according to the requirements of 1) the catalog in effect the year the student enters CPACS, or 2) the catalog current at the time the student applies for the degree.

Students entering the College for the first time in the summer will be subject to the catalog for the academic year immediately following.

Students formerly in a CPACS program who drop out of the College for one year must complete requirements of the catalog current at the time of readmission.

Failure to complete the requirements for the degree within seven years after the date the student first enters the College will subject the student to graduation under the requirements of a later catalog to be approved by the Dean.

The College reserves the right to institute and make effective, after due notice, during the course of a student’s work toward a degree, any new ruling which may be necessary for the general good of the College and to substitute courses currently offered for those no longer offered.

COLLEGE DEGREE REQUIREMENTS

Achievement-Centered Education (ACE)

All CPACS students on the Lincoln campus must fulfill the Achievement-Centered Education (ACE) requirements. The 30-hour ACE requirement will include a minimum of 3 hours of approved course work in each of the 10 designated Achievement-Centered Education (ACE) student learning outcome areas which can be viewed at http://ace.unl.edu. Students will be provided a list of courses they can select from to meet each of the 10 ACE Student Learning Outcomes.

Foreign Languages/Language Requirement

Students in the College of Public Affairs and Community Service who have completed the University of Nebraska high school admission requirement of two years in the same language will not be required to complete additional language for their degree.

Minimum Hours Required for Graduation

Each candidate must present a total of at least 120 semester hours of college credit to meet graduation requirements.

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

A minimum grade of at least C- must be earned in all required courses within the major, unless a higher grade is designated by the department/school. Completion of a course within the major with a grade below a C- will not be considered as having fulfilled prerequisite requirements for additional courses taken in the major field of study. A higher grade may be designated by the department/school.

Pass/No Pass Limits

See individual school/department limitations regarding Pass/No Pass.

GPA Requirements

Each candidate for the degree must attain a cumulative grade point average of at least 2.0. A minimum grade of at least C- must be earned in all required courses within the major, unless a higher grade is designated by the department/school. All grades reported by the faculty to the registrar become a part of the student’s permanent record and are included in the computation of the grade point average, even though some of these grades may be for work done in excess of the 120 hours required for graduation.

Transfer Credit Rules

The transfer of D grades in non-major courses are accepted only from within the University of Nebraska system. Students from other institutions must present a grade of C- or above for all course work.

Generally, hours earned at an accredited college are accepted by the University, however, the college will evaluate all hours submitted for transfer to determine applicability toward the degree. A maximum of 64 hours may be transferred from a two-year college and a maximum of 90 hours from a four-year institution.

Course Level Requirements (Hour Requirement 300+)

Individual departments/schools should be consulted for the minimum number of upper division hours required.

Residency

Thirty of the last 36 hours required for the degree must be registered for and carried within the University of Nebraska system.

Extended Education and Independent Study Rules

Individual schools/departments should be consulted for rules regarding extended education and independent study credit applicable to majors or minors.

DEGREES & MAJORS

Bachelor of Science in Criminology and Criminal Justice (BSCCJ)

Although the bachelor of science in criminology and criminal justice degree can be earned in its entirety on the Lincoln campus, the degree is granted by the University of Nebraska at Omaha.

MINORS & AREAS OF SPECIALIZATIONS OFFERED

Minor in Criminology and Criminal Justice

The requirements to earn a minor in criminology and criminal justice will consist of a minimum of 18 credit hours to include CRIM 101 Survey of Criminal Justice (3 cr), a minimum of two of the three CRIM 203 Police and Society, CRIM 211 The Criminal Court System, CRIM 221 Survey of Corrections (6 cr), and a minimum of 9 credit hours of upper level (300/400) criminology and criminal justice courses (excluding CRIM 300 Applied Statistics). An overall C average in courses applied to the minor is required and all courses must be taken for a letter grade (not Pass/No Pass). In addition, all 9 credit hours of upper division course work must be taken in residence at the University of Nebraska.

Minor or Certificate in Gerontology

Undergraduates may earn a certificate or minor in gerontology. The certificate consists of 15 hours of specified course work plus a one-semester practicum. The minor is comprised of 18 hours of course work. Although an undergraduate major in gerontology is not offered on the UNL campus, the certificate program may be used as a minor or concentration within several degree programs earned through other University departments.

Courses that meet the gerontology requirement are taught by gerontology department faculty as well as related faculty in other UNL and UNO departments. Students should consult the Department of Gerontology for the appropriate selection of courses.

Application materials for admission to the Gerontology Certificate Program can be obtained either from the Department office, 310 Nebraska Hall (402-472-0754); or CPACS Building 211 on the Omaha campus (402-554-2272), or at http://www.unomaha.edu/gero.

GRADUATE STUDENT INFORMATION

The College of Public Affairs and Community Service offers graduate programs in Criminology and Criminal Justice, Gerontology, Social Work, and Public Administration. Refer to the College of Public Affairs and Community Service at the University of Nebraska at Omaha website (http://cpacs.unomaha.edu) for information on these graduate programs.

OTHER

Grade Appeals Procedure

Students who wish to appeal a grade which they feel was capriciously or prejudicially given shall first discuss the matter with the instructor within 30 days of the final course grade being posted. If the matter is not resolved, the student must meet with the department/school chairperson. If a satisfactory agreement cannot be reached, the student must appeal, in writing, to the department/school curriculum committee. If a satisfactory agreement cannot be reached, the student may submit a written appeal to the Office of the Dean within 20 working days of the exhaustion of the departmental procedures.

The Committee on Academic Standards and Curriculum for the College of Public Affairs and Community Service is the official body for handling the appeal.

In the event that the instructor is unavailable for handling a grade complaint, the student will meet with the Department Chair/School Director and the Dean to determine the most appropriate course of action agreeable to all parties.